<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bjj | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/bjj/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-20T19:51:17-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Funny Thing About Quitting]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/10/the-funny-thing-about-quitting/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-10T20:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/10/the-funny-thing-about-quitting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We were shooting the shit in the gym on Thursday, when the subject of wasted memberships came up.  As I&rsquo;m sure is common
in any other type of service with a monthly membership, we apparently have a fair amount of people who pay for an
unlimited pass but only show up once every two weeks or so.  Or even people who pay for a membership and just don&rsquo;t show
up at all.  This isn&rsquo;t such a big deal at a place where the monthly fee is $10, but for BJJ gyms in metropolitan areas,
the costs tend to fall somewhere between $100-$200 / month.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a pretty significant amount of money.  So why would people spend it for a service they&rsquo;re not bothering to use?
Sure, there&rsquo;s a &ldquo;one year&rdquo; contract for the gym, but owners tend to be understanding most of the time, and the effort in
canceling that is pretty trivial.  I think the real barrier is in the way people think about quitting.</p>

<p>When we pick up a hobby and things get serious, it starts working its way into our definitions of ourselves.  This is
especially true for something like jiu jitsu, which involves a heavy investment and intrinsically comes with rewards
like &ldquo;higher self confidence&rdquo;, but it also applies to anything from learning a new language to picking up an instrument
to experimenting with painting.</p>

<p>So it&rsquo;s only natural that when life starts getting in the way, we cling onto that image.  Maybe we go from every day to
only a few times a week.  Then once a week.  Then once a month.  Then <em>&ldquo;Oh yeah, I&rsquo;m learning to speak Spanish, but
it&rsquo;s been a few months since I&rsquo;ve had the chance to practice&hellip;&rdquo;</em>  But we rarely ever cross the threshold into
consciously declaring that we&rsquo;ve quit.  Are you still really playing the guitar if it&rsquo;s been six months since you&rsquo;ve
touched it?  One year?  Three?</p>

<p>Canceling a membership requires the conscious decision that <em>yes, I&rsquo;ve quit</em>.  But we never really seem to cross that
point.  It&rsquo;s always one rationalization after another.  Perhaps if we&rsquo;re could be more honest with ourselves, we could
save a lot of the resources that that costs us, whether that be a monthly membership fee that could be better put
towards something else, or the energy and creativity spent in thinking up justifications for ourselves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Belt!]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/08/new-belt/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-08T21:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/08/new-belt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Normally I try to keep the &ldquo;dear diary&rdquo; factor on the blog low.  But in all the bustle of settling back into the east
coast with a new work arrangement, I all but forgot about the whole blogging thing until roughly 2 minutes ago.  So if
you&rsquo;re one of the ones who reads this for what little informational value I manage to provide, or are otherwise
uninterested in participating in this rare bout of masturbatory self-congratulations, here&rsquo;s your cue.</p>

<p>Still here?  So&hellip;  I got my blue belt in BJJ recently.  For anyone unfamiliar, it&rsquo;s basically the &ldquo;hurrah, you&rsquo;re no
longer a rookie&rdquo; rank, and in all seriousness this is one of my prouder moments.  Why?  Because of all my regular
activities, BJJ is the one where I have absolutely no talent whatsoever.  Seriously.  It took me a solid 2 years to get
to this point, and every day of that was spent with the mat being wiped by my face.  Ask anyone at the gym: I still get
rag-dolled on a regular basis.</p>

<p>Now, as a software developer (and all-around lazy nerd) I have a propensity to approach most problems by a) finding an
easier way to do it, b) deciding it&rsquo;s not worth the time, or c) see (a).  It&rsquo;s an approach that works for software, for
games, and probably for most challenges you&rsquo;re likely to find in the first world.  But it&rsquo;s great having proof that
sometimes you just have to show up and grind through and that&rsquo;s the only way to improve.  It&rsquo;s a reminder that
surprisingly often, the only actual obstacle is just you being a giant chicken and unwilling to leave your comfort zone.</p>

<p>So, as the kid who couldn&rsquo;t do a single push-up and ran a 13 minute mile in school, I&rsquo;d like to give myself a pat on the
back for managing to get this far.  And despite all the split lips, swollen fingers, and sprained joints, I sure hope I
get a lot farther in the future.</p>

<p>Oh, and&hellip;  I kind of lied about the lack of material.  I had another 52-weeks post lined up, but the experiment failed
horribly.  I&rsquo;m just buying time so I can do a second iteration and save SOME face, so&hellip;  Look forward to that one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
