<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-16T15:57:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[asciinema]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/16/asciinema/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-16T15:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/16/asciinema</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was tooling around the other day and discovered a service called <a href="https://asciinema.org">asciinema</a> which provides
terminalcasts&mdash;essentially, &ldquo;screencasts&rdquo; with terminal I/O.  This is awesome for a few reasons.</p>

<p>From a content consumer&rsquo;s standpoint, it&rsquo;s often hard to follow a blog post that&rsquo;s trying to outline a command line tip,
or a vim tip, for the simple fact that the static nature of writing alone isn&rsquo;t optimal for showing the flow between
&ldquo;steps&rdquo; (commands, keystrokes, what have you) and &ldquo;output&rdquo; (what you&rsquo;re supposed to see after executing commands).
Having a dynamic format for demos helps with this greatly.  Sure, there are screencasts, but that involves dealing with
videos and their associated heavy Flash Player bullshit.  asciinema is rendered with just bits of html and js.</p>

<p>From a wannabe content producer&rsquo;s standpoint&hellip;  Writing is <em>hard</em>.  Writing while crafting appropriate examples is
harder.  Doing all that while struggling with capturing the nature of the examples in plain text?  No thanks.
Again&mdash;Yes, there is the option of screencasts, but those are painful to set up.  Screencasts means worrying about
things like capturing software, background audio, What Tab Do I Have Open In My Browser, and Will Video Compression
Screw My Text Legibility.  As a consummately lazy person who only wants to do short self-contained clips for now&hellip;
That&rsquo;s way too big of a barrier.  asciinema is easy&mdash;Just install, then <code>asciinema rec</code> from the terminal and <code>&lt;CTRL-D&gt;</code>
to exit and upload.</p>

<p>And embedding takes 2 seconds&mdash;Check it!</p>

<script type="text/javascript" src="https://asciinema.org/a/10785.js" id="asciicast-10785" async></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['MURICA - Ribs]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/11/murica-ribs/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-11T21:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/11/murica-ribs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-NJP5Mrc/0/L/DSC_3131-L.jpg"></p>

<p>It is one of my greatest regrets as a Super Manly-Man that my current living situation is prohibitive against the
construction of fire pits, or even the ownership of so much as a grill.  And it is a travesty that on the Fourth of
July&mdash;one of the meatiest holidays of the meatiest of countries (&lsquo;MURICAAAAA)&mdash;I had to settle for a measly oven for my
ribs.  But alas, one must make do.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As far as ribs done in a scrawny house-oven go, these were actually pretty good; I basically stole the entire thing
wholesale from an episode of Good Eats.  While I wouldn&rsquo;t say braised ribs inspire me to go out and slay bears, I&rsquo;d say
all in all it could have turned out a lot worse.</p>

<h2>Meat</h2>

<ul>
<li>2 racks of ribs</li>
</ul>


<h2>Spice Rub</h2>

<ul>
<li>8 parts (I used a &frac14; cup per &ldquo;part&rdquo;) brown sugar</li>
<li>3 parts kosher salt (halve that if you insist on using table salt, you heathen)</li>
<li>1 part Chili P</li>
<li>1 part &ldquo;everything else&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<h2>Everything Else</h2>

<p>A great big mix of&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li>Old Bay</li>
<li>Dried Thyme</li>
<li>Cayenne Pepper</li>
<li>Black Pepper</li>
<li>Onion Powder</li>
</ul>


<h2>Braising Liquid</h2>

<ul>
<li>1 cup white while</li>
<li>2 Tb white wine vinegar</li>
<li>A few cloves of garlic, crushed</li>
<li>drizzle of honey</li>
</ul>


<p>Combine everything in the Spice Rub and make sure to mix well.  I ended up mixing and storing it in a few Ball jars,
since this stuff will keep forever.  Cover the ribs in it.  Seriously, don&rsquo;t be shy with the spice either&mdash;what are you,
a communist?</p>

<p>After the ribs are completely coated, wrap them in aluminum foil.  First seal up the foil lengthwise, then roll up the
ends to make a neat little package.  If you&rsquo;re paranoid like me, you can double-layer the foil.  Stick this in the
fridge overnight.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-J847KwB/0/L/DSC_3069-L.jpg"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-4MR872V/0/L/DSC_3074-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Several beers and a good night&rsquo;s sleep later, wake up and groggily pre-heat your oven to 225F.  Put everything for the
Braising Liquid into a saucepan, and bring to a simmer.  Remove the ribs, unroll one of the foil ends, and dump the
braising liquid into the foil packages.  It&rsquo;s kind of like feeding a pet, if your pet were aluminum and you were
planning on eating its insides.</p>

<p>Place everything onto a metal tray, and the tray into the oven.  Wait for 2 &frac12; to 3 hours, then remove and unwrap the
ribs.  Drain the braising liquid into a saucepan.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-N6TLMVp/0/L/DSC_3079-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Reduce the liquid in the pan until it reaches a sauce-like consistency.  We&rsquo;re talking about well past the french
&ldquo;spoon-back-coating&rdquo; level; look for something closer to a thick glaze.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-ZVPCzzC/0/L/DSC_3086-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Slather the sauce onto the ribs, then stick them under a broiler for a few minutes.  Marvel at the excellent color and
sizzling goodness.</p>

<p>Slice, cover with more sauce, and garnish with copious amounts of Independence.  Potato salad might also work.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-qX9g7j3/0/L/DSC_3138-L.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Caramelized Lemongrass Chicken]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/03/caramelized-lemongrass-chicken/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T15:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/03/caramelized-lemongrass-chicken</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-FBL6Qgb/0/L/DSC_3055-L.jpg"></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t make this as often as I should, since to be honest prepping lemongrass is kind of a pain even with a food
processor.  But when I do make the effort, it&rsquo;s totally worth it.  The refreshing flavors of lemongrass play really well
with the rich, strong flavors of caramel and chicken.  Plus, who doesn&rsquo;t like fish sauce?  Make sure to use the brand
with the crabs, though; otherwise, what&rsquo;s the point?</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>1 lb boneless chicken thighs</li>
<li>4 stalks of lemongrass</li>
<li>1 yellow onion, chopped</li>
<li>2 Tbs sugar, 2 Tbs high heat oil</li>
<li>2 tsp fish sauce</li>
<li>4 cloves minced garlic</li>
<li>cilantro</li>
<li>scallions</li>
<li>whole chilies</li>
<li>salt, pepper</li>
</ul>


<p>Start off with prepping the lemongrass.  Cut the bottoms off the stalks as well as the tops, right where they start
turning dark green.  Bash them a few times with the back of your knife (or a brick, I guess), and slice into thin rings.
Then run your knife through the thin rings a few times to end up with a fine mince.  This is probably the most painful
and labor-intensive part of this entire dish, but it&rsquo;s important.  Bruising and chopping the lemongrass in this way
is essential to releasing the flavor, but at the same time nobody wants to pick big pieces of lemongrass out of their
teeth.  For the lazy/economical among us, I&rsquo;m sure a few pulses in the food processor would also work.  I&rsquo;ve also been
told you can buy pulverized lemongrass frozen, but&hellip;  Come on.  If you&rsquo;re reading this blog, you obviously have the
time to do some proper prep.</p>

<p>Cut the chicken thighs into small &frac12; to 1-inch cubes.  If the thighs came with skin, great; keep it, it helps with
flavor.  If not, that&rsquo;s alright too I suppose.  Personally, I just buy thighs with bone and skin on, and just debone
myself.  And as with most of these types of dishes, I&rsquo;m morally obligated to note that trying to substitute chicken
breast here is a capital offense.  Thighs just have so much more flavor.</p>

<p>Season the chicken with salt, pepper, and a few tablespoons of the chopped lemongrass, and set it aside for a few
minutes.  In the meantime, heat the oil in a large skillet over medium-high heat until it&rsquo;s shimmery and just about to
smoke.  Add the sugar, which should melt with some stirring after a minute or two.  Keep stirring, and wait for the
sugar syrup to turn brown and caramel-y.  At no point should the mixture smoke: If it does, the pan&rsquo;s gotten too hot,
and should be taken off the heat for a bit.</p>

<p>Stir in the rest of the chopped lemongrass, the onion, and the garlic, and fry for a few minutes.  Crank the heat all
the way up and throw in the chicken.  After a minute, throw in the chilies, and keep cooking until the chicken&rsquo;s done.
Take the pan off the heat, then add the fish sauce.  (Hint: Make sure to save the fish sauce for when the high heat
cooking is done, or else it&rsquo;ll smell up the joint.)  Finish with chopped scallions and chopped cilantro.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-FHVvjDS/0/L/DSC_3045-L.jpg"></p>

<p>With a solid bowl of white rice, this amount of chicken is probably good for serving about 3-4 people, depending on
appetite needs and size.  For this particular run, I ended up with a bowl of vermicelli, with julienned cucumbers and
mint on the side.  Topped with more fish sauce.  Having no exposure to any sort of Vietnamese home culture, I can&rsquo;t
really speak to this dish&rsquo;s authenticity or anything like that.  I mean, I&rsquo;m sure some Vietnamese food icon is rolling
in their grave over my use of fish sauce and vermicelli, but at least it&rsquo;s delicious.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-5CjWGbk/0/L/DSC_3063-L.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bracket Expansion in the Shell]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/bracket-expansion-in-the-shell/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T18:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/bracket-expansion-in-the-shell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick post to show of a neat little trick for those who are more command-line-driven: bracket expansion.</p>

<p>Basically, bracket expansion means that <code>some-string-called-{x,y}-here</code> desugars in the shell to
<code>some-string-called-x-here some-string-called-y-here</code>.  This is especially useful if, say, you&rsquo;re in a Java-like
directory structure and you accidentally placed your source class in your test folder, and you need to move it back:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="c"># desugars into mv src/test/java/com/foobar/app/Class.java src/main/java/com/foobar/app/Class.java</span>
</span><span class='line'>mv src/<span class="o">{</span><span class="nb">test</span>,main<span class="o">}</span>/java/com/foobar/app/Class.java
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Or if you&rsquo;ve already committed to source control, this also works quite nicely with <code>git mv</code>.  Another nice example from
recent memory is, say, if you were cleaning up some directories nested by date and wanted to only wipe a few months:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>rm /posts/2014/<span class="o">{</span>01,03,06,07<span class="o">}</span>/*.html
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Anyway, just a quick little post for a neat little trick.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Fuck It Friday" - Weeks 12 + 13, Street Food + Potatoes]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/fuck-it-its-friday-weeks-12-13/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T17:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/fuck-it-its-friday-weeks-12-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-5WQTNMH/0/L/DSC_3030-L.jpg"></p>

<p>This <em>was</em> going to be a big ol&#8217; fancy affair.  I set out to knock out two weeks&#8217; worth of challenges at once, and take
advantage of some sweet, sweet morels at the market.  Unfortunately, the potatoes decided to be uncooperative, so here
we are.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The original idea was to make curried fried clams as the &ldquo;street food&rdquo; portion of the challenge; luckily that turned out
pretty well.  I first laced some flour with turmeric, cumin, garam masala, cayenne, and salt, then soaked some minced
clams in milk.  A few minutes in some 350-degree oil later, voila!  One note though: rest them in parchment paper or a
mesh rack; paper towels will just end up steaming them as they cool, ruining the crunchy texture.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-7Rn3Gpg/0/L/DSC_3023-L.jpg"></p>

<p>While the curryish flavors got a bit overwhelmed by the tartar sauce, I like to think that it provided a bit more depth
to the flavor.  Placebo effect, anyone?</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s where things get a bit dicey.  The original plan was to slice up a bunch of potatoes and stack them, then form a
mini-cake by surrounding it with a potato-morel &ldquo;icing&rdquo;.  However, I decided to be a dunce and add some morel-induced
cream, which ended up turning the potato-morel combo into more of a wet puree than a potato cake.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-kc4j69J/0/L/DSC_3025-L.jpg"></p>

<p>To salvage the situation, I ended up pan-frying the slices and combining them with the puree, making something like a
mutated gratin dauphinois.</p>

<p>At this point, I had given up all delusions of pretentious grandeur and decided, &ldquo;Fuck it, it&rsquo;s Friday&rdquo;.  Thus, I turned the
entire thing on its head, going from <em>frou-frou potato cake</em> to <em>giant plate of stuff</em> with cole slaw and extra tartar
sauce.  All things considered, it could have turned out much worse; at least it was still delicious, and that&rsquo;s what
really counts.  And I suppose the &ldquo;pile of food&rdquo; format is more appropriate for the street food theme anyway.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-vjNkfpR/0/L/DSC_3035-L.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello, Hardware World!]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/14/hello-hardware-world/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-14T16:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/14/hello-hardware-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, one of our tech leads at work previewed <a href="https://github.com/ogrodnek/analog-metrics-talk">a talk</a> that he&rsquo;s
planning to give on analog metrics for the upcoming Strange Loop conference.  I&rsquo;ve always wanted to play with
microcontrollers, and this really gave me a kick in the pants to get started.  Since I had a bit of amazon credit lying
around, I decided to buy an arduino starter kit with all sorts of buttons, lights, and doo-dads, but not enough power to
actually fry anything (I hope).  I still can&rsquo;t tell my head from my ass, but so far I can make a button turn on an LED.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Camera-Awesome-Photos/i-h59QFDb/0/L/CA_06051420063663-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Next step: world domination!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Follow The Honey]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/05/follow-the-honey/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-05T20:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/05/follow-the-honey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-kDb523C/0/L/DSC_2978-L.jpg"></p>

<p>A few weeks ago I was dragged somewhat skeptically to a honey store.  Yep, that&rsquo;s right&mdash;a honey store.  A store, that&rsquo;s
dedicated to honey.  I know.  Strange as it may sound, it&rsquo;s actually a thing.  But after my (thus far only) trip,
I&rsquo;m a convert.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The storefront is very cozy, nestled within the basement of a building in Harvard Square.  The inside is all amber and,
to the surprise of absolutely nobody, decorated with various bee-related paraphernalia&mdash;Everything from cards with bees
to beeswax candles.  Why couldn&rsquo;t I have known about this place back when we were doing
<a href="http://alexkuang.com/blog/2010/10/01/caneles-bordelais/">caneles</a>?  The first attempts with copper molds all but
required beeswax; hell, I still prefer that to cooking spray.  But I digress.</p>

<p>The workers were all super happy and friendly.  I wonder if it was the general almost-hippie peaceful vibe of the
interior, but they almost seemed <em>too</em> happy.  As in I was almost tempted to ask for the, ahem, &ldquo;special&rdquo; honey, so to
speak.  In any case, they were all perfectly pleasant and helpful and eager to offer samples from the honey bar.  Did
I mention they have a honey bar?  It&rsquo;s absolutely bizarre.  The first question I was asked was &ldquo;what flavors do you like
in your honey?&rdquo;  <em>I have no idea, are you kidding me?  I&rsquo;ve only had the kind in the bear bottles.</em></p>

<p>I ended up trying a few varieties ranging from the savory and spicy to the sweet and fruity.  And it&rsquo;s like coffee&mdash;Once
you have the real stuff, you don&rsquo;t want to go back unless you have no other choice.  For my part, I walked out with
nearly 3 digits&#8217; worth of merch.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-xBT3tP7/0/L/DSC_2989-L.jpg"></p>

<p>The most interesting is probably the Hawaiian honey, which is from bees gathering from flowers off the side of volcanos
in Hawaii.  If that sounds exotic, don&rsquo;t worry&mdash;It&rsquo;s got a correspondingly exotic price tag, about 30-some dollars for 8
oz (226g).  I bought two jars: one was Kiawe honey infused separately with lilikoi flowers, and one uninfused Macadamia
honey.  The former actually came in semi-solid form (common for raw honey) and packed a sharp passion fruit flavor.  The
latter was a more &ldquo;typical&rdquo; liquid texture, and rosey gold with a mild nutty flavor.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-RqWvFwQ/0/L/DSC_2990-L.jpg"></p>

<p>In addition to these, I also walked out with two jars of honey gathered from Oaxaca, Mexico.  Oaxaca&rsquo;s a great
region for food agriculture&mdash;Some pretty good coffee comes out of there as well.  This honey was very savory, almost
spicey, and a dark maple-syrupy color.  It was also very reasonably priced, something like $12-13 for I would guess 12oz
out of the keg.  Oh, did I mention there were kegs?  Honey, <em>on tap</em>.  Whodaknownit?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-7QKxJ2M/0/L/DSC_2977-L.jpg"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-hBBmCWs/0/L/DSC_2991-L.jpg"></p>

<p>If it isn&rsquo;t obvious by now, I&rsquo;d recommend anyone in the area to stop by at least once, regardless of inherent interest
in bees and honey.  If nothing else there are very nice people giving out free samples, and who knows?  Maybe just a few
tastes will be enough.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oysters with Lemon Pearls - Week 11 Molecular]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/27/oysters-with-lemon-pearls-week-11-molecular/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-27T17:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/27/oysters-with-lemon-pearls-week-11-molecular</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-5NhtLD4/0/L/DSC_2972-L.jpg"></p>

<p>I was really looking forward to the Molecular theme, since I&rsquo;d been itching to play with some of this newfangled
Modernist Cuisine stuff for a while now.  So I went ahead and ordered a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Modernist-Pantry-Spherification-Kit/dp/B008657GS0/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1401210725&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=spherification+kit">spherification kit</a>
from amazon, and came up with the idea of pairing spheres with oysters.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The kit came with fairly straightforward instructions, so I just followed those.  For my liquid base I used lemonade
mixed with lemon juice for acidity.  I added 2 grams of sodium citrate, since the kit recommended that for potentially
acidic solutions.</p>

<p>The spheres came together fairly well, though it was pretty slow going at first.  I&rsquo;m also displeased that the syringe
included with the kit is one use only&hellip;</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-p99X433/0/L/DSC_2968-L.jpg"></p>

<p>The spheres look good, but I think that&rsquo;s about all that I can say about them positively.  Taste-wise, they were
slightly rubbery and the insides were way too viscous&mdash;Closer to maple syrup than juice.  Maybe it was the
disappointment from expecting something closer to the &ldquo;popping boba&rdquo; found in bubble tea/frozen yogurt, but overall I
just found the texture unpleasant.  In addition, the alginate stifled the acidity in the lemon and left a funny taste in
my mouth, making the pearls taste basically like jello filled with slightly off sugar syrup.</p>

<p>All in all, I would have been better served making plain old lemon jello with the oysters, which is what I&rsquo;ve done in
the past.  It&rsquo;s possible that I did something terribly wrong despite my self-perceived precision, or perhaps this kit
just didn&rsquo;t include the right substances for this set of circumstances.  Half the instructions seemed to exist for
upselling, e.g., &ldquo;buy our slotted spoon!&rdquo;, &ldquo;buy our PH meter!&rdquo;</p>

<p>Either way, this was a huge disappointment and I don&rsquo;t see myself trying again any time soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Preferred Dark Souls I]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/23/why-i-preferred-dark-souls-i/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-23T21:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/23/why-i-preferred-dark-souls-i</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dark Souls 2 is a great game.  Let&rsquo;s get that out of the way.  I&rsquo;ve logged low 3 digits in hours of gameplay, and made
it through the game multiple times.  The combat system is tuned, there&rsquo;s a ton of content, and multiplayer is pretty fun
(or at least, it was at the levels I hung around).  But I still prefer the original, and Demon&rsquo;s Souls, over it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The biggest turn-off in DS2 was the shift in design goals.  The dripping atmosphere and rich world were always the
primary draws in the franchise, and the difficulty took a back seat (relatively speaking) as a tool to work towards that
goal.  In DS2, it felt more like the developers&#8217; primary goal was &ldquo;HOW CAN WE MAKE THIS HARDER?&rdquo;  This was evidenced in
the way combat shifted towards the many-vs-one paradigm; not only with regular enemies, but with the bosses as well.
The Skeleton Lords, the Dragon Knights, the Looking Glass Knight, Twin Pursuers, Ruin Sentinels&hellip;  &ldquo;How can we make
this harder?  Let&rsquo;s just put more enemies in.&rdquo;  Not only is the repetition insulting, aiming for &ldquo;hard&rdquo; is just
completely missing the point.</p>

<p>Take the DS1 fight with Artorias.  It&rsquo;s such a fan favorite not only because it was ridiculously hard, but because the
entire fight was steeped in the world&rsquo;s lore.  After fighting Sif, going through the Abyss, and reading bits and pieces
from the game&rsquo;s NPCs about the fall of Artorias the Abysswalker, his charge towards the player holds a gravity that
couldn&rsquo;t be matched by even 20 Pursuers.  Seriously, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ctW277Kpcv0">check it</a>.</p>

<p>Speaking of the lore, that&rsquo;s another big point of contention with me.  I feel like there&rsquo;s a big difference between lore
and plot.  Lore is the background of the world.  It&rsquo;s the story behind each NPC, each item, each location, and it&rsquo;s
great for it to be subtle and nebulous.  A richly built, subtly woven world gives the player an opportunity to explore
and really dive into the atmosphere of everything.</p>

<p>The plot, however, is simply the thread of the story that drives the player&rsquo;s main progression, and needs to be very
clear cut.  Another concrete example, as spoiler-free as possible: In DS1, the player embarks on a quest to re-light the
first flame on the request of a dying man in the asylum.  On his quest to do that, he awakens a primordial serpent, and
the progression from there differs, ending with the player either re-kindling the first flame or leaving it to die.  The
story is pretty straightforward there, and at any given point you&rsquo;re pretty clear about the motivations of your
character.</p>

<p>In contrast, DS2 opens up with something about a curse in Drangleic and how you must go there, <strong>only to
never revisit the topic</strong>.  No seriously, what the hell is that?  They make this whole deal with the old ladies about
the curse of Drangleic, and then you get there and it becomes about finding the 4 Great Souls and King Vendrick?  And
then I guess somehow you&rsquo;re supposed to realize that oh right, after finding the king you need to travel through certain
memories to retrieve certain knowledge, and oh by the way SHADOWY RULER.  If that sounds confusing because I&rsquo;m trying to
leave out spoilers, don&rsquo;t worry&mdash;It&rsquo;s not much better with the characters and specifics filled in.</p>

<p>Beyond even the toning down of the art, this lack of direction was, to put it politely, a huge buzz-kill.  I understand
that a lot of these decisions were made to bring the franchise to a wider audience, since Demon&rsquo;s Souls was a rather
niche title with relatively limited commercial success.  But seriously guys.  DS2 was like watered down tea to DS1 +
DeS&#8217; black coffee.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coi]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/15/coi/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-15T19:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/15/coi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="https://scontent-a-lga.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-prn2/t1.0-9/10366159_10152435781269470_5551473906445502316_n.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>Of course it&rsquo;s just after I dish out a healthy dose of self-deprecation about restaurant writing that I feel compelled
to write about another restaurant.  So I&rsquo;ll keep it short.</p>

<p>I went to Daniel Patterson&rsquo;s Coi recently.  The only thing I can say about the food is that it wasn&rsquo;t overtly
over-the-top.  Nor was it deliberately modernist or filled with crazy techniques using chemicals I can&rsquo;t pronounce.  But
it was very very delicious and still managed to surprise me.  I can&rsquo;t overstate how awesome this is, and would recommend
the trip to anyone given to spending unhealthy amounts of money on food.</p>

<p>Also bought a signed copy of the book while I was there.  I can&rsquo;t wait to read it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Funny Thing About Quitting]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/10/the-funny-thing-about-quitting/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-10T20:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/10/the-funny-thing-about-quitting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We were shooting the shit in the gym on Thursday, when the subject of wasted memberships came up.  As I&rsquo;m sure is common
in any other type of service with a monthly membership, we apparently have a fair amount of people who pay for an
unlimited pass but only show up once every two weeks or so.  Or even people who pay for a membership and just don&rsquo;t show
up at all.  This isn&rsquo;t such a big deal at a place where the monthly fee is $10, but for BJJ gyms in metropolitan areas,
the costs tend to fall somewhere between $100-$200 / month.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a pretty significant amount of money.  So why would people spend it for a service they&rsquo;re not bothering to use?
Sure, there&rsquo;s a &ldquo;one year&rdquo; contract for the gym, but owners tend to be understanding most of the time, and the effort in
canceling that is pretty trivial.  I think the real barrier is in the way people think about quitting.</p>

<p>When we pick up a hobby and things get serious, it starts working its way into our definitions of ourselves.  This is
especially true for something like jiu jitsu, which involves a heavy investment and intrinsically comes with rewards
like &ldquo;higher self confidence&rdquo;, but it also applies to anything from learning a new language to picking up an instrument
to experimenting with painting.</p>

<p>So it&rsquo;s only natural that when life starts getting in the way, we cling onto that image.  Maybe we go from every day to
only a few times a week.  Then once a week.  Then once a month.  Then <em>&ldquo;Oh yeah, I&rsquo;m learning to speak Spanish, but
it&rsquo;s been a few months since I&rsquo;ve had the chance to practice&hellip;&rdquo;</em>  But we rarely ever cross the threshold into
consciously declaring that we&rsquo;ve quit.  Are you still really playing the guitar if it&rsquo;s been six months since you&rsquo;ve
touched it?  One year?  Three?</p>

<p>Canceling a membership requires the conscious decision that <em>yes, I&rsquo;ve quit</em>.  But we never really seem to cross that
point.  It&rsquo;s always one rationalization after another.  Perhaps if we&rsquo;re could be more honest with ourselves, we could
save a lot of the resources that that costs us, whether that be a monthly membership fee that could be better put
towards something else, or the energy and creativity spent in thinking up justifications for ourselves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some CH Backport vimporn]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/02/some-ch-backport-vimporn/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-02T20:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/02/some-ch-backport-vimporn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In some ways, the curehappiness backports came at the perfect time, since I&rsquo;d been looking for something to sharpen my
vim skills on.  Technically I work in vim day-to-day, but usually the rest of the mental activity involved with coding
end up pushing my vim-awareness more to the side than I&rsquo;d like.  This backport, however, was heavy on repetition but
otherwise braindead, so it made the perfect set of practice exercises.  And since I had such fun (hey, it was a really
boring Sunday afternoon&hellip;), I figured I&rsquo;d share in case anyone else finds this useful&mdash;or even better, has suggestions
to make similar tasks more efficient in the future.  Please note that this is a rather quick fly-by and assumes moderate
familiarity with vim mechanics.  I&rsquo;ll probably do more slow, detailed posts in the future&hellip;</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Start</h3>

<p>Since I had all the posts in html form, using <code>:set paste</code> and copy-pasting from the browser seemed the most
straightforward.  Or at least, more straightforward than trying to manually un-mangle everything in the post after being
wrung through wordpress.  For most of the posts, the paste result looked something like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/start.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p>Not too awful, but the TODO is obvious:</p>

<ol>
<li>Needs a banner image</li>
<li>Lines need to be wrapped (not strictly necessary, but personal pet peeve)</li>
<li>Ingredients + Methodology need to be de-dented</li>
<li>Ingredients needs to be an unordered list</li>
<li>Methodology needs to be an ordered list.</li>
</ol>


<p>Technically I guess headings need to be put in too, but since headings are simply <code># HEADING 1</code>, <code>## HEADING 2</code>, etc, in
markdown, that&rsquo;s pretty trivial.</p>

<h3>Banner image</h3>

<p>This bit was easy.  I have a plugin installed called <code>vim-snipmate</code> (check it out
<a href="https://github.com/garbas/vim-snipmate">here</a>) that&rsquo;s just built for stuff like this.  Simply put, defining the snippet
below:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>snippet img
</span><span class='line'>    {% img center ${1} %}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>allowed me to type <code>img&lt;TAB&gt;</code> and it would insert <code>{% img center %}</code>, with my cursor right after the <code>center</code> and ready
to drop in my picture url.</p>

<h3>Wrapping lines</h3>

<p>vim has a normal mode command, <code>gq</code>, that does this quite well.  Personally I like using visual line mode (<code>V</code>) to
select the text to wrap, but using it with a motion (e.g., <code>gq}</code> to wrap a block) works as well.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/gq-before.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/gq-after.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p>I only wrapped the plain paragraphs here, as there is still some fancy dedenting and formatting to do with the Ingredients
and Methodology sections first.</p>

<h3>De-denting</h3>

<p>The vim command for de-denting is <code>&lt;</code>.  Once again, combining with visual line mode or a motion (ex: <code>&lt;}</code>) makes it
quick and easy.  (Just in case&mdash;Yes, <code>&gt;</code> is the command for indenting)</p>

<h3>Ingredients => Unordered List</h3>

<p>This one, I&rsquo;ll admit, is a little snazzy.  I used the lesser-known cousin of visual and visual line mode, visual block
mode (accessed via <code>&lt;Ctrl&gt;-V</code>).  Once selecting the first characters of the lines I wanted with visual block, I could
hit <code>&lt;Shift-I&gt;</code> to drop into insert mode before current character, <code>-</code> to insert what I wanted, then <code>&lt;ESC&gt;</code> to apply
to everything in the selection.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/ul-before.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/ul-during.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/ul-after.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p>Note that this is also a great way to mass-comment blocks of code in languages that only support single line comments
with <code>#</code> or whatnot.</p>

<h3>Methodology => Ordered List</h3>

<p>And of course, the best is for last.  Ordered lists in markdown, logically, can be formatted something like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>1. item 1
</span><span class='line'>2. item 2
</span><span class='line'>3. item 3</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>However, it&rsquo;s actually possible to cheat and still get ordered list output by doing:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>1. item 1
</span><span class='line'>1. item 2
</span><span class='line'>1. item 3</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>It turns out that the markdown spec doesn&rsquo;t care about the order of the numbering as long as the lines begin with
numbers in that format.  So technically, I could use the same trick as the Ingredients Unordered List except inserting
<code>1.</code>, and I&rsquo;d be done.</p>

<p>&hellip;  But where&rsquo;s the fun in that?</p>

<p>So here&rsquo;s another tidbit: in vim, if you place the cursor over a number and hit <code>&lt;Ctrl&gt;-A</code> in normal mode, it increments
the number.  In a very smart way, too&mdash;it takes into account all of the digits, not just the one under the cursor.
Using this, it&rsquo;s pretty easy to write a vim macro (namely, a series of recorded keystrokes that can be repeated).</p>

<p>Rather than explain in long form, it seems easier just paste the sequence and annotate it.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>qq^yaWjP^^Aq <span class="c"># Complete keystroke sequence</span>
</span><span class='line'>             <span class="c"># Note that ^A is one character--see below for details</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>qq   <span class="c"># Start recording keystrokes into the q register</span>
</span><span class='line'>^    <span class="c"># Go to first non-blank character of line</span>
</span><span class='line'>yaW  <span class="c"># yank (copy) a Word--Capital W means a &quot;word&quot; is terminated only by spaces, not punctuation like &quot;-&quot; </span>
</span><span class='line'>j    <span class="c"># Go down a line</span>
</span><span class='line'>P^   <span class="c"># Paste before cursor, then go back to first non-blank character</span>
</span><span class='line'>^A   <span class="c"># Increment number</span>
</span><span class='line'>q    <span class="c"># Stop recording</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>It ends up looking something like this, played out:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/mac-1.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/mac-2.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://alexkuang.github.io/images/ch-backport-vim/mac-3.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><em>(Aside: I should start making gifs again for stuff like this&hellip;  Perhaps another day when I have more time.)</em></p>

<p>Once the macro is recorded, it can be played back via <code>@q</code>, or whichever register it was recorded into.  More
importantly, because it resets to the right positions in the lines and moves down automatically, it can actually be
repeated!  e.g., <code>2@q</code> turns this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>1. item 1
</span><span class='line'>item 2
</span><span class='line'>item 3
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>into this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>1. item 1
</span><span class='line'>2. item 2
</span><span class='line'>3. item 3
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Writing macros to position in a looping way like this is another post altogether, but suffice to say this saved a TON of
time over multiple posts.  Granted, it still depends on the <code>1.</code> being inserted manually, but that&rsquo;s pretty trivial I
think.</p>

<p>Another neat thing that might not immediately be obvious is that regular yanking (or copying, if you will) goes into the
same registers as macro recordings.  So you can use <code>"qp</code> to paste the contents of your macro into a buffer to map it to
keys or functions (ex: <code>nnoremap &lt;leader&gt;o ^yaW[...]</code>).</p>

<p>Furthermore, this means that if a recording goes wrong, you can just paste it out, edit it, then select and <code>"qy</code> (or
similar) to yank back the edited form.  The only caveat is that certain characters like <code>^A</code> may paste out and LOOK like
two characters, but is infact only one character.  Not a big deal if you&rsquo;re just yanking and replacing text, but it can
be a weird GOTCHA if you&rsquo;re trying to write a macro by hand or something.  (In this particular case, the <code>^A</code> character
can be obtained in insert mode via <code>&lt;Ctrl-V&gt;&lt;Ctrl-A&gt;</code>, but it pays to watch out in general for stuff like this)</p>

<p>So there you have it, ladies and gentlemen&mdash;My idea of fun on a Sunday afternoon&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CH Backports]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/ch-backports/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-26T21:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/ch-backports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For anyone unfamiliar, I wrote a food blog a while back called curehappiness with my then-roommate,
<a href="http://tlextrait.com/">Thomas</a>.  It was active mostly during my college years, dying down due to a whole variety of
reasons&mdash;office life, apathy at the post-grad lifestyle, wordpress being a pain&hellip;  All that great stuff.  The project
had originally started as an off-the-cuff idea for something to do with a newly commissioned server; after a while, I
decided to shuffle up my server arrangements, and curehappiness&#8217; Wordpress installation got the axe.  Since I couldn&rsquo;t
be bothered to backup the entire WP install, I just saved a bunch of the posts in HTML form instead, with the idea of
one day porting it to whatever new platform I would be running.</p>

<p>After all this time on Octopress + Github Pages, I finally pulled the trigger.  All the backported posts will be from
before 2013, tagged as <code>ch-backports</code>, and will contain a link at the top to this post.  They&rsquo;ve largely been preserved
verbatim, minus a few corrections like &lsquo;boal&rsquo; &ndash;> &lsquo;bowl&rsquo; (seriously, past Alex???).  However, I couldn&rsquo;t resist adding
small notes from the future, which will be in blockquotes at the top:</p>

<blockquote><p>like so.</p></blockquote>

<p>I ported the posts with the most worthwhile content&mdash;namely, recipes and records of experiments.  Restaurant reviews and
other such content were few and far between, and honestly aside from a couple of wisecracks and some nice pictures, they
felt pretty banal; not a solid reason for censorship, granted, but I still felt it wasn&rsquo;t worth the effort.  I&rsquo;ll
probably upload the photos from those posts to smugmug at some point and save the rewrites for when I have actual
original insights beyond &ldquo;yes, the food was good&rdquo;.</p>

<p>As a final note, migrating was not trivial, but I did get some nice hackery out of it.  I&rsquo;ll probably post the
tech-gorey details later, but suffice to say that I&rsquo;ve learned my lesson about storing data in arbitrary mangled html
generated by a WYSIWYG editor run through who knows how many plugins and themes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hack Days Are Awesome]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/hack-days-are-awesome/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-26T15:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/hack-days-are-awesome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this week, we had a &ldquo;hack day&rdquo; at work.  Or more precisely, two hack days.  I think the name is pretty
self-explanatory&mdash;work on whatever you want, which can be something helpful to or completely unrelated to your currently
assigned tasks, as long as it&rsquo;s something interesting.  Now, &ldquo;hack time&rdquo; is a pretty established institution in the
software world, especially amongst the hip startuppy companies.  I&rsquo;m sure everyone has heard of Google&rsquo;s &ldquo;20% time&rdquo; idea
by now, and the story of Microsoft&rsquo;s Xbox starting as a side-project.  Proponents (especially those who are trying to
pitch a business case to managers with varying degrees of pointy-haired-ness) cite building camaraderie, stimulating
creativity, and increasing morale as some of the biggest benefits.</p>

<p>None of this is news.  But I came away this week with a surprising realization.  When coding professionally for business
use cases, things like resilience and stability are often at the top of the requirement list&mdash;Or at least, I&rsquo;d really
hope so.  If it&rsquo;s not, kindly give me the name of your company so I know what stock to not buy ;).  To this end, coding
is never as simple as just sitting down and banging away at a keyboard.  It involves testing, discussions, design,
thinking, more testing, more thinking, and so on and so forth.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t get me wrong.  These are all very, very good things.  But I, at least, was surprised at how nice it was to just
sit down and bang away at a keyboard with abandon.  It sounds rather obvious in hindsight, but compared to the usual
rigorously managed process of software development at work, it&rsquo;s super liberating to just cowboy out some code with no
considerations other than speed and getting the job done.  And what&rsquo;s more, I realized that I had constrained myself to
the same careful management in all of my personal projects as well, especially when prototyping out potential MVPs and
such.  Again&mdash;Definitely a good thing, in most cases.  But after this week I&rsquo;m thinking that injecting some &ldquo;hack
day&rdquo;-ish time into my personal projects is in order, if for no reason other than to let the crazy out.</p>

<p><strong>tl;dr</strong> &ndash; Hack days are awesome.  I should do more of them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whole Chicken Biryani]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/23/whole-chicken-biryani/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T21:38:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/23/whole-chicken-biryani</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-2SMxkfv/0/L/DSC_2941-L.jpg"></p>

<p>And it&rsquo;s time for yet another episode of &ldquo;As [I Have] Seen On TV&rdquo;!  This time, I draw inspiration from Ramsay&rsquo;s Great
Escape, in which Gordon gets tired of his financial troubles and career as a TV chef and so decides to&hellip;  Go off to
make more TV.  Go figure.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Regardless of motivations, it&rsquo;s a pretty engaging show.  Throughout two seasons, he travels through southeast
Asia&mdash;India, China, Vietnam, and the like&mdash;slumming it with the locals to learn their skills and eventually returning to
the &ldquo;civilized areas&rdquo; of the country to demonstrate his newfound knowledge.  The only real complaint I have is the
(hopefully unintended) air of condescension that he develops at times.  &ldquo;Look, these people have <em>absolutely nothing</em>
and they still eat like kings!  It&rsquo;s <em>amazing</em>!&rdquo;</p>

<p>That aside, there are some memorable moments, one of which was a wedding catering to something in the neighborhood of
1000 guests.  Ramsay goes back to his line cook roots and helps a chef stuff a goat with some chicken stuffed with quail
stuffed with egg which is then loaded into a giant vat of rice. Despite my dreams to own a farm one day I still haven&rsquo;t
the means to pull a goat out of thin air, but I figured a whole chicken biryani might be worth a shot.  While I have
done biryani before, this was highly experimental, so this will be more of a photo log than set instructions</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-45Rk3rc/0/L/DSC_2943-L.jpg"></p>

<p>First, the chicken was rubbed with oil and lemon juice mixed with biryani-ish spices: cloves, cayenne, cumin seed,
coriander, and so on.  That was left to sit for a little bit while I par-boiled my rice, and then thrown into a pot to
roast with some potatoes.  I used my usual temps: 450 for &frac12; hour, 370 after.  In this case I shortened the cooking
time a bit, since it still had to cook with the rice.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-sD6CTSf/0/L/DSC_2944-L.jpg"></p>

<p>After the chicken was done, I deglazed the bottom of the pot and lined it with freshly sliced tomatoes.  Then I stuffed
some of the rice and potato into the chicken, loaded the chicken and potatoes back into the pot, and covered with the
par-boiled rice.  I lined the pot cover with a cloth to trap the steam, and it finished in about 45 minutes at a
medium-lowish heat.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-5JQdj93/0/L/DSC_2950-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Overall this turned out pretty well.  There wasn&rsquo;t much deviation from &ldquo;standard biryani procedure&rdquo;, which basically
just involves cubed meat instead of a whole bird.  The biggest pain was getting the meat off the chicken at the end: it
came off, but took some effort.  Perhaps a longer cooking time, or more moisture to cook the chicken with, next time?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Garlic Soy Chicken Wings]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/17/garlic-soy-chicken-wings/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-17T20:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/17/garlic-soy-chicken-wings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-ZfrmLNX/0/L/DSC_2936-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Yes, I&rsquo;m going to be <em>that</em> Asian who posts a chicken wing recipe involving some combination of garlic, soy, and honey.
Next thing you know I&rsquo;ll be writing book reviews for the Joy Luck Club and acting in sketches about Tiger Moms.  Though
I suppose the latter would be pretty entertaining&hellip;</p>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t the first chicken wing recipe I&rsquo;ve posted <em>(note to self: still need to port those old entries over&hellip;)</em>, but
it is a pretty quick and easy one.  The only awkward part is that in situations like this, it&rsquo;s not worth the effort to
not make a ton, but then everything takes a while to eat&hellip;  But I think that&rsquo;s a pretty good problem to have.</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>3 lb chicken wings</li>
<li>1 cup vegetable oil</li>
<li>&frac14; cup honey</li>
<li>&frac14; cup soy sauce</li>
<li>&frac14; cup Shaoxing wine</li>
<li>4 cloves garlic</li>
<li>1 tbsp brown sugar</li>
<li>Pinch of salt</li>
</ul>


<p>To prepare, mix all the sauce ingredients together, and toss the chicken in.  If you&rsquo;re feeling really bored, jab them a
few times to help the sauce seep in.  Mix evenly, then let it sit in the fridge overnight.  In my experience, the wings
can be kept this way for up to 3 days&mdash;I&rsquo;d vouch for longer, but they&rsquo;re generally eaten in that time frame.</p>

<p>When ready, pre-heat the oven to 375, and bake for about 30 minutes.  Do note that I usually cook in batches, so if the
whole 3 lb needs to be done at once, 45 minutes would probably be safer.  Give them a quick toss on the stove with some
fresh herbs.  Scallions are usually a pretty good bet, but I like cilantro too.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-VS3Xmzp/0/L/DSC_2918-L.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shepherd's Pie - Week 10, Australian]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/shepherds-pie-week-10-australian/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-12T22:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/shepherds-pie-week-10-australian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-hnc6sSv/0/L/DSC_2915-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Alright, so I cheated a little bit.  Despite extensive (not really) research, I couldn&rsquo;t find anything in the top google
results for Australian that really clicked.  At least, anything using conventional ingredients; I didn&rsquo;t quite get the
chance to special-order some kangaroo.  Since I&rsquo;m told meat pies are popular in Australia and the lamb was technically
from there, it still counts&hellip;  Right?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Even though it&rsquo;s technically an Aussie theme, I went with a more british twist on the ingredients, especially with the
Worcestershire sauce.  The following makes enough to modestly feed 4 off a pretty decent size tray.  <em>No, I don&rsquo;t have
exact dimensions for the tray, it&rsquo;s a meat pie, eyeball it FFS.</em></p>

<ul>
<li>1 lb ground lamb</li>
<li>1 lb yellow potato, heavy cream</li>
<li>Stock, preferably beef</li>
<li>A dash (or 3) Worcestershire sauce</li>
<li>1 tbsp tomato paste</li>
<li>Carrots &lsquo;n peas (or other vegetables)</li>
<li>Garlic</li>
<li>Thyme</li>
</ul>


<p>First off, the meez.  Chop up the garlic, pick the thyme leaves, and finely dice the vegetables, if applicable.  In my
case, it&rsquo;s more like &ldquo;take the bag out of the freezer.&rdquo;  Seriously, for carrots and peas in something like meat pie,
frozen works best.</p>

<p>Put a nice heavy pan on the stove and get it ripping hot.  Add the lamb and garlic, and let the meat get some color.
Don&rsquo;t jab at it or anything for the first few minutes; we want it to fry, not boil.</p>

<p>After it gets a nice dark brown color, start stirring and breaking it apart into tiny pieces.  When it&rsquo;s done, you
should hear sizzling from fat, not hissing from steam&mdash;this should take 10, 15 minutes or so.</p>

<p>Stir in the worcestershire sauce and tomato paste, then add the thyme and beef stock.  How much beef stock is pretty
subjective: I use just enough to mix with the tomato paste for a gravy-ish texture.  The key is not so little that
everything is dry, but not so much that it bubbles over in the oven.  If I had to guess, I&rsquo;d say it&rsquo;s just shy of 2
cups, but perhaps a picture of the end product would be helpful?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-kZsbxX3/0/L/DSC_2895-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Put a lid on, and let it simmer on very low heat for at least 30-40 minutes, preferably an hour, just to let everything
come together.  Alternately, popping the pan in the oven at ~300-350 also works.</p>

<p>Preheat the oven to 400.  While the meat is going and the oven is warming, prepare the mash.  I really hope I don&rsquo;t have
to provide detailed instructions for that&hellip;  If that&rsquo;s needed, there&rsquo;s always google.</p>

<p>When the meat is done, stick it in a tray and spread the mash on top.  Score with a fork for effect, if desired.  Then
stick into the oven again for about 30 minutes to finish everything off and brown the top a bit.  For presentation, I
bet some eggwash would help with the browning, but I&rsquo;ve never found it necessary.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-qMkv5Mz/0/L/DSC_2908-L.jpg"></p>

<p>In this particular attempt, I added a bit too much stock and it ended up bubbling out onto the potato.  Still delicious,
though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Curry Chicken Galantine]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/30/curry-chicken-galantine/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-30T21:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/30/curry-chicken-galantine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-Chicken-Galantine/i-K79mZTH/0/L/DSC_2867-L.jpg"></p>

<p><em>What?!  A food post that isn&rsquo;t themed?!</em>  That&rsquo;s right.  While the 52weeks deal resulted in consistency, doing only
those posts all the time got a bit stale, so I decided to go a bit off the beaten path.  This dish was inspired by what
is still one of the coolest videos I&rsquo;ve ever seen: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kAekQ5fzfGM">Jacques Pepin deboning an entire chicken</a>.
A Galantine is a French (big surprise) technique where all of the bones are removed from a chicken, but the meat and
skin is kept intact like the remains of some sort of creepy skinwalker type transformation.   Everything is then
stuffed, rolled up, and roasted.</p>

<p>Despite its simplicity, it&rsquo;s one of the coolest techniques I have ever seen, and it makes carving much much easier
since you don&rsquo;t have any bones to contend with while grappling a hot chicken fresh out of the oven.  I&rsquo;ve only done this
a few times, and it&rsquo;s already become my de-facto method for preparing whole chicken&mdash;the cool factor, the corpse
desecration, the ease of plating&hellip;  What&rsquo;s not to like?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Why Curry</h3>

<p>For this particular chicken, I decided to combine a thoroughly French technique with thoroughly un-French
flavors&mdash;Curry.</p>

<p>Even though I&rsquo;m all elitist and tend mix my own spices nowadays, my childhood was spent eating curries made with instant
powder mixes.  (<em>For the record, nothing wrong with curry powder mixes, assuming they&rsquo;re made from actual spices&hellip;</em>)
The most common of these was Madras Curry, particularly <a href="http://vietwah.com/Joomla/components/com_virtuemart/shop_image/product/fab54182fc7c87449f726b0e7cb3bec9.jpg">this brand</a>.
If the image link breaks, just google &ldquo;Ca Ri An Do&rdquo;.  It&rsquo;s a pretty unremarkable curry based heavily in turmeric,
definitely tending more towards the mild flavors that the Chinese/Japanese tend to flavor rather than the ripping hot
Vindaloo style you can see with some of the Indian curries.</p>

<p>But one of the problems I&rsquo;ve always had with this one in particular was that the sauce would have to get really thick
for the flavor to come out in the chicken.  In this past I&rsquo;d done this with judicious (read: heavy-handed) use of cream,
starch from potatoes, and reduction of liquid, but it never really got to the level I would have liked.  So when I was
thinking about variations on a Galantine, doing a stuffing with this curry powder was just about the first thing that
came to mind.</p>

<h3>The Chicken</h3>

<p>I can&rsquo;t possibly explain the technique behind a Galantine as well as the man himself, so if you didn&rsquo;t click on the
video link above, I suggest you do.  Go on.  I&rsquo;ll even put it down here as well.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kAekQ5fzfGM">Link</a></p>

<p>Watched it?  Good.  Pretty awesome, isn&rsquo;t it?  The stuffing is pretty simple:</p>

<ol>
<li>Finely dice yukon potatoes and carrots, and boil until tender</li>
<li>Mash up with a fork, dumping in generous helpings of curry powder and a pinch of salt</li>
<li>Add a touch of heavy cream for consistency, and because cream is delicious.</li>
</ol>


<p>In essence it was a rustic mashed potato.  I&rsquo;m sure a super fancy restaurant could do a potato and carrot puree or
something, but ain&rsquo;t nobody got time for that in this kitchen.  Stuff the chicken, truss it up, dust it with more curry
powder and salt, and stick it in the oven.  I stole my roasting technique from Thomas Keller&mdash;450 for ~25 minutes, then
370 until the internal temp of the thickest part of the thigh is 160&mdash;but really, whatever works.  Afterwards I just
made a sauce by deglazing the stuff in the roasting pan with some cream, and&mdash;<em>voila!</em></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-Chicken-Galantine/i-46XNmjz/0/L/DSC_2864-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Some people might say this technique is a bit old fashioned, but screw them.  Clearly they&rsquo;ve never deboned a chicken
with their hands&mdash;It&rsquo;s like ripping off a scab, except a million times more satisfying.  And delicious.  And chicken
wing lollipops?  Come on.  Ridiculous.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anime Boston 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/23/anime-boston-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-23T21:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/23/anime-boston-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Events/Anime-Boston-2014/i-8K2GL55/0/L/DSC_2822-L.jpg"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been years since I&rsquo;ve been to Anime Boston, or any other sort of nerdy/geeky gathering.  Maybe it was me drifting
away from the subculture and slowly becoming a filthy casual.  Maybe it was moving 40 miles &lt;&ndash; that way and not having a
car.  Or maybe it was the fact that they switched from nifty plastic convention badges to the slightly ghetto
paper-in-sleeve setup that they still had going this year.  For those who remember the cards&mdash;<em>yes, it&rsquo;s been that
long.</em></p>

<p>So when I was dropping by Copley this weekend to revisit some old watering holes and found out the convention was in
town, I figured why not?  I had some time to kill, and the registration lines looked pretty short.  I ended up only
staying the afternoon since my con-going stamina isn&rsquo;t what it used to be <em>(refer above to casual status)</em>, but here are
some quick impressions.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Attack on Titan</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Events/Anime-Boston-2014/i-QzFKFvb/0/L/DSC_2842-L.jpg"></p>

<p>To the surprise of absolutely nobody there, there was a lot of Attack on Titan this year.  Hell, even I managed to watch
it, and I&rsquo;ve been living under a proverbial anime rock.  Of course, there are the requisite calls of &ldquo;BEST ANIME EVER&rdquo;,
but I&rsquo;m not convinced that will hold after a few years.  Yes, it&rsquo;s solid.  And yes, it&rsquo;s a breath of fresh air in a sea of
Naruto and Bleach and all that.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, it&rsquo;s easy to tell good anime from bad, but a bit harder to predict whether they will have staying
power a la Cowboy Bebop, or slowly fizzle out.  In fact, I remember the exact same &ldquo;BEST ANIME&rdquo; calls around Full Metal
Alchemist the last time I went to AnimeBoston, and the accompanying tide of Ed &lsquo;n Al Elric cosplays.  This Saturday?  I
don&rsquo;t think I saw even two.</p>

<h3>Cosplays</h3>

<p>Speaking of cosplays, on the whole they have gotten a lot better.  I think as anime fandom grows and evolves, it becomes
less and less acceptable to &ldquo;cosplay&rdquo; by taping together a few pieces of felt and slapping on a $2 wig.  I see a lot
more creativity and a lot more effort all around, and that&rsquo;s a win for everyone.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Events/Anime-Boston-2014/i-GBxtNQn/0/L/DSC_2815-L.jpg"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Events/Anime-Boston-2014/i-xCZTxB4/0/L/DSC_2847-L.jpg"></p>

<h3>Alpacas</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Events/Anime-Boston-2014/i-q353B9K/0/L/DSC_2768-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Alpacas were a big deal this year.  Like really big.  &ldquo;Women want to be with you, men want to become you&rdquo; big.  I have
no idea why.  As far as I can tell they&rsquo;re not from any particular franchise or anything, it&rsquo;s just something that
happened.  &hellip;  Yeah, I got nothing.  They are pretty cute though.</p>

<h3>MARCO?!  POLO!!</h3>

<p>In the sea of new, it was comforting to see some old standbys were still alive and well, like the &ldquo;MARCO POLO&rdquo; meme.  I
know some people have problems with it <em>(dude, why are you at a convention center full of people if you have noise
issues?)</em>, but I find it comforting.  Kind of.  Discomfortingly awkward when someone tries to start and nobody bothers
responding I guess.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Events/Anime-Boston-2014/i-X9wkwZh/0/L/DSC_2826-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Also the stair high fives.  I actually don&rsquo;t remember 100% whether this was a thing years ago, but I&rsquo;m choosing to don
my rose-colored glasses and say it is.  Nothing says camaraderie through shared interests like high-fiving strangers on
an escalator.</p>

<p>I do wish the spontaneous Hare Hare Yukai dance parties still happened though&hellip;</p>

<h3>Terrorists</h3>

<p>My least favorite part of the con by far was the newly instituted bag checks.  Apparently they were new this year, and I
think I&rsquo;m not the only one who wasn&rsquo;t a fan.  I&rsquo;m told it was the Mayor&rsquo;s office&rsquo;s idea.  While I understand the safety
risks of having this many people in one place at once, I just wish the process worked a bit better.  As the day went on
and more swag was had, it became progressively more and more difficult to go back and forth between &ldquo;convention&rdquo; and
&ldquo;non-convention&rdquo; areas for food/coffee/what have you&mdash;and God help you if you have any techie-looking equipment in
complicated bags.  It was like a grab-bag of bite-sized TSA experiences.  Complete with drug sniffing dogs!</p>

<p>&hellip;  Alright, that&rsquo;s not fair.  The dogs were pretty cool.  My point still stands though.</p>

<p><em>(Full album <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Events/Anime-Boston-2014/">here</a>)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hipster Garlic Bread - Week 9, Garlic]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/22/hipster-garlic-bread-week-9-garlic/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-22T06:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/22/hipster-garlic-bread-week-9-garlic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Hipster-Garlic-Bread/i-XZVS2Lh/0/L/DSC_2581-L.jpg"></p>

<p>Garlic is such an ubiquitous ingredient that I could have easily <a href="http://alexkuang.com/blog/2013/11/17/roast-leg-of-lamb/">cheated</a>
my way around this week&rsquo;s theme.  But where&rsquo;s the fun in that?  In the end, the decision came down to the deliciousness
of garlic bread and my curiosity for the concept of &ldquo;pull-apart bread&rdquo;, something that has been on the rise on
instagrammy/pinteresty/otherwise-artsy-craftsy sites lately.  The result was the above: some sort of garlic pull-apart
boule that&rsquo;s kind of a cross between your typical &ldquo;pull-apart bread&rdquo; and a hasselback potato.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There isn&rsquo;t really too much to write about; this is one of those things that an autistic monkey could probably do, which
makes it a great go-to for party prep.  But here are some general guidelines anyway.  For ingredients:</p>

<ul>
<li>1 sourdough boule, roughly the size of your face</li>
<li>1+ stick (~113 grams) of butter, room-temp</li>
<li>1+ bulb of garlic</li>
<li>sliced mozzarella</li>
<li>thyme</li>
<li>bacon (optional, but who doesn&rsquo;t like bacon?)</li>
</ul>


<p>Yeah, you read the butter quantity right.  Those are rough estimates, but I&rsquo;d say they&rsquo;re absolute bare minimums for the
butter and garlic.  If you cared that much about your health, why are you anywhere near a recipe that combines bread,
butter, and cheese in the first place?  Anyone who does this might as well do it properly and enjoy the full flavor; in
for a penny, in for a pound.  As for the garlic, well&hellip;  The toothbrush is an amazing invention, and chewing gum isn&rsquo;t
a terrible fallback.  As for the actual prep:</p>

<ol>
<li>Fire up the oven at 375 F</li>
<li>Chop off the top of the garlic horizontally, so that you get a nice cross-section view of all the cloves.  Stick it
in the oven to roast.  I&rsquo;d say about 30 minutes.</li>
<li>While that&rsquo;s happening, slice the bread and make a ~1.5in grid.  Just make sure to stop cutting about &frac14;-&frac12; inch
before hitting the bottom of the bread.</li>
<li>After the garlic is done, extract your cloves with a fork; they should be pretty mushy at this point.  Mash it
together with the softened butter, making sure to get the garlic nice and pasty and incorporated.  If you&rsquo;re using
unsalted butter, a nice dose of salt would be a great idea at this point.

<ul>
<li>Note: For those who store butter in the fridge and are lazy, melting the butter with the garlic will also work
here; however, melting it fully will make even distribution in the bread harder.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spread the garlic butter using a knife, and really get it into the cracks.  Shank the bread like you&rsquo;re in a state
prison and it looked at you wrong.</li>
<li>Stuff it some more with thyme, mozzarella, and so on.  Bake in the oven for, oh I dunno, ~30 minutes, depending on
the size of the bread.</li>
</ol>


<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Hipster-Garlic-Bread/i-BSbTwgh/0/L/DSC_2576-L.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
