<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Meta | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-28T10:11:26-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jab, Jab]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/jab/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T19:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/jab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past, my biggest problem with blogging has always been with finding something to write about.  Every time an idea
came, I&rsquo;d recall the original post that inspired it, or have one miraculously pop up on google upon doing more
research.  Inevitably the post would be articulate, well-researched, and laden with comments from impressed readers to
boot.  And I would hit control+w, convinced that I don&rsquo;t have anything to add; even if I did, I&rsquo;m an awful writer and
nobody reads my blog anyway.</p>




<p>But writing is an Important Skill, one that I&rsquo;d very much like to improve.  I&rsquo;m certainly not going to get any better by
<em>not</em> doing it, and <a href="http://weknowmemes.com/2012/05/sucking-at-something-is-the-first-step-to-becoming/">everyone has to start somewhere</a>: keep practicing, keep
drilling, keep jabbing away, and eventually you&rsquo;ll probably make progress.  I remember an old post of Jeff Atwood&rsquo;s
where his only advice was to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/10/how-to-achieve-ultimate-blog-success-in-one-easy-step.html">pick a schedule</a> and stick
with it.  Maybe it&rsquo;s about time I did just that.  <strong>One post a week</strong>, even if the topic sounds asinine and I&rsquo;m low on
inspiration and nobody will read it (or <em>especially</em> if nobody will read it?).</p>




<p>With all that said, I&rsquo;d like to introduce my newest housemate, <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Animals/Zelda">Zelda</a>.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Animals/Zelda/i-rNGBWHH/0/L/DSC_2268-L.jpg"></p>




<p>She arrived with all of 3 days&#8217; notice, and is at just about that age where kittens tend to be terrible people.  She&rsquo;ll
bully the other (much bigger) cats, knock over bowls and trash bags, attack everything like the king of the jungle, and
just generally be an unabashed little snot.  But she&rsquo;s disarmingly adorable, so naturally none of that matters in the
slightest.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
