<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gaming | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/gaming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-25T18:11:22-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Preferred Dark Souls I]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/23/why-i-preferred-dark-souls-i/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-23T21:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/23/why-i-preferred-dark-souls-i</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dark Souls 2 is a great game.  Let&rsquo;s get that out of the way.  I&rsquo;ve logged low 3 digits in hours of gameplay, and made
it through the game multiple times.  The combat system is tuned, there&rsquo;s a ton of content, and multiplayer is pretty fun
(or at least, it was at the levels I hung around).  But I still prefer the original, and Demon&rsquo;s Souls, over it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The biggest turn-off in DS2 was the shift in design goals.  The dripping atmosphere and rich world were always the
primary draws in the franchise, and the difficulty took a back seat (relatively speaking) as a tool to work towards that
goal.  In DS2, it felt more like the developers' primary goal was &ldquo;HOW CAN WE MAKE THIS HARDER?&rdquo;  This was evidenced in
the way combat shifted towards the many-vs-one paradigm; not only with regular enemies, but with the bosses as well.
The Skeleton Lords, the Dragon Knights, the Looking Glass Knight, Twin Pursuers, Ruin Sentinels&hellip;  &ldquo;How can we make
this harder?  Let&rsquo;s just put more enemies in.&rdquo;  Not only is the repetition insulting, aiming for &ldquo;hard&rdquo; is just
completely missing the point.</p>

<p>Take the DS1 fight with Artorias.  It&rsquo;s such a fan favorite not only because it was ridiculously hard, but because the
entire fight was steeped in the world&rsquo;s lore.  After fighting Sif, going through the Abyss, and reading bits and pieces
from the game&rsquo;s NPCs about the fall of Artorias the Abysswalker, his charge towards the player holds a gravity that
couldn&rsquo;t be matched by even 20 Pursuers.  Seriously, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ctW277Kpcv0">check it</a>.</p>

<p>Speaking of the lore, that&rsquo;s another big point of contention with me.  I feel like there&rsquo;s a big difference between lore
and plot.  Lore is the background of the world.  It&rsquo;s the story behind each NPC, each item, each location, and it&rsquo;s
great for it to be subtle and nebulous.  A richly built, subtly woven world gives the player an opportunity to explore
and really dive into the atmosphere of everything.</p>

<p>The plot, however, is simply the thread of the story that drives the player&rsquo;s main progression, and needs to be very
clear cut.  Another concrete example, as spoiler-free as possible: In DS1, the player embarks on a quest to re-light the
first flame on the request of a dying man in the asylum.  On his quest to do that, he awakens a primordial serpent, and
the progression from there differs, ending with the player either re-kindling the first flame or leaving it to die.  The
story is pretty straightforward there, and at any given point you&rsquo;re pretty clear about the motivations of your
character.</p>

<p>In contrast, DS2 opens up with something about a curse in Drangleic and how you must go there, <strong>only to
never revisit the topic</strong>.  No seriously, what the hell is that?  They make this whole deal with the old ladies about
the curse of Drangleic, and then you get there and it becomes about finding the 4 Great Souls and King Vendrick?  And
then I guess somehow you&rsquo;re supposed to realize that oh right, after finding the king you need to travel through certain
memories to retrieve certain knowledge, and oh by the way SHADOWY RULER.  If that sounds confusing because I&rsquo;m trying to
leave out spoilers, don&rsquo;t worry&mdash;It&rsquo;s not much better with the characters and specifics filled in.</p>

<p>Beyond even the toning down of the art, this lack of direction was, to put it politely, a huge buzz-kill.  I understand
that a lot of these decisions were made to bring the franchise to a wider audience, since Demon&rsquo;s Souls was a rather
niche title with relatively limited commercial success.  But seriously guys.  DS2 was like watered down tea to DS1 +
DeS' black coffee.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
