<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: recipes | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/recipes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-27T17:28:10-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Garlic Soy Chicken Wings]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/17/garlic-soy-chicken-wings/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-17T20:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/17/garlic-soy-chicken-wings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-ZfrmLNX/0/L/DSC_2936-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-ZfrmLNX/0/L/DSC_2936-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Yes, I&rsquo;m going to be <em>that</em> Asian who posts a chicken wing recipe involving some combination of garlic, soy, and honey.
Next thing you know I&rsquo;ll be writing book reviews for the Joy Luck Club and acting in sketches about Tiger Moms.  Though
I suppose the latter would be pretty entertaining&hellip;</p>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t the first chicken wing recipe I&rsquo;ve posted <em>(note to self: still need to port those old entries over&hellip;)</em>, but
it is a pretty quick and easy one.  The only awkward part is that in situations like this, it&rsquo;s not worth the effort to
not make a ton, but then everything takes a while to eat&hellip;  But I think that&rsquo;s a pretty good problem to have.</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>3 lb chicken wings</li>
<li>1 cup vegetable oil</li>
<li>&frac14; cup honey</li>
<li>&frac14; cup soy sauce</li>
<li>&frac14; cup Shaoxing wine</li>
<li>4 cloves garlic</li>
<li>1 tbsp brown sugar</li>
<li>Pinch of salt</li>
</ul>


<p>To prepare, mix all the sauce ingredients together, and toss the chicken in.  If you&rsquo;re feeling really bored, jab them a
few times to help the sauce seep in.  Mix evenly, then let it sit in the fridge overnight.  In my experience, the wings
can be kept this way for up to 3 days&mdash;I&rsquo;d vouch for longer, but they&rsquo;re generally eaten in that time frame.</p>

<p>When ready, pre-heat the oven to 375, and bake for about 30 minutes.  Do note that I usually cook in batches, so if the
whole 3 lb needs to be done at once, 45 minutes would probably be safer.  Give them a quick toss on the stove with some
fresh herbs.  Scallions are usually a pretty good bet, but I like cilantro too.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-VS3Xmzp/0/L/DSC_2918-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-VS3Xmzp/0/L/DSC_2918-L.jpg</a>"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shepherd's Pie - Week 10, Australian]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/shepherds-pie-week-10-australian/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-12T22:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/shepherds-pie-week-10-australian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-hnc6sSv/0/L/DSC_2915-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-hnc6sSv/0/L/DSC_2915-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Alright, so I cheated a little bit.  Despite extensive (not really) research, I couldn&rsquo;t find anything in the top google
results for Australian that really clicked.  At least, anything using conventional ingredients; I didn&rsquo;t quite get the
chance to special-order some kangaroo.  Since I&rsquo;m told meat pies are popular in Australia and the lamb was technically
from there, it still counts&hellip;  Right?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Even though it&rsquo;s technically an Aussie theme, I went with a more british twist on the ingredients, especially with the
Worcestershire sauce.  The following makes enough to modestly feed 4 off a pretty decent size tray.  <em>No, I don&rsquo;t have
exact dimensions for the tray, it&rsquo;s a meat pie, eyeball it FFS.</em></p>

<ul>
<li>1 lb ground lamb</li>
<li>1 lb yellow potato, heavy cream</li>
<li>Stock, preferably beef</li>
<li>A dash (or 3) Worcestershire sauce</li>
<li>1 tbsp tomato paste</li>
<li>Carrots &lsquo;n peas (or other vegetables)</li>
<li>Garlic</li>
<li>Thyme</li>
</ul>


<p>First off, the meez.  Chop up the garlic, pick the thyme leaves, and finely dice the vegetables, if applicable.  In my
case, it&rsquo;s more like &ldquo;take the bag out of the freezer.&rdquo;  Seriously, for carrots and peas in something like meat pie,
frozen works best.</p>

<p>Put a nice heavy pan on the stove and get it ripping hot.  Add the lamb and garlic, and let the meat get some color.
Don&rsquo;t jab at it or anything for the first few minutes; we want it to fry, not boil.</p>

<p>After it gets a nice dark brown color, start stirring and breaking it apart into tiny pieces.  When it&rsquo;s done, you
should hear sizzling from fat, not hissing from steam&mdash;this should take 10, 15 minutes or so.</p>

<p>Stir in the worcestershire sauce and tomato paste, then add the thyme and beef stock.  How much beef stock is pretty
subjective: I use just enough to mix with the tomato paste for a gravy-ish texture.  The key is not so little that
everything is dry, but not so much that it bubbles over in the oven.  If I had to guess, I&rsquo;d say it&rsquo;s just shy of 2
cups, but perhaps a picture of the end product would be helpful?</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-kZsbxX3/0/L/DSC_2895-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-kZsbxX3/0/L/DSC_2895-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Put a lid on, and let it simmer on very low heat for at least 30-40 minutes, preferably an hour, just to let everything
come together.  Alternately, popping the pan in the oven at ~300-350 also works.</p>

<p>Preheat the oven to 400.  While the meat is going and the oven is warming, prepare the mash.  I really hope I don&rsquo;t have
to provide detailed instructions for that&hellip;  If that&rsquo;s needed, there&rsquo;s always google.</p>

<p>When the meat is done, stick it in a tray and spread the mash on top.  Score with a fork for effect, if desired.  Then
stick into the oven again for about 30 minutes to finish everything off and brown the top a bit.  For presentation, I
bet some eggwash would help with the browning, but I&rsquo;ve never found it necessary.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-qMkv5Mz/0/L/DSC_2908-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-qMkv5Mz/0/L/DSC_2908-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>In this particular attempt, I added a bit too much stock and it ended up bubbling out onto the potato.  Still delicious,
though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Curry Chicken Galantine]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/30/curry-chicken-galantine/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-30T21:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/30/curry-chicken-galantine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-Chicken-Galantine/i-K79mZTH/0/L/DSC_2867-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-Chicken-Galantine/i-K79mZTH/0/L/DSC_2867-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p><em>What?!  A food post that isn&rsquo;t themed?!</em>  That&rsquo;s right.  While the 52weeks deal resulted in consistency, doing only
those posts all the time got a bit stale, so I decided to go a bit off the beaten path.  This dish was inspired by what
is still one of the coolest videos I&rsquo;ve ever seen: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kAekQ5fzfGM">Jacques Pepin deboning an entire chicken</a>.
A Galantine is a French (big surprise) technique where all of the bones are removed from a chicken, but the meat and
skin is kept intact like the remains of some sort of creepy skinwalker type transformation.   Everything is then
stuffed, rolled up, and roasted.</p>

<p>Despite its simplicity, it&rsquo;s one of the coolest techniques I have ever seen, and it makes carving much much easier
since you don&rsquo;t have any bones to contend with while grappling a hot chicken fresh out of the oven.  I&rsquo;ve only done this
a few times, and it&rsquo;s already become my de-facto method for preparing whole chicken&mdash;the cool factor, the corpse
desecration, the ease of plating&hellip;  What&rsquo;s not to like?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Why Curry</h3>

<p>For this particular chicken, I decided to combine a thoroughly French technique with thoroughly un-French
flavors&mdash;Curry.</p>

<p>Even though I&rsquo;m all elitist and tend mix my own spices nowadays, my childhood was spent eating curries made with instant
powder mixes.  (<em>For the record, nothing wrong with curry powder mixes, assuming they&rsquo;re made from actual spices&hellip;</em>)
The most common of these was Madras Curry, particularly <a href="http://vietwah.com/Joomla/components/com_virtuemart/shop_image/product/fab54182fc7c87449f726b0e7cb3bec9.jpg">this brand</a>.
If the image link breaks, just google &ldquo;Ca Ri An Do&rdquo;.  It&rsquo;s a pretty unremarkable curry based heavily in turmeric,
definitely tending more towards the mild flavors that the Chinese/Japanese tend to flavor rather than the ripping hot
Vindaloo style you can see with some of the Indian curries.</p>

<p>But one of the problems I&rsquo;ve always had with this one in particular was that the sauce would have to get really thick
for the flavor to come out in the chicken.  In this past I&rsquo;d done this with judicious (read: heavy-handed) use of cream,
starch from potatoes, and reduction of liquid, but it never really got to the level I would have liked.  So when I was
thinking about variations on a Galantine, doing a stuffing with this curry powder was just about the first thing that
came to mind.</p>

<h3>The Chicken</h3>

<p>I can&rsquo;t possibly explain the technique behind a Galantine as well as the man himself, so if you didn&rsquo;t click on the
video link above, I suggest you do.  Go on.  I&rsquo;ll even put it down here as well.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kAekQ5fzfGM">Link</a></p>

<p>Watched it?  Good.  Pretty awesome, isn&rsquo;t it?  The stuffing is pretty simple:</p>

<ol>
<li>Finely dice yukon potatoes and carrots, and boil until tender</li>
<li>Mash up with a fork, dumping in generous helpings of curry powder and a pinch of salt</li>
<li>Add a touch of heavy cream for consistency, and because cream is delicious.</li>
</ol>


<p>In essence it was a rustic mashed potato.  I&rsquo;m sure a super fancy restaurant could do a potato and carrot puree or
something, but ain&rsquo;t nobody got time for that in this kitchen.  Stuff the chicken, truss it up, dust it with more curry
powder and salt, and stick it in the oven.  I stole my roasting technique from Thomas Keller&mdash;450 for ~25 minutes, then
370 until the internal temp of the thickest part of the thigh is 160&mdash;but really, whatever works.  Afterwards I just
made a sauce by deglazing the stuff in the roasting pan with some cream, and&mdash;<em>voila!</em></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-Chicken-Galantine/i-46XNmjz/0/L/DSC_2864-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-Chicken-Galantine/i-46XNmjz/0/L/DSC_2864-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Some people might say this technique is a bit old fashioned, but screw them.  Clearly they&rsquo;ve never deboned a chicken
with their hands&mdash;It&rsquo;s like ripping off a scab, except a million times more satisfying.  And delicious.  And chicken
wing lollipops?  Come on.  Ridiculous.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hipster Garlic Bread - Week 9, Garlic]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/22/hipster-garlic-bread-week-9-garlic/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-22T06:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/22/hipster-garlic-bread-week-9-garlic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Hipster-Garlic-Bread/i-XZVS2Lh/0/L/DSC_2581-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Hipster-Garlic-Bread/i-XZVS2Lh/0/L/DSC_2581-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Garlic is such an ubiquitous ingredient that I could have easily <a href="http://alexkuang.com/blog/2013/11/17/roast-leg-of-lamb/">cheated</a>
my way around this week&rsquo;s theme.  But where&rsquo;s the fun in that?  In the end, the decision came down to the deliciousness
of garlic bread and my curiosity for the concept of &ldquo;pull-apart bread&rdquo;, something that has been on the rise on
instagrammy/pinteresty/otherwise-artsy-craftsy sites lately.  The result was the above: some sort of garlic pull-apart
boule that&rsquo;s kind of a cross between your typical &ldquo;pull-apart bread&rdquo; and a hasselback potato.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There isn&rsquo;t really too much to write about; this is one of those things that an autistic monkey could probably do, which
makes it a great go-to for party prep.  But here are some general guidelines anyway.  For ingredients:</p>

<ul>
<li>1 sourdough boule, roughly the size of your face</li>
<li>1+ stick (~113 grams) of butter, room-temp</li>
<li>1+ bulb of garlic</li>
<li>sliced mozzarella</li>
<li>thyme</li>
<li>bacon (optional, but who doesn&rsquo;t like bacon?)</li>
</ul>


<p>Yeah, you read the butter quantity right.  Those are rough estimates, but I&rsquo;d say they&rsquo;re absolute bare minimums for the
butter and garlic.  If you cared that much about your health, why are you anywhere near a recipe that combines bread,
butter, and cheese in the first place?  Anyone who does this might as well do it properly and enjoy the full flavor; in
for a penny, in for a pound.  As for the garlic, well&hellip;  The toothbrush is an amazing invention, and chewing gum isn&rsquo;t
a terrible fallback.  As for the actual prep:</p>

<ol>
<li>Fire up the oven at 375 F</li>
<li>Chop off the top of the garlic horizontally, so that you get a nice cross-section view of all the cloves.  Stick it
in the oven to roast.  I&rsquo;d say about 30 minutes.</li>
<li>While that&rsquo;s happening, slice the bread and make a ~1.5in grid.  Just make sure to stop cutting about &frac14;-&frac12; inch
before hitting the bottom of the bread.</li>
<li>After the garlic is done, extract your cloves with a fork; they should be pretty mushy at this point.  Mash it
together with the softened butter, making sure to get the garlic nice and pasty and incorporated.  If you&rsquo;re using
unsalted butter, a nice dose of salt would be a great idea at this point.

<ul>
<li>Note: For those who store butter in the fridge and are lazy, melting the butter with the garlic will also work
here; however, melting it fully will make even distribution in the bread harder.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spread the garlic butter using a knife, and really get it into the cracks.  Shank the bread like you&rsquo;re in a state
prison and it looked at you wrong.</li>
<li>Stuff it some more with thyme, mozzarella, and so on.  Bake in the oven for, oh I dunno, ~30 minutes, depending on
the size of the bread.</li>
</ol>


<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Hipster-Garlic-Bread/i-BSbTwgh/0/L/DSC_2576-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Hipster-Garlic-Bread/i-BSbTwgh/0/L/DSC_2576-L.jpg</a>"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instant Ramen Gnocchi - Week 8, TV Show Inspired]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/instant-ramen-gnocchi-week-8-tv-show-inspired/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T22:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/instant-ramen-gnocchi-week-8-tv-show-inspired</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>(In which I am served a massive slice of humble pie)</em></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-HPM7fVm/0/L/DSC_2602-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-HPM7fVm/0/L/DSC_2602-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p><em>Mind of a Chef</em> is not just great background noise for getting work done, it also pads out the list of cool and
unusual things I&rsquo;d like to try in the kitchen.  Out of all the things I&rsquo;d seen on the show, making gnocchi out of ramen
seemed among the most unusual and also among the simplest, so I decided it would be a prime target for this week&rsquo;s &ldquo;TV
Show Inspired&rdquo; theme.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Failure</h2>

<p>Because of its apparent simplicity, I decided to take this on on the night before my flight.  In an uncharacteristic
bout of hubris, my thoughts went something like&hellip; <em>It&rsquo;s just instant ramen blended with milk, right?  No need for a
methodical approach or anything, just toss everything in.</em>  Of course, as the Universe is wont to do, my sloppiness was
rewarded promptly with miserable failure.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-mzq93d8/0/L/DSC_2469-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-mzq93d8/0/L/DSC_2469-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>I started off by boiling the ramen in milk, and dumping all of it into a food processor with a bunch of egg yolks.  The
first hint that things were off probably should have come at this stage.  The dough held a consistency that was closer
to batter than anything, and there were far too many lumps to be normal.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-FsDKq22/0/L/DSC_2470-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-FsDKq22/0/L/DSC_2470-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-fNZCkgb/0/L/DSC_2474-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-fNZCkgb/0/L/DSC_2474-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>As anyone who isn&rsquo;t an idiot should have predicted <em>(ahem)</em>, as soon as the mixture was piped into boiling water, it
completely fell apart.  Even reducing the pot to a bare simmer, it could not hold together at all, and just ended up a
lumpy mess.  I tried frying the results of this, and piping the raw batter straight into the pan, but there&rsquo;s just no
fighting physics.</p>

<p>The best that could have happened here would have been something resembling a grit cake, and that would require some
stabilization in the way of flour / eggs / what-have-you, which I didn&rsquo;t have since I&rsquo;d cleaned out my food supplies in
preparation for my 2-week trip the next day.  &hellip;  Yep.</p>

<p>On hindsight, it&rsquo;s pretty easy to spot the things that went wrong:</p>

<ul>
<li>First off, the ramen should not have been boiled.  By the time it&rsquo;s finished boiling, it&rsquo;s already absorbed all the
liquid it can, which means that it will not integrate with any more that&rsquo;s added, no matter how much time it spends in
the food processor.</li>
<li>Along the lines of the above, I should have used much much less liquid, since I want barely enough to turn the ramen
into a dough.</li>
<li>The eggs yolks were added way too soon into the mixture.  The residual heat from the boiling liquid probably cooked
the yolks before they could be integrated, resulting in more of lumps and robbing the dough of any thickening effects
from the yolks overall.</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Retry</h2>

<p>With that spectacular SNAFU under my belt, I&rsquo;d resolved that I&rsquo;d make another proper attempt as soon as I touched back
down in Boston.  Luckily, this time went much better&mdash;Good enough to actually write out, in fact.  Here are the
ingredients I eventually settled on:</p>

<ul>
<li>500ml whole milk</li>
<li>4 egg yolks</li>
<li>2 packs instant ramen (I used Nong Shim, ~119g apiece)</li>
</ul>


<p>First off, boil 500ml milk.  Break the ramen bricks up and soak them in the milk.  There should be just barely enough
milk to cover.  Take the ramen out as soon as they become pliable enough to no longer be considered bricks&mdash;this should
only take a minute, two tops.  Dump the ramen with ~200ml of the milk into a food processor, and blend until it reaches
a dough-like consistency.  <em>(Note: I have a decently sturdy Cuisinart, and the dough had enough thickness to make it
move, so I&rsquo;d say aim for something along those lines)</em>  When everything is mixed together and cool enough to touch, add
the egg yolks and give it another few pulses to incorporate.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-SFK4xfS/0/L/DSC_2584-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-SFK4xfS/0/L/DSC_2584-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Now that looks like a proper dough.  Bring a large pot of salted water to boil, then scoop the dough into a pastry bag
(a ziploc with the corner cut out also works).  Pipe out an inch or so at a time into the water, slicing pieces off with
a straight edge.  I used the back of a paring knife for this part.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-mrqgdF2/0/L/DSC_2589-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-mrqgdF2/0/L/DSC_2589-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Never have I been so glad to see my food looking like poo in a toilet.</p>

<p>As soon as the pieces start floating, get them onto a greased plate.  Fry in butter, then serve as preferred.</p>

<h2>Impressions</h2>

<p>DISCLAIMER: I realized soon after tasting these that I have not actually had potato gnocchi before, so I have nothing to
draw a comparison to.  I&rsquo;ll make it a point to get some from Whole Foods or something ASAP.</p>

<p>Overall the gnocchi had a very interesting texture.  For reasons unknown, I&rsquo;d always expected these to have more bite or
chew to them, but they tasted more creamy than anything.  Simultaneously, they were much heavier than I thought they
would be.  No big surprise here, since they&rsquo;re just pulverized starch and milk.  In the headline picture I served them
with pork belly and spinach, and for my second portion I used pork and miso corn.  Both times I was going for a sort of
&ldquo;deconstructed ramen&rdquo; theme, which worked out fairly well.  The only thing I&rsquo;d change is the portion size&mdash;Something
this heavy is much better suited as an appetizer or a first course.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
