<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vim | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/vim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-18T21:03:02-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some CH Backport vimporn]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/02/some-ch-backport-vimporn/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-02T20:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/02/some-ch-backport-vimporn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In some ways, the curehappiness backports came at the perfect time, since I&rsquo;d been looking for something to sharpen my
vim skills on.  Technically I work in vim day-to-day, but usually the rest of the mental activity involved with coding
end up pushing my vim-awareness more to the side than I&rsquo;d like.  This backport, however, was heavy on repetition but
otherwise braindead, so it made the perfect set of practice exercises.  And since I had such fun (hey, it was a really
boring Sunday afternoon&hellip;), I figured I&rsquo;d share in case anyone else finds this useful&mdash;or even better, has suggestions
to make similar tasks more efficient in the future.  Please note that this is a rather quick fly-by and assumes moderate
familiarity with vim mechanics.  I&rsquo;ll probably do more slow, detailed posts in the future&hellip;</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Start</h3>

<p>Since I had all the posts in html form, using <code>:set paste</code> and copy-pasting from the browser seemed the most
straightforward.  Or at least, more straightforward than trying to manually un-mangle everything in the post after being
wrung through wordpress.  For most of the posts, the paste result looked something like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/start.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p>Not too awful, but the TODO is obvious:</p>

<ol>
<li>Needs a banner image</li>
<li>Lines need to be wrapped (not strictly necessary, but personal pet peeve)</li>
<li>Ingredients + Methodology need to be de-dented</li>
<li>Ingredients needs to be an unordered list</li>
<li>Methodology needs to be an ordered list.</li>
</ol>


<p>Technically I guess headings need to be put in too, but since headings are simply <code># HEADING 1</code>, <code>## HEADING 2</code>, etc, in
markdown, that&rsquo;s pretty trivial.</p>

<h3>Banner image</h3>

<p>This bit was easy.  I have a plugin installed called <code>vim-snipmate</code> (check it out
<a href="https://github.com/garbas/vim-snipmate">here</a>) that&rsquo;s just built for stuff like this.  Simply put, defining the snippet
below:</p>

<p>```
snippet img</p>

<pre><code>{% img center ${1} %}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>allowed me to type <code>img&lt;TAB&gt;</code> and it would insert <code>{% img center %}</code>, with my cursor right after the <code>center</code> and ready
to drop in my picture url.</p>

<h3>Wrapping lines</h3>

<p>vim has a normal mode command, <code>gq</code>, that does this quite well.  Personally I like using visual line mode (<code>V</code>) to
select the text to wrap, but using it with a motion (e.g., <code>gq}</code> to wrap a block) works as well.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/gq-before.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/gq-after.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p>I only wrapped the plain paragraphs here, as there is still some fancy dedenting and formatting to do with the Ingredients
and Methodology sections first.</p>

<h3>De-denting</h3>

<p>The vim command for de-denting is <code>&lt;</code>.  Once again, combining with visual line mode or a motion (ex: <code>&lt;}</code>) makes it
quick and easy.  (Just in case&mdash;Yes, <code>&gt;</code> is the command for indenting)</p>

<h3>Ingredients => Unordered List</h3>

<p>This one, I&rsquo;ll admit, is a little snazzy.  I used the lesser-known cousin of visual and visual line mode, visual block
mode (accessed via <code>&lt;Ctrl&gt;-V</code>).  Once selecting the first characters of the lines I wanted with visual block, I could
hit <code>&lt;Shift-I&gt;</code> to drop into insert mode before current character, <code>-</code> to insert what I wanted, then <code>&lt;ESC&gt;</code> to apply
to everything in the selection.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/ul-before.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/ul-during.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/ul-after.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p>Note that this is also a great way to mass-comment blocks of code in languages that only support single line comments
with <code>#</code> or whatnot.</p>

<h3>Methodology => Ordered List</h3>

<p>And of course, the best is for last.  Ordered lists in markdown, logically, can be formatted something like this:</p>

<p><code>
1. item 1
2. item 2
3. item 3
</code></p>

<p>However, it&rsquo;s actually possible to cheat and still get ordered list output by doing:</p>

<p><code>
1. item 1
1. item 2
1. item 3
</code></p>

<p>It turns out that the markdown spec doesn&rsquo;t care about the order of the numbering as long as the lines begin with
numbers in that format.  So technically, I could use the same trick as the Ingredients Unordered List except inserting
<code>1.</code>, and I&rsquo;d be done.</p>

<p>&hellip;  But where&rsquo;s the fun in that?</p>

<p>So here&rsquo;s another tidbit: in vim, if you place the cursor over a number and hit <code>&lt;Ctrl&gt;-A</code> in normal mode, it increments
the number.  In a very smart way, too&mdash;it takes into account all of the digits, not just the one under the cursor.
Using this, it&rsquo;s pretty easy to write a vim macro (namely, a series of recorded keystrokes that can be repeated).</p>

<p>Rather than explain in long form, it seems easier just paste the sequence and annotate it.</p>

<p>```sh
qq<sup>yaWjP</sup>^^Aq # Complete keystroke sequence</p>

<pre><code>         # Note that ^A is one character--see below for details
</code></pre>

<p>qq   # Start recording keystrokes into the q register
^    # Go to first non-blank character of line
yaW  # yank (copy) a Word&mdash;Capital W means a &ldquo;word&rdquo; is terminated only by spaces, not punctuation like &ldquo;&ndash;&rdquo;
j    # Go down a line
P^   # Paste before cursor, then go back to first non-blank character
^A   # Increment number
q    # Stop recording
```</p>

<p>It ends up looking something like this, played out:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/mac-1.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/mac-2.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ch-backport-vim/mac-3.png" width="598" height="440"></p>

<p><em>(Aside: I should start making gifs again for stuff like this&hellip;  Perhaps another day when I have more time.)</em></p>

<p>Once the macro is recorded, it can be played back via <code>@q</code>, or whichever register it was recorded into.  More
importantly, because it resets to the right positions in the lines and moves down automatically, it can actually be
repeated!  e.g., <code>2@q</code> turns this:</p>

<p><code>
1. item 1
item 2
item 3
</code></p>

<p>into this:</p>

<p><code>
1. item 1
2. item 2
3. item 3
</code></p>

<p>Writing macros to position in a looping way like this is another post altogether, but suffice to say this saved a TON of
time over multiple posts.  Granted, it still depends on the <code>1.</code> being inserted manually, but that&rsquo;s pretty trivial I
think.</p>

<p>Another neat thing that might not immediately be obvious is that regular yanking (or copying, if you will) goes into the
same registers as macro recordings.  So you can use <code>"qp</code> to paste the contents of your macro into a buffer to map it to
keys or functions (ex: <code>nnoremap &lt;leader&gt;o ^yaW[...]</code>).</p>

<p>Furthermore, this means that if a recording goes wrong, you can just paste it out, edit it, then select and <code>"qy</code> (or
similar) to yank back the edited form.  The only caveat is that certain characters like <code>^A</code> may paste out and LOOK like
two characters, but is infact only one character.  Not a big deal if you&rsquo;re just yanking and replacing text, but it can
be a weird GOTCHA if you&rsquo;re trying to write a macro by hand or something.  (In this particular case, the <code>^A</code> character
can be obtained in insert mode via <code>&lt;Ctrl-V&gt;&lt;Ctrl-A&gt;</code>, but it pays to watch out in general for stuff like this)</p>

<p>So there you have it, ladies and gentlemen&mdash;My idea of fun on a Sunday afternoon&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
