<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: food | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-23T07:43:12-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roast Leg of Lamb]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/roast-leg-of-lamb/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-17T12:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/roast-leg-of-lamb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Leg-of-Lamb/i-q4M6vbN/0/L/DSC_2277-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Leg-of-Lamb/i-q4M6vbN/0/L/DSC_2277-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Last weekend I saw a giant leg of New Zealand lamb that looked way too good to pass up, crazy Whole Foods prices or not.
Huge roasted joints of meat are always a win with me but I strongly prefer bone in; there&rsquo;s just so much more flavor
that way.  I took the basic steps from <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5qvEdCmD8Pk">this video</a> by Thomas Keller, using
an oven temp of 325 for ~1hr and frenching the tip of the bone to aid in carving.  I finished the last few minutes with
a cranked up broiler to really get a nice crust on the surface.</p>

<p>There was one problem I had with the conventional wisdom, though: laying the herbs on/around the meat and just seasoning
the surface doesn&rsquo;t seem like it would be enough to really get that taste in there, especially with something this
thick.  So I took a cue from how cloves are used in ham, substituting the cloves for garlic and the ham joint for a lamb
leg.  Spearing the garlic with small sprigs of rosemary added just the right extra punch, and ended up staining the
garlic green as a bonus.</p>

<p>I would consider this experiment a success.  Embedding the garlic really gets the flavor into the meat, and the rosemary
adds a lot to the presentation as well. If nothing else, it can be an excuse to crack some Monty Python shrubbery jokes
at the dinner table.  Chances to do that don&rsquo;t come around nearly as often as they should.</p>

<p>(More photos can be found <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Leg-of-Lamb/">here</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Big Bowl O Beef]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/big-bowl-o-beef/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T21:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/big-bowl-o-beef</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to test out how images worked with the blog, but had nothing imminent to write about.  Since kittens are
already taken, here&rsquo;s a picture of a big bowl of beef with kimchi and rice.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Bowl-O-Beef-2013/i-FtTgtWC/0/L/DSC_2245-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Bowl-O-Beef-2013/i-FtTgtWC/0/L/DSC_2245-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Not too bad.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
