<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: food | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-26T11:06:20-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicken Shahi Korma - Week 3, One Pot]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/19/chicken-shahi-week-3-one-pot/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-19T10:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/19/chicken-shahi-week-3-one-pot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-KPv4qLJ/0/L/DSC_2381-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-KPv4qLJ/0/L/DSC_2381-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>One thing I&rsquo;ve noticed about the weekly food challenges is that it syncs very well with my new self-imposed weekly post
quota.  This works out nicely for me, but at the same time it provides a very convenient cop-out from having to write
anything new, e.g. about tech.  While at the end of the day I&rsquo;m still writing more than I would have, I&rsquo;m wondering if
it&rsquo;d be a good idea to stop counting these towards the weekly quota, or only count them partially.  Another option would
be to pick and choose which challenges to limit the volume, but cherry-picking challenges is for weenies.  Thoughts for
the future, I guess.</p>

<p>At any rate, the &ldquo;point&rdquo; of this week&rsquo;s theme is simplicity&mdash;Getting good flavor out of an easy set up, i.e. &ldquo;one pot&rdquo;.
It seemed like a good time to test out my burgeoning indian food skills, but as it turns out the most complicated part
was just the combination of the spices.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>Ingredients</h4>

<ul>
<li>Large spices

<ul>
<li>8 green cardamom pods</li>
<li>6 cloves</li>
<li>3-inch stick of cinnamon</li>
<li>3 bay leaves</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Small spices

<ul>
<li>1 tsp ground cumin</li>
<li>1 tsp ground coriander</li>
<li>&frac14; tsp ground cayenne</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>4 lb chicken thighs</li>
<li>1 cup plain yogurt</li>
<li>Handful of chopped cilantro</li>
<li>Handful of slivered blanched almonds</li>
</ul>


<p>Normally for non-baking work I prefer to cook by taste and instinct rather than measuring too precisely.  But in this
case spices can be quite strong, and it&rsquo;ll probably take years before I could do that effectively, so it&rsquo;s better to be
on the safe side.  For the curious, here&rsquo;s roughly what the spice setup looks like for 4 lb of chicken:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-JzpM4D6/0/L/DSC_2372-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-JzpM4D6/0/L/DSC_2372-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>I like cilantro so I tend to put in a bit extra; most people will probably want a bit less than what&rsquo;s shown above.
Another quick note is that the chicken thighs should preferably come with skin and bone; again, just more flavor that
way.  You could do it with boneless skinless thighs, or even breasts, but come on.</p>

<p>There really isn&rsquo;t much to this, technique-wise:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>First, combine the small spices and cilantro with the yogurt, then season the chicken pieces with salt and pepper.</p></li>
<li><p>Heat up a healthy amount of oil in your pot, then toss in the large spices and give them a quick stir.  Start
browning the chicken on medium-high heat.  The browning can be done in a separate pan, but 1) you&rsquo;d be missing out on
the flavor from the brown bits at the bottom, and 2) the theme is &ldquo;one pot&rdquo; and that&rsquo;d be cheating.  Don&rsquo;t
over-crowd&mdash;You really want the color on there, so work in multiple batches if necessary.  By the time the chicken&rsquo;s
done, the kitchen should already be smelling delicious.</p></li>
<li><p>Remove all the chicken from the pot, keeping the oil from frying, and toss in some almonds.  As soon as they start
browning, re-add all the chicken along with any juices that may have appeared.  Add the yogurt sauce and give it a good
mix, then cover and let everything simmer on low for 20 minutes or so.</p></li>
<li><p>When ready, turn the heat back up and let the sauce reduce.  Stir gently once in a while to make sure nothing is
burning and sticking.  The final thickness of the sauce is ultimately preference, but in western terms it should at
<em>least</em> pass the &ldquo;coat the back of the spoon&rdquo; test and then some.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>And since this is, after all, &ldquo;one pot&rdquo;, here is a picture of everything in one pot <em>(excuse the desaturation, I blame
the steam.)</em>:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-M9sWXcq/0/L/DSC_2379-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-M9sWXcq/0/L/DSC_2379-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>When everything is ready, serve with basmati rice or a nice piece of flatbread.  And yes, like most curries, this tastes
even better after sitting around for a day or two.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pierogi - Week 2, Polish]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/13/pierogi-week-2-polish/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T11:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/13/pierogi-week-2-polish</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pierogi/i-JHfpDKq/0/L/DSC_2369-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pierogi/i-JHfpDKq/0/L/DSC_2369-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Week 2&rsquo;s theme is Polish, a cuisine that I basically have never touched, or so I thought.  According to the
<a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/52weeksofcooking/comments/1ujvk2/week_2_introduction_thread_polish/">introduction thread</a>,
Polish food involves a lot of meat and potatoes, and the list of example foods included golabki which I&rsquo;d made a bunch
of times already under its Russian name golubtsy.  But choosing that felt too much like cheating, so I went with pierogi
instead.</p>

<p>Since I had only heard of the term pierogi and had no idea what it actually was or what was involved, the first obvious
stop was Google.  A few quick searches revealed that it was the polish equivalent of a filled dumpling/ravioli, and the potato
filling + sour cream in the skin distinguished it from all the other types of dumplings I had seen.  Since the skin
was a bit more foreign and required some resting time, I decided to start with that first.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>Skin</h4>

<p>Normally I&rsquo;m the first guy to start screaming about scales and precise weights when anything involves dough, but for
things like dumplings I believe that approximations are perfectly fine, and a scale is probably excessive.
Nevertheless, since this was the first time I decided to jot down some numbers for consistency&rsquo;s sake:</p>

<ul>
<li>250g flour (~2 cups)</li>
<li>50g softened/melted butter (~&frac14; cup)</li>
<li>160g sour cream (~&frac12; cup)</li>
<li>1 egg</li>
<li>pinch of salt</li>
</ul>


<p>I combined the flour with the egg and salt to make a crumbly mixture, then added the butter and sour cream.  The dough
incorporated very easily after a few minutes of working, and was very pliable.  I let it rest for about 30 minutes while
I prepared the filling.  Resting only made the dough even softer because of the relaxing gluten; I also suspect that the
sour cream has a loosening effect like a weaker version of ascorbic acid in puff pastry dough, but I&rsquo;m not 100% on that
so don&rsquo;t quote me.</p>

<h4>Filling</h4>

<p>The filling was exceedingly simple.  I just boiled up some yellow potatoes, and mashed them without liquid.  The
seasoning was salt, pepper, and shredded sharp cheddar; I&rsquo;d say the cheddar was somewhere around 1/3 to &frac12; of the
volume of mash that I had.  After everything was mixed, I stepped away for a cup of coffee (and to let the filling fall
to room temp so it wasn&rsquo;t burning hot, if you care about that sort of thing).</p>

<p>After the filling was prepared and cooled, I rolled out the dough into a ~1/8 inch sheet.  I aimed for something a
little bit thicker than ravioli skins, but not by much.  But since I didn&rsquo;t have a dough cutter and actually needed
circular skins, I decided to use a drinking glass instead:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pierogi/i-QX4VMGK/0/L/DSC_2337-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pierogi/i-QX4VMGK/0/L/DSC_2337-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>After pressing out all the rounds, there was a non-trivial amount of dough scrap left which I felt bad about.  I was
feeling daring so I just re-worked and re-rolled it to get as many rounds as possible; the only thing I&rsquo;d note here is
that an additional resting period is necessary for the gluten to re-relax, so I&rsquo;d recommend filling the pressed rounds
while waiting for that to happen.  Or, for the more lazy amongst us, I suppose the scraps could just be cut up and saved
to be dropped in soup or something&hellip;  But who wants to do that?</p>

<p>Wrapping is fairly easy.  Just fold the skin over a small mound of the potato mixture then press the edges together
with your fingers.  If the edges don&rsquo;t stick, you probably over-floured your board or something, so add a bit of water
to help it along.  To really seal things in and make them look prettier, press the edges again with the tines of a fork.
(For those who really care, the gallery at the bottom of the post has how much filling I used for each)</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pierogi/i-c2DwTKD/0/L/DSC_2353-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pierogi/i-c2DwTKD/0/L/DSC_2353-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>A few of them are slightly lopsided, but not too bad for a first batch.</p>

<h4>Impressions</h4>

<p>Most sources online recommend boiling the pierogis and then frying them with butter and onions to serve.  Since these
are essentially potatoes in dough, I thought they&rsquo;d need a bit of help so I used roughly sliced shallots instead, and
added some kielbasa on the side.  Can&rsquo;t have a &ldquo;meat and potatoes&rdquo; style meal without the meat.</p>

<p>I think the biggest surprise was that pierogis are really &ldquo;go big or go home&rdquo;.  The quantities above are enough to make
roughly 20 skins, or a full two dozen if you really want to stretch it.  The filling needed for that amount of skin
could probably be made from one decent sized yellow potato, <em>maybe</em> two.  And since nobody wants to boil and mash one
potato, that means that you have to make about 100 at once for it to be worth the time.  Alternatively this could
probably be a nice use for leftovers of regular mashed potato, but probably not if you like your mash really creamy.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t really speak to authenticity or anything since I&rsquo;ve never actually had pierogis, but I thought they were pretty
nice taste-wise.  Personally they reminded me of fried ravioli, except slightly thicker and more rustic.  I went in
expecting a super heavy mouthful of starch, but the texture was surprisingly light and the sour cream in the skin helped
things along.  I still don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;d eat these alone, at least not the variety filled with just potato and
cheese&mdash;Even with the shallots, the dish needed the extra punch from the kielbasa.  However, some bacon in the filling
might change my mind.  Adding bacon is never a bad idea.</p>

<p>(Full gallery <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pierogi">here</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ramen Cake - Week 1, Eggs]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/06/ramen-cake-week-1-eggs/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-06T13:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/06/ramen-cake-week-1-eggs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&mdash;Or, really ghetto okonomiyaki&hellip;</em></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-zJ4NmjL/0/L/DSC_2315-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-zJ4NmjL/0/L/DSC_2315-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>It should come as no surprise to anyone that I&rsquo;m subscribed to
<a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/52weeksofcooking">/r/52weeksofcooking</a>.  The tl;dr is that each week, the subreddit chooses a
food &ldquo;theme&rdquo;&mdash;an ingredient, ethnicity, or some other idea&mdash;and users post dishes that they make according to the theme.
I&rsquo;ve always thought that the idea seemed like a lot of fun, so what better time to start than the new year?  If nothing
else, it makes good blog fodder.</p>

<p>Week 1&rsquo;s theme is eggs, which is a nice and easy start to this little series of experiments.  For this theme I chose
what I like to call &ldquo;ramen cake&rdquo;.  The idea is roughly the same as that of okonomiyaki&mdash;In fact, I got the idea after
watching the corresponding <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=od2YWgQmeo4">video</a> on Cooking With Dog (an excellent channel
in general, by the way).  It&rsquo;s a nice way to have ramen that doesn&rsquo;t come in a bowl of soup, and with the right
combination of fillings it could even be something approaching nutritious.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First, boil your ramen and set aside.  I recommend removing the ramen 30 seconds or so before it&rsquo;s fully cooked.  It&rsquo;ll
continue cooking in the pan later, and overcooking just results in mush&mdash;especially when freeze-dried noodles are
involved.  In the meantime, prepare any other toppings you need as well.  For the pictures in this post I used nong shim
ramen with some sardines and quickly stir-fried bok choy, but basically anything works.  Finally, beat about 3-4 large
eggs (depending on your preferences) until the yolks and whites are evenly incorporated.</p>

<p>Heat up a well-oiled, preferably non-stick, pan over medium-high heat.  Drop the eggs, and as soon as the bottom starts
cooking add the other ingredients and the ramen. Jostle it a bit as necessary to distribute everything, the leave it
alone to set.  Now is a great time to garnish with scallions and add some sauce&mdash;to keep it real, I like using oyster
sauce mixed with part of the ramen packet and a bit of peanut oil to adjust for viscosity.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-xtFsvCZ/0/L/DSC_2304-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-xtFsvCZ/0/L/DSC_2304-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>When the bottom has solidified enough to handle without disintegrating, it&rsquo;s ready to flip.  Just make sure that the egg
hasn&rsquo;t entirely cooked through yet&mdash;after the flip, we want it to drip downwards a bit and bind all of the ingredients
into one cohesive mass.  Also note that flipping can be a bit hit or miss sometimes, depending on a combination of
spatula size, pan skills, and luck.  One easy option is to cut it into pieces in the pan, and just flip the pieces
individually.</p>

<p>In this case, the culinary gods were with me, and I made the flip successfully:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-BNVnCJp/0/L/DSC_2307-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-BNVnCJp/0/L/DSC_2307-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>After the flip, let everything keep frying.  The goal here is to let the rest of the egg cook through and caramelize the
ramen a little bit along the way&mdash;Extra points if the bottom is slightly crispy, like so:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-M4rt2bc/0/L/DSC_2310-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-M4rt2bc/0/L/DSC_2310-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>While waiting for everything to cook, feel free to slather on more sauce.  Either way, it should be ready to be shoveled
into faces after a few minutes.</p>

<p>(Full gallery <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake">here</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ramen Stock]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/04/ramen-stock/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-04T11:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/04/ramen-stock</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been sick as a dog for the last couple of days, so I guess this week I&rsquo;ll keep it light.  Since it&rsquo;s about 0
degrees F outside right now, what better time to mention ramen?</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-7f9FtLM/0/L/photo-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-7f9FtLM/0/L/photo-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>The above was made with pork belly, spinach, and pickled mushrooms.  I&rsquo;ll probably write everything up in more detail
when I&rsquo;m feeling more prolific, but I&rsquo;d like to take this chance to mention that a great use for the leftover bones
(say, from a roast leg of lamb, or a chicken carcass) is ramen stock.  Just roast the bones in the oven and stick them
in a pot with a few aromatics and vegetables: onions, leeks, carrots, mushrooms, and so on.  Leave it to simmer for a
few hours, and boom.  Stock.  If it&rsquo;s not feasible to leave the stove on, a crock pot would probably work just as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roast Leg of Lamb]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/roast-leg-of-lamb/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-17T12:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/roast-leg-of-lamb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Leg-of-Lamb/i-q4M6vbN/0/L/DSC_2277-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Leg-of-Lamb/i-q4M6vbN/0/L/DSC_2277-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Last weekend I saw a giant leg of New Zealand lamb that looked way too good to pass up, crazy Whole Foods prices or not.
Huge roasted joints of meat are always a win with me but I strongly prefer bone in; there&rsquo;s just so much more flavor
that way.  I took the basic steps from <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5qvEdCmD8Pk">this video</a> by Thomas Keller, using
an oven temp of 325 for ~1hr and frenching the tip of the bone to aid in carving.  I finished the last few minutes with
a cranked up broiler to really get a nice crust on the surface.</p>

<p>There was one problem I had with the conventional wisdom, though: laying the herbs on/around the meat and just seasoning
the surface doesn&rsquo;t seem like it would be enough to really get that taste in there, especially with something this
thick.  So I took a cue from how cloves are used in ham, substituting the cloves for garlic and the ham joint for a lamb
leg.  Spearing the garlic with small sprigs of rosemary added just the right extra punch, and ended up staining the
garlic green as a bonus.</p>

<p>I would consider this experiment a success.  Embedding the garlic really gets the flavor into the meat, and the rosemary
adds a lot to the presentation as well. If nothing else, it can be an excuse to crack some Monty Python shrubbery jokes
at the dinner table.  Chances to do that don&rsquo;t come around nearly as often as they should.</p>

<p>(More photos can be found <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Leg-of-Lamb/">here</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
