<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: food | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-20T19:51:17-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Fuck It Friday" - Weeks 12 + 13, Street Food + Potatoes]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/fuck-it-its-friday-weeks-12-13/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T17:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/fuck-it-its-friday-weeks-12-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-5WQTNMH/0/L/DSC_3030-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-5WQTNMH/0/L/DSC_3030-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>This <em>was</em> going to be a big ol' fancy affair.  I set out to knock out two weeks' worth of challenges at once, and take
advantage of some sweet, sweet morels at the market.  Unfortunately, the potatoes decided to be uncooperative, so here
we are.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The original idea was to make curried fried clams as the &ldquo;street food&rdquo; portion of the challenge; luckily that turned out
pretty well.  I first laced some flour with turmeric, cumin, garam masala, cayenne, and salt, then soaked some minced
clams in milk.  A few minutes in some 350-degree oil later, voila!  One note though: rest them in parchment paper or a
mesh rack; paper towels will just end up steaming them as they cool, ruining the crunchy texture.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-7Rn3Gpg/0/L/DSC_3023-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-7Rn3Gpg/0/L/DSC_3023-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>While the curryish flavors got a bit overwhelmed by the tartar sauce, I like to think that it provided a bit more depth
to the flavor.  Placebo effect, anyone?</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s where things get a bit dicey.  The original plan was to slice up a bunch of potatoes and stack them, then form a
mini-cake by surrounding it with a potato-morel &ldquo;icing&rdquo;.  However, I decided to be a dunce and add some morel-induced
cream, which ended up turning the potato-morel combo into more of a wet puree than a potato cake.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-kc4j69J/0/L/DSC_3025-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-kc4j69J/0/L/DSC_3025-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>To salvage the situation, I ended up pan-frying the slices and combining them with the puree, making something like a
mutated gratin dauphinois.</p>

<p>At this point, I had given up all delusions of pretentious grandeur and decided, &ldquo;Fuck it, it&rsquo;s Friday&rdquo;.  Thus, I turned the
entire thing on its head, going from <em>frou-frou potato cake</em> to <em>giant plate of stuff</em> with cole slaw and extra tartar
sauce.  All things considered, it could have turned out much worse; at least it was still delicious, and that&rsquo;s what
really counts.  And I suppose the &ldquo;pile of food&rdquo; format is more appropriate for the street food theme anyway.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-vjNkfpR/0/L/DSC_3035-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-vjNkfpR/0/L/DSC_3035-L.jpg</a>"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Follow The Honey]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/05/follow-the-honey/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-05T20:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/05/follow-the-honey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-kDb523C/0/L/DSC_2978-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-kDb523C/0/L/DSC_2978-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>A few weeks ago I was dragged somewhat skeptically to a honey store.  Yep, that&rsquo;s right&mdash;a honey store.  A store, that&rsquo;s
dedicated to honey.  I know.  Strange as it may sound, it&rsquo;s actually a thing.  But after my (thus far only) trip,
I&rsquo;m a convert.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The storefront is very cozy, nestled within the basement of a building in Harvard Square.  The inside is all amber and,
to the surprise of absolutely nobody, decorated with various bee-related paraphernalia&mdash;Everything from cards with bees
to beeswax candles.  Why couldn&rsquo;t I have known about this place back when we were doing
<a href="http://alexkuang.com/blog/2010/10/01/caneles-bordelais/">caneles</a>?  The first attempts with copper molds all but
required beeswax; hell, I still prefer that to cooking spray.  But I digress.</p>

<p>The workers were all super happy and friendly.  I wonder if it was the general almost-hippie peaceful vibe of the
interior, but they almost seemed <em>too</em> happy.  As in I was almost tempted to ask for the, ahem, &ldquo;special&rdquo; honey, so to
speak.  In any case, they were all perfectly pleasant and helpful and eager to offer samples from the honey bar.  Did
I mention they have a honey bar?  It&rsquo;s absolutely bizarre.  The first question I was asked was &ldquo;what flavors do you like
in your honey?&rdquo;  <em>I have no idea, are you kidding me?  I&rsquo;ve only had the kind in the bear bottles.</em></p>

<p>I ended up trying a few varieties ranging from the savory and spicy to the sweet and fruity.  And it&rsquo;s like coffee&mdash;Once
you have the real stuff, you don&rsquo;t want to go back unless you have no other choice.  For my part, I walked out with
nearly 3 digits' worth of merch.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-xBT3tP7/0/L/DSC_2989-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-xBT3tP7/0/L/DSC_2989-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>The most interesting is probably the Hawaiian honey, which is from bees gathering from flowers off the side of volcanos
in Hawaii.  If that sounds exotic, don&rsquo;t worry&mdash;It&rsquo;s got a correspondingly exotic price tag, about 30-some dollars for 8
oz (226g).  I bought two jars: one was Kiawe honey infused separately with lilikoi flowers, and one uninfused Macadamia
honey.  The former actually came in semi-solid form (common for raw honey) and packed a sharp passion fruit flavor.  The
latter was a more &ldquo;typical&rdquo; liquid texture, and rosey gold with a mild nutty flavor.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-RqWvFwQ/0/L/DSC_2990-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-RqWvFwQ/0/L/DSC_2990-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>In addition to these, I also walked out with two jars of honey gathered from Oaxaca, Mexico.  Oaxaca&rsquo;s a great
region for food agriculture&mdash;Some pretty good coffee comes out of there as well.  This honey was very savory, almost
spicey, and a dark maple-syrupy color.  It was also very reasonably priced, something like $12-13 for I would guess 12oz
out of the keg.  Oh, did I mention there were kegs?  Honey, <em>on tap</em>.  Whodaknownit?</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-7QKxJ2M/0/L/DSC_2977-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-7QKxJ2M/0/L/DSC_2977-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-hBBmCWs/0/L/DSC_2991-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Other/Follow-The-Honey/i-hBBmCWs/0/L/DSC_2991-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>If it isn&rsquo;t obvious by now, I&rsquo;d recommend anyone in the area to stop by at least once, regardless of inherent interest
in bees and honey.  If nothing else there are very nice people giving out free samples, and who knows?  Maybe just a few
tastes will be enough.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oysters with Lemon Pearls - Week 11 Molecular]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/27/oysters-with-lemon-pearls-week-11-molecular/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-27T17:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/27/oysters-with-lemon-pearls-week-11-molecular</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-5NhtLD4/0/L/DSC_2972-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-5NhtLD4/0/L/DSC_2972-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>I was really looking forward to the Molecular theme, since I&rsquo;d been itching to play with some of this newfangled
Modernist Cuisine stuff for a while now.  So I went ahead and ordered a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Modernist-Pantry-Spherification-Kit/dp/B008657GS0/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1401210725&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=spherification+kit">spherification kit</a>
from amazon, and came up with the idea of pairing spheres with oysters.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The kit came with fairly straightforward instructions, so I just followed those.  For my liquid base I used lemonade
mixed with lemon juice for acidity.  I added 2 grams of sodium citrate, since the kit recommended that for potentially
acidic solutions.</p>

<p>The spheres came together fairly well, though it was pretty slow going at first.  I&rsquo;m also displeased that the syringe
included with the kit is one use only&hellip;</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-p99X433/0/L/DSC_2968-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-p99X433/0/L/DSC_2968-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>The spheres look good, but I think that&rsquo;s about all that I can say about them positively.  Taste-wise, they were
slightly rubbery and the insides were way too viscous&mdash;Closer to maple syrup than juice.  Maybe it was the
disappointment from expecting something closer to the &ldquo;popping boba&rdquo; found in bubble tea/frozen yogurt, but overall I
just found the texture unpleasant.  In addition, the alginate stifled the acidity in the lemon and left a funny taste in
my mouth, making the pearls taste basically like jello filled with slightly off sugar syrup.</p>

<p>All in all, I would have been better served making plain old lemon jello with the oysters, which is what I&rsquo;ve done in
the past.  It&rsquo;s possible that I did something terribly wrong despite my self-perceived precision, or perhaps this kit
just didn&rsquo;t include the right substances for this set of circumstances.  Half the instructions seemed to exist for
upselling, e.g., &ldquo;buy our slotted spoon!&rdquo;, &ldquo;buy our PH meter!&rdquo;</p>

<p>Either way, this was a huge disappointment and I don&rsquo;t see myself trying again any time soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coi]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/15/coi/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-15T19:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/15/coi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://scontent-a-lga.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-prn2/t1.0-9/10366159_10152435781269470_5551473906445502316_n.jpg">https://scontent-a-lga.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-prn2/t1.0-9/10366159_10152435781269470_5551473906445502316_n.jpg</a>" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>Of course it&rsquo;s just after I dish out a healthy dose of self-deprecation about restaurant writing that I feel compelled
to write about another restaurant.  So I&rsquo;ll keep it short.</p>

<p>I went to Daniel Patterson&rsquo;s Coi recently.  The only thing I can say about the food is that it wasn&rsquo;t overtly
over-the-top.  Nor was it deliberately modernist or filled with crazy techniques using chemicals I can&rsquo;t pronounce.  But
it was very very delicious and still managed to surprise me.  I can&rsquo;t overstate how awesome this is, and would recommend
the trip to anyone given to spending unhealthy amounts of money on food.</p>

<p>Also bought a signed copy of the book while I was there.  I can&rsquo;t wait to read it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whole Chicken Biryani]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/23/whole-chicken-biryani/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T21:38:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/23/whole-chicken-biryani</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-2SMxkfv/0/L/DSC_2941-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-2SMxkfv/0/L/DSC_2941-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>And it&rsquo;s time for yet another episode of &ldquo;As [I Have] Seen On TV&rdquo;!  This time, I draw inspiration from Ramsay&rsquo;s Great
Escape, in which Gordon gets tired of his financial troubles and career as a TV chef and so decides to&hellip;  Go off to
make more TV.  Go figure.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Regardless of motivations, it&rsquo;s a pretty engaging show.  Throughout two seasons, he travels through southeast
Asia&mdash;India, China, Vietnam, and the like&mdash;slumming it with the locals to learn their skills and eventually returning to
the &ldquo;civilized areas&rdquo; of the country to demonstrate his newfound knowledge.  The only real complaint I have is the
(hopefully unintended) air of condescension that he develops at times.  &ldquo;Look, these people have <em>absolutely nothing</em>
and they still eat like kings!  It&rsquo;s <em>amazing</em>!&rdquo;</p>

<p>That aside, there are some memorable moments, one of which was a wedding catering to something in the neighborhood of
1000 guests.  Ramsay goes back to his line cook roots and helps a chef stuff a goat with some chicken stuffed with quail
stuffed with egg which is then loaded into a giant vat of rice. Despite my dreams to own a farm one day I still haven&rsquo;t
the means to pull a goat out of thin air, but I figured a whole chicken biryani might be worth a shot.  While I have
done biryani before, this was highly experimental, so this will be more of a photo log than set instructions</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-45Rk3rc/0/L/DSC_2943-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-45Rk3rc/0/L/DSC_2943-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>First, the chicken was rubbed with oil and lemon juice mixed with biryani-ish spices: cloves, cayenne, cumin seed,
coriander, and so on.  That was left to sit for a little bit while I par-boiled my rice, and then thrown into a pot to
roast with some potatoes.  I used my usual temps: 450 for &frac12; hour, 370 after.  In this case I shortened the cooking
time a bit, since it still had to cook with the rice.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-sD6CTSf/0/L/DSC_2944-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-sD6CTSf/0/L/DSC_2944-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>After the chicken was done, I deglazed the bottom of the pot and lined it with freshly sliced tomatoes.  Then I stuffed
some of the rice and potato into the chicken, loaded the chicken and potatoes back into the pot, and covered with the
par-boiled rice.  I lined the pot cover with a cloth to trap the steam, and it finished in about 45 minutes at a
medium-lowish heat.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-5JQdj93/0/L/DSC_2950-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-5JQdj93/0/L/DSC_2950-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Overall this turned out pretty well.  There wasn&rsquo;t much deviation from &ldquo;standard biryani procedure&rdquo;, which basically
just involves cubed meat instead of a whole bird.  The biggest pain was getting the meat off the chicken at the end: it
came off, but took some effort.  Perhaps a longer cooking time, or more moisture to cook the chicken with, next time?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
