<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Food | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-28T15:49:03-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Side Rant on Pasta]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2015/03/28/side-rant-pasta/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-28T13:59:04-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2015/03/28/side-rant-pasta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Torchio-w-Sausage/i-RLfRc4f/0/L/DSC_3412-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Torchio-w-Sausage/i-RLfRc4f/0/L/DSC_3412-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>I have the fortune of living near a couple of markets that stock Rustichella, and this morning I spotted
some in a shape that I hadn&rsquo;t seen before and kinda had to go for it.  Nickel to anyone who guesses why it&rsquo;s called
&ldquo;torchio.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I was in the middle of drumming up a post about what I ended up making with it but got kind of caught up in a side-rant
that I realized I hadn&rsquo;t written about before and probably deserved its own post, so&hellip;  Here it is.</p>

<h3>All Dried Pasta</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve heard a fair amount of people say (especially on shared grocery trips with college-level budgets) that &ldquo;pasta is
just pasta&rdquo; so the preferable choice is the cheapest one.  I don&rsquo;t disagree with the principle of making sure you get
appropriate value for your money, but I do disagree with that assessment of pasta&ndash;even the dried stuff.</p>

<p>There are significant (if subtle) differences in the quality of product between different tiers of manufacturers, and it
mostly boils down to two things: process, and ingredients.</p>

<h3>Rustichella</h3>

<p>At the top of my personal tier list is Rustichella Best Pasta&trade;.  They are the best dried pasta I&rsquo;ve tried thus far,
albeit with a price tag to match&ndash;The torchio above cost me about $6 for the package.  This is the pasta I look for when
I&rsquo;m going all-out with home-making-the-hell-out-of-everything.  I mean, if you&rsquo;re going to bother to do a crazy
sauce/etc from scratch, why start skimping on the pasta?</p>

<p>For ingredients, there are only two: durum flour, and water.  Simple, easy.</p>

<p>The process is where it gets a bit more interesting.  A lot of shapes like spaghetti, linguine, and penne are made by
extruding the pasta dough through a set of dies&ndash;basically a device with a hole in it.  Rustichella has their own
in-house bronze die system that works wonders on the end product and gives it a rough texture on the outside.  I don&rsquo;t
have a macro lens, but hopefully it can still be seen here:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Torchio-w-Sausage/i-qRrC8cz/0/L/DSC_3451-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Torchio-w-Sausage/i-qRrC8cz/0/L/DSC_3451-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Even the smooth, non-ridged parts of the pasta have a nice roughness to it.  What this amounts to is a better ability for
the pasta to carry the sauce that it&rsquo;s mixed with, resulting in an overall better dish.</p>

<p>The other thing I think is worth noting is that Rustichella claims to use a low temperature slow dry, versus a more
typical high temperature quick dry.  My guess is that this yields better consistency in the product and possibly better
texture&ndash;In my experience, exposing dough to high temperatures does make it more prone to gumming up and even cracking.
I do feel like Rustichella has a slightly better mouth feel and cooks more evenly so the drying process could have
something to do with it, but this is purely anecdotal and could just be confirmation bias on my part.</p>

<h3>The Good Stuff</h3>

<p>Next on the list would be
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/De-Cecco-Bucatini-16-Ounce-Boxes/dp/B001EPPBE0/ref=pd_sim_gro_4?ie=UTF8&amp;refRID=12NFHK20DVCYZAESJYFK">De Cecco</a>
and similar brands.  De Cecco is my &ldquo;everyday&rdquo; brand, and my go-to when I don&rsquo;t feel like pulling out all the stops or
when I can&rsquo;t find the shape of Rustichella I want.  And while Rustichella sits at the top of my list, De Cecco isn&rsquo;t too
far behind.  That is to say&hellip;  Rustichella might be leaps and bounds above price-wise and at times that&rsquo;s worth it, but
there isn&rsquo;t a correspondingly crazy gap in terms of the quality of the product.</p>

<p>As far as process, De Cecco still uses bronze dies so their pasta has a decent texture.  If you check out the amazon
link, the zoomed in photo of the boxes actually does a nice job showcasing that.</p>

<p>On ingredients, durum wheat is still at the top of the list (always a good sign!), but there seems to be a bunch of crap
tacked onto the end.  What&rsquo;s kind of funny is that in the amazon description, they say the product is a &ldquo;Good source of
Protein, Thiamin, Folic Acid, Iron, Riboflavin and Niacin&rdquo;, i.e. all of the extra ingredients at the end that aren&rsquo;t
flour.  Not sure if it&rsquo;s a nutrition play for marketing or what, but I wish they&rsquo;d just leave the pasta well enough
alone.</p>

<h3>The Lower Tier</h3>

<p>And trailing the bottom is the likes of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Barilla-Pasta-Penne-16-Ounce/dp/B00IB1D764/ref=cm_cr_pr_product_top?ie=UTF8">Barilla</a>,
<a href="http://www.shopwell.com/prince-penne-rigate/pasta/p/4112902036">Prince</a>,
and various grocery store brands.  This is where you start seeing shortcuts everywhere, and these are the ones I would
avoid except under duress.</p>

<p>For ingredients, you see the same deal along the lines of &ldquo;wheat with stuff added in.&rdquo;  However, what&rsquo;s noteworthy here
is that there are now two entries for the wheat in the ingredient list, generally listed as &ldquo;Semolina (Wheat), Durum
(Wheat)&rdquo;.  The difference between various types of flour deserves another post (or five), but the tl;dr is that &ldquo;durum
wheat&rdquo; is generally more process-heavy than &ldquo;semolina wheat&rdquo;.  My theories for the mixing here would be 1) cost cutting,
or 2) using the semolina to offset some other shortcoming in the process, e.g. high temp fast-drying.</p>

<p>A really obvious difference here comes from the process.  Brands in this tier tend to cheap out on their process as
well, and the most noticeable part of that is the use of plastic dies instead of metal ones.  As a result, the pasta&rsquo;s
surface is ultra-smooth, which leads to vastly inferior sauceability.  Go ahead, feel up some spaghetti from both De
Cecco and Prince.  One will be nice and rough, and the other will be as smooth as a shaved baby&rsquo;s bottom&ndash;Not that I
advocate shaving babies or anything.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>At the end of the day, getting this involved about the quality of dried pasta seems kind of petty, but these little
things add up.  The price difference between, say, De Cecco and Rustichella might not be reflective of the quality
difference.  It&rsquo;s another instance of the 80-20 rule&ndash;On some days I feel like it&rsquo;s worth it, other days not so much.
But I&rsquo;d argue that everyone that cares about their food should at least spring for something like De Cecco.  Unless
you&rsquo;re cooking with Chef Boyardee and Hamburger Helper, of course.  Then I don&rsquo;t think what pasta is being used really
matters.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Curry House Noodles]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/curry-house-noodles/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-02T13:49:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/curry-house-noodles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-8tzWS42/0/L/DSC_3216-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-8tzWS42/0/L/DSC_3216-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>These noodles were heavily inspired by my trip to <a href="http://www.thehse.com/">The House</a> in San Francisco.  They had a dish
that was essentially a very fancy lo mein, with some Satay-ish sauce with wasabi, topped with vegetable and steak.
Noodles?  Steak?  SAUCE?!  I didn&rsquo;t know it was possible to combine so many of my favorite things.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This version is much more simple, with much less vegetable variety and substituting the wasabi-sauce with the good ol&#8217;
standby Madras curry.</p>

<p>First, prep all relevant vegetables&ndash;In my case, julienning carrots and cucumbers, and slicing some onions.  Then boil
the noodles according to the relevant package instructions and shock with cold water to stop the cooking.  I recommend a
wheat-based noodle; nothing with huge amounts of egg, or alkaline.  Not that it&rsquo;d be terrible or anything, I just don&rsquo;t
think it&rsquo;d work as well.</p>

<p>While doing all that, also sear off and cook a steak&ndash;The specifics of a well-cooked steak probably deserve a post of
their own.</p>

<p>While the steak is resting in a nice warm place, get a pan nice and hot and cook off the onions and vegetables.  Add in
the spices.  I was feeling slightly lazy, so I went back to the ol&#8217; Madras curry powder.  Anyone hand-mixing spices
should go for something with heavier turmeric/coriander and just a touch of spice, as opposed to a mixture that&rsquo;s
basically all cayenne.</p>

<p>Add a tiny bit of water to turn the curry into a thick paste and help the vegetables cook off.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-JBZW4kW/0/L/DSC_3210-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-JBZW4kW/0/L/DSC_3210-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Add the noodles and give them a toss.  Add some cream to round out the flavors, then finish the cooking.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-bdKbzWN/0/L/DSC_3215-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-bdKbzWN/0/L/DSC_3215-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>And after everything is all nice, cooked, and combined, top with julienned cucumbers, steak, and maybe some scallions.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-d7hpQdj/0/L/DSC_3221-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-d7hpQdj/0/L/DSC_3221-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Funny Pina Coladas]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/funny-pina-coladas/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-02T13:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/funny-pina-coladas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And so ends my streak of weekly posts.  ~8 months isn&rsquo;t too bad, is it?  I swear I have a legitimate excuse, though.
You see, last week I was away at an all-hands retreat for work.  Not only was I away from my computer for the majority
of it, some <a href="http://blog.bizo.com/blog/from-the-digital-c-suite/linkedin-to-acquire-bizo">big announcements</a> and the
resultant celebrations left me physically incapacitated, to put it politely.</p>

<p>In retribution, I offer you two things.  First, is a make-up food post (that will be published immediately after this
one).  Second, is a picture of a pina colada in a pineapple that I made on a bored Sunday afternoon:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-qwZfFsq/0/L/DSC_3201-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-qwZfFsq/0/L/DSC_3201-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>The pineapple idea turned out pretty nicely.  I actually came really close to buying one of those fancy kitchen gadgets
that I always make fun of&ndash;in this case, a pineapple corer.  Luckily I refrained and, as it turns out, you can do pretty
well with a <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-s2XvKSK/0/L/DSC_3153-L.jpg">paring knife</a> and a
<a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-d33xr5Q/0/L/DSC_3156-L.jpg">spoon</a>.  That said, the drink itself
could have used much improvement.  I used to think I wasn&rsquo;t a &ldquo;booze&rdquo; type person until I met folks who really knew what
they were doing and realized that, much like food, booze requires a lot of skill and care to pull off properly.  So I&rsquo;ll
be exploring that more; whether enough to start posting about it remains to be seen.  But in the meantime&hellip;</p>

<p>Pineapple!</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-wt87t3P/0/L/DSC_3208-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-wt87t3P/0/L/DSC_3208-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['MURICA - Ribs]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/11/murica-ribs/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-11T21:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/11/murica-ribs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-NJP5Mrc/0/L/DSC_3131-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-NJP5Mrc/0/L/DSC_3131-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>It is one of my greatest regrets as a Super Manly-Man that my current living situation is prohibitive against the
construction of fire pits, or even the ownership of so much as a grill.  And it is a travesty that on the Fourth of
July&ndash;one of the meatiest holidays of the meatiest of countries (&lsquo;MURICAAAAA)&ndash;I had to settle for a measly oven for my
ribs.  But alas, one must make do.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As far as ribs done in a scrawny house-oven go, these were actually pretty good; I basically stole the entire thing
wholesale from an episode of Good Eats.  While I wouldn&rsquo;t say braised ribs inspire me to go out and slay bears, I&rsquo;d say
all in all it could have turned out a lot worse.</p>

<h2>Meat</h2>

<ul>
<li>2 racks of ribs</li>
</ul>


<h2>Spice Rub</h2>

<ul>
<li>8 parts (I used a &frac14; cup per &ldquo;part&rdquo;) brown sugar</li>
<li>3 parts kosher salt (halve that if you insist on using table salt, you heathen)</li>
<li>1 part Chili P</li>
<li>1 part &ldquo;everything else&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<h2>Everything Else</h2>

<p>A great big mix of&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li>Old Bay</li>
<li>Dried Thyme</li>
<li>Cayenne Pepper</li>
<li>Black Pepper</li>
<li>Onion Powder</li>
</ul>


<h2>Braising Liquid</h2>

<ul>
<li>1 cup white while</li>
<li>2 Tb white wine vinegar</li>
<li>A few cloves of garlic, crushed</li>
<li>drizzle of honey</li>
</ul>


<p>Combine everything in the Spice Rub and make sure to mix well.  I ended up mixing and storing it in a few Ball jars,
since this stuff will keep forever.  Cover the ribs in it.  Seriously, don&rsquo;t be shy with the spice either&ndash;what are you,
a communist?</p>

<p>After the ribs are completely coated, wrap them in aluminum foil.  First seal up the foil lengthwise, then roll up the
ends to make a neat little package.  If you&rsquo;re paranoid like me, you can double-layer the foil.  Stick this in the
fridge overnight.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-J847KwB/0/L/DSC_3069-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-J847KwB/0/L/DSC_3069-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-4MR872V/0/L/DSC_3074-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-4MR872V/0/L/DSC_3074-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Several beers and a good night&rsquo;s sleep later, wake up and groggily pre-heat your oven to 225F.  Put everything for the
Braising Liquid into a saucepan, and bring to a simmer.  Remove the ribs, unroll one of the foil ends, and dump the
braising liquid into the foil packages.  It&rsquo;s kind of like feeding a pet, if your pet were aluminum and you were
planning on eating its insides.</p>

<p>Place everything onto a metal tray, and the tray into the oven.  Wait for 2 &frac12; to 3 hours, then remove and unwrap the
ribs.  Drain the braising liquid into a saucepan.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-N6TLMVp/0/L/DSC_3079-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-N6TLMVp/0/L/DSC_3079-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Reduce the liquid in the pan until it reaches a sauce-like consistency.  We&rsquo;re talking about well past the french
&ldquo;spoon-back-coating&rdquo; level; look for something closer to a thick glaze.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-ZVPCzzC/0/L/DSC_3086-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-ZVPCzzC/0/L/DSC_3086-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Slather the sauce onto the ribs, then stick them under a broiler for a few minutes.  Marvel at the excellent color and
sizzling goodness.</p>

<p>Slice, cover with more sauce, and garnish with copious amounts of Independence.  Potato salad might also work.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-qX9g7j3/0/L/DSC_3138-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-qX9g7j3/0/L/DSC_3138-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Caramelized Lemongrass Chicken]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/03/caramelized-lemongrass-chicken/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T15:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/03/caramelized-lemongrass-chicken</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-FBL6Qgb/0/L/DSC_3055-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-FBL6Qgb/0/L/DSC_3055-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t make this as often as I should, since to be honest prepping lemongrass is kind of a pain even with a food
processor.  But when I do make the effort, it&rsquo;s totally worth it.  The refreshing flavors of lemongrass play really well
with the rich, strong flavors of caramel and chicken.  Plus, who doesn&rsquo;t like fish sauce?  Make sure to use the brand
with the crabs, though; otherwise, what&rsquo;s the point?</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>1 lb boneless chicken thighs</li>
<li>4 stalks of lemongrass</li>
<li>1 yellow onion, chopped</li>
<li>2 Tbs sugar, 2 Tbs high heat oil</li>
<li>2 tsp fish sauce</li>
<li>4 cloves minced garlic</li>
<li>cilantro</li>
<li>scallions</li>
<li>whole chilies</li>
<li>salt, pepper</li>
</ul>


<p>Start off with prepping the lemongrass.  Cut the bottoms off the stalks as well as the tops, right where they start
turning dark green.  Bash them a few times with the back of your knife (or a brick, I guess), and slice into thin rings.
Then run your knife through the thin rings a few times to end up with a fine mince.  This is probably the most painful
and labor-intensive part of this entire dish, but it&rsquo;s important.  Bruising and chopping the lemongrass in this way
is essential to releasing the flavor, but at the same time nobody wants to pick big pieces of lemongrass out of their
teeth.  For the lazy/economical among us, I&rsquo;m sure a few pulses in the food processor would also work.  I&rsquo;ve also been
told you can buy pulverized lemongrass frozen, but&hellip;  Come on.  If you&rsquo;re reading this blog, you obviously have the
time to do some proper prep.</p>

<p>Cut the chicken thighs into small &frac12; to 1-inch cubes.  If the thighs came with skin, great; keep it, it helps with
flavor.  If not, that&rsquo;s alright too I suppose.  Personally, I just buy thighs with bone and skin on, and just debone
myself.  And as with most of these types of dishes, I&rsquo;m morally obligated to note that trying to substitute chicken
breast here is a capital offense.  Thighs just have so much more flavor.</p>

<p>Season the chicken with salt, pepper, and a few tablespoons of the chopped lemongrass, and set it aside for a few
minutes.  In the meantime, heat the oil in a large skillet over medium-high heat until it&rsquo;s shimmery and just about to
smoke.  Add the sugar, which should melt with some stirring after a minute or two.  Keep stirring, and wait for the
sugar syrup to turn brown and caramel-y.  At no point should the mixture smoke: If it does, the pan&rsquo;s gotten too hot,
and should be taken off the heat for a bit.</p>

<p>Stir in the rest of the chopped lemongrass, the onion, and the garlic, and fry for a few minutes.  Crank the heat all
the way up and throw in the chicken.  After a minute, throw in the chilies, and keep cooking until the chicken&rsquo;s done.
Take the pan off the heat, then add the fish sauce.  (Hint: Make sure to save the fish sauce for when the high heat
cooking is done, or else it&rsquo;ll smell up the joint.)  Finish with chopped scallions and chopped cilantro.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-FHVvjDS/0/L/DSC_3045-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-FHVvjDS/0/L/DSC_3045-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>With a solid bowl of white rice, this amount of chicken is probably good for serving about 3-4 people, depending on
appetite needs and size.  For this particular run, I ended up with a bowl of vermicelli, with julienned cucumbers and
mint on the side.  Topped with more fish sauce.  Having no exposure to any sort of Vietnamese home culture, I can&rsquo;t
really speak to this dish&rsquo;s authenticity or anything like that.  I mean, I&rsquo;m sure some Vietnamese food icon is rolling
in their grave over my use of fish sauce and vermicelli, but at least it&rsquo;s delicious.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-5CjWGbk/0/L/DSC_3063-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-5CjWGbk/0/L/DSC_3063-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
