<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: food | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-08T22:43:01-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jamaican Beef Patty - Week 6, Jamaican]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/22/jamaican-beef-patty-week-6-jamaican/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-22T13:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/22/jamaican-beef-patty-week-6-jamaican</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Jamaican-Beef-Patty/i-gFrttbp/0/L/DSC_2467-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Jamaican-Beef-Patty/i-gFrttbp/0/L/DSC_2467-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Living out of a hotel room in San Francisco makes it pretty hard to complete any sort of themed cooking challenge.
Luckily, I had the wherewithal to go one or two challenges ahead and snap up some appropriate pictures.  Unluckily, I
was a dunce and left the notes on the ingredient amounts at home&hellip;  Times like this I wish that Octopress had a proper
draft feature so I could just write the entire post out ahead of time.  As it is, everyone will have to settle for a
<a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Jamaican-Beef-Patty/i-LsmL2g8">photo</a> of the meez for &frac12; lb of beef, and some
quick notes from memory:</p>

<ul>
<li>The seasonings in the photo are salt, allspice, paprika, garlic, scotch bonnets, and thyme.  Basically, the beginnings
of a slightly ghetto jerk seasoning.</li>
<li>The crust was built kind of like your standard shortcrust pie dough.  The only thing is that I found a lot of places
recommending vegetable shortening.  We don&rsquo;t abide by shortening in my house, so I just replaced it with a slightly
smaller quantity of butter.  It also contained a bit of turmeric, hence the brilliant yellow color.</li>
<li>Prep was simple: saute everything, wrap in dough, bake at 375 for about 25 minutes.</li>
</ul>


<p>The result tasted just about how you&rsquo;d expect the above combination to taste: like a curry beef pie.  I&rsquo;d shaped these
into a rough slightly-bigger-than-pierogi sort of shape, but that left an unsatisfying amount of filling per bite.  Next
time I&rsquo;d probably go with something like McDonald&rsquo;s Apple Pie size.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, even with that hypothetical improvement I found the patties a bit flat and boring.  I guess it&rsquo;s because
curry meat pie-like constructs were a mainstay of my childhood, and most of the time the Chinese version was made with
puff pastry which I vastly prefer to shortcrust.  Plus, I&rsquo;ve read that the most common way to eat the Jamaican patties
is stuffed inside coco-bread (a soft roll made with coconut milk), and the thought of the bread starch on top of the
crust starch just grosses me out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm baaaaack]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/10/im-baaaaack/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T20:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/10/im-baaaaack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been nearly two years since I&rsquo;ve done any serious baking and pastry work.  One part of it was graduating into a
full-time job that meant most of my time would be spent away in an office instead of at home keeping an eye on my dough
or batter or what have you.  The other part is my current apartment&rsquo;s oven being&hellip;  How do I put this politely&hellip;  a
piece of shit.</p>

<p>But the other day&rsquo;s challenge with the panna cotta ended up rousing the baker in me more than I&rsquo;d expected, and when
everyone around me started discussing macarons, I had a pretty bad case of my equivalent of the withdrawal shakes.  So I
figured I&rsquo;d take a shot at beating my oven into submission; after all, even with a proper oven I&rsquo;d MacGuyver&rsquo;d my way
out of worse things back in school.  The result?</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-Bb46M8t/0/L/macred1-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-Bb46M8t/0/L/macred1-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Far from perfect, but it&rsquo;s good to know that my hands haven&rsquo;t completely rusted off.  And with the recent changes in
lifestyle, hopefully I&rsquo;ll be able to get back into more interesting experimentation as well; just have to be more
careful about not repeating the college experience and gaining a ton of weight along the way.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-tR5PPpB/0/L/macred2-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-tR5PPpB/0/L/macred2-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>A shot of the shells as a bonus.  My piping still kind of sucks and I definitely need to practice and tweak more, but
overall it could have been much worse.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Panna Cotta with Apple Compote - Week 5, Vanilla]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/panna-cotta-with-apple-compote-week-5-vanilla/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-08T10:52:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/panna-cotta-with-apple-compote-week-5-vanilla</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-gpKW6cR/0/L/DSC_2421-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-gpKW6cR/0/L/DSC_2421-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>The few times I&rsquo;ve used vanilla have always been for dessert, so for this week&rsquo;s challenge I really wanted to try
something savory.  Unfortunately I couldn&rsquo;t think of anything that didn&rsquo;t sound horrifying even in my head, so I ended
up going with a dessert anyway; tough nuts.  To be fair though, I stuck with the spirit of leaving my comfort zone and
made multiple things I&rsquo;ve never done before&mdash;panna cotta and apple compote.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Since this was my first attempt, I feel like everything could still use some fine-tuning, but overall the results were
acceptable (more on that below), so I&rsquo;ll jot down the quantities and everything just for reference.</p>

<h2>Apples</h2>

<ul>
<li>2 braeburn apples</li>
<li>200g sugar</li>
<li>8g pectin</li>
<li>1 vanilla bean</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>A quick note on pectin:</strong>  Pectin comes in many forms.  The top differentiator is high or low methoxy
pectin, which dictates what kind of environment the pectin needs to set.  Generally speaking, unless you&rsquo;re shopping at
the modernist pantry, high-methoxy pectin is what you&rsquo;ll be getting.  HM pectin sets in an acidic environment, which is
why most of the time it&rsquo;s already cut with a little bit of citric acid when sold.  This is perfectly fine.  Of course, HM
pectin is itself differentiated by how fast it sets: Rapid set, medium set, and so on.  In this case, it shouldn&rsquo;t
matter too much, as any common consumer pectin that&rsquo;s labeled as suitable for jam should be around the right range, but
it&rsquo;s still worth noting since the variation in citric acid + pectin type is what accounts for some brands of pectin not
working with some types of fruit.</p>

<p>The first part is fairly easy.  Dice up the apples into small &frac12; inch chunks (for the more particular among us, I ended
up with roughly 240g apple).  Combine it with the sugar, pectin, and vanilla bean, and put everything on low heat.  The
sugar should start melting fairly quickly, and the apples will start bubbling as they cook, like so:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-nrDwR7n/0/L/DSC_2395-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-nrDwR7n/0/L/DSC_2395-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Keep the apples on low heat until they are completely cooked through and translucent; this should take about 45 minutes.
In the above photo, a few of the chunks in the center and to the left are starting to get there.  Be careful not to burn
anything, and give the pot a stir every once in a while.</p>

<p>After the cooking, they should basically look like jelly.  At this point, the seeds from the spent vanilla pod can be
scraped out and combined with the apples, but that&rsquo;s optional.  Stick everything in a ball jar (or other container of
choice) and chill in the fridge.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-DtBs7C2/0/L/DSC_2405-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-DtBs7C2/0/L/DSC_2405-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<h2>Panna Cotta</h2>

<ul>
<li>600ml cream</li>
<li>3 sheets of gelatin (~5g)</li>
<li>50g sugar</li>
<li>1 vanilla bean</li>
<li>4 cardamom pods</li>
</ul>


<p>First thing is to bloom the gelatin in cold water, using whatever timing the manufacturer recommends.  Pierce the
cardamom pods to help let the flavor out&mdash;either use your hands to crack them a bit, or score the pods with a knife.
For the sugar, just split the bean down the middle and scrape out the seeds.  Because of the moisture, the seeds often
come out feeling more like a paste; just knead it into the sugar with your fingers to prevent clumps in the final
product.</p>

<p>Add about 50ml of the cream to the sugar, and whisk&mdash;Again, this is just to prevent any clumping that may occur.  Add
the rest of the cream, and the cardamom pods, and bring everything to a light simmer&mdash;be careful that it doesn&rsquo;t come to
a full rolling boil.  Hopefully the gelatin has bloomed by now, so add that and let it simmer for another minute or two.
Pour the cream into whatever containers are appropriate, and let everything set in the fridge.  I recommend at least 3-4
hours, preferably overnight.</p>

<h2>Impressions</h2>

<ul>
<li>The apples came out way denser than I expected.  I&rsquo;ve never worked with pectin before, but I think the big mistake was
not accounting for the naturally occurring pectin in the fruit itself.  On hindsight, given how the most commonly sold
pectin is <em>apple pectin</em>, this was kind of a dunce cap moment.</li>
<li>The fruit was also way stronger and sweeter than I expected.  Next time I might dial down the sugar/vanilla in the
fruit, serve less of it, or just not combine it with something as delicate as panna cotta.  Haven&rsquo;t quite decided on
that one yet.</li>
<li>The panna cotta did not have gelatin problems (thankfully), but it was still a bit dense.  For the next try I might
cut the cream down with some milk, probably about 500ml cream to 100ml milk.</li>
<li>The cardamom also didn&rsquo;t come out as much as I would have liked.  It was just barely noticeable if tasting the cream
alone, so I think in the future a full 6 pods for 600ml liquid would be better.  Or even more if being served with
something as strong as a fruit compote.</li>
<li>Now that I think about it, maybe I&rsquo;d be better of cutting out the fruit and serving the panna cotta alone with some
sugar syrup that I&rsquo;ve steeped with cardamom pods.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raclette - Week 4, Things You Hated as a Kid]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/28/raclette-week-4-things-you-hated-as-a-kid/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T06:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/28/raclette-week-4-things-you-hated-as-a-kid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-gvTHKVq/0/L/DSC_2393-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-gvTHKVq/0/L/DSC_2393-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Being your token asian immigrant, my experience with cheese was limited to Kraft slices and string cheese.  Now, there&rsquo;s
nothing wrong with good american cheese on a burger, but I hated string cheese with a burning passion&mdash;Especially when
my mom wanted me to eat some as a snack, citing something or other about calcium and strong bones.  <em>Pfft</em>.  Subsequent
exposure to the likes of cheez-whiz and store-brand grated parmesan really didn&rsquo;t help, and eventually I just dismissed
cheese as categorically unpleasant.</p>

<p>Since then I&rsquo;ve discovered the miracles of parmesan and mozzarella and even some more exotic ones like morbier and p'tit
basque.  But the first moment I realized that cheese could be excellent in its own right, and even be a major player in
a proper dish, was with raclette.</p>

<p>Raclette is commonly eaten in the swiss alps.  At its core, it&rsquo;s raclette cheese melted over boiled potatoes, commonly
served with cured meat and some pickles or vegetables in the root family; in the above photo, I went with the common
french pickle <em>cornichon</em> and some prosciutto.  The preparation is as easy as food gets: literally just boiling some
potatoes and melting some cheese (I recommend using a toaster oven or a broiler), and then arranging everything on a
plate.</p>

<p>But despite its simplicity, raclette had a large effect on expanding my worldview in food, so&hellip;  There it is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicken Shahi Korma - Week 3, One Pot]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/19/chicken-shahi-week-3-one-pot/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-19T10:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/19/chicken-shahi-week-3-one-pot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-KPv4qLJ/0/L/DSC_2381-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-KPv4qLJ/0/L/DSC_2381-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>One thing I&rsquo;ve noticed about the weekly food challenges is that it syncs very well with my new self-imposed weekly post
quota.  This works out nicely for me, but at the same time it provides a very convenient cop-out from having to write
anything new, e.g. about tech.  While at the end of the day I&rsquo;m still writing more than I would have, I&rsquo;m wondering if
it&rsquo;d be a good idea to stop counting these towards the weekly quota, or only count them partially.  Another option would
be to pick and choose which challenges to limit the volume, but cherry-picking challenges is for weenies.  Thoughts for
the future, I guess.</p>

<p>At any rate, the &ldquo;point&rdquo; of this week&rsquo;s theme is simplicity&mdash;Getting good flavor out of an easy set up, i.e. &ldquo;one pot&rdquo;.
It seemed like a good time to test out my burgeoning indian food skills, but as it turns out the most complicated part
was just the combination of the spices.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>Ingredients</h4>

<ul>
<li>Large spices

<ul>
<li>8 green cardamom pods</li>
<li>6 cloves</li>
<li>3-inch stick of cinnamon</li>
<li>3 bay leaves</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Small spices

<ul>
<li>1 tsp ground cumin</li>
<li>1 tsp ground coriander</li>
<li>&frac14; tsp ground cayenne</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>4 lb chicken thighs</li>
<li>1 cup plain yogurt</li>
<li>Handful of chopped cilantro</li>
<li>Handful of slivered blanched almonds</li>
</ul>


<p>Normally for non-baking work I prefer to cook by taste and instinct rather than measuring too precisely.  But in this
case spices can be quite strong, and it&rsquo;ll probably take years before I could do that effectively, so it&rsquo;s better to be
on the safe side.  For the curious, here&rsquo;s roughly what the spice setup looks like for 4 lb of chicken:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-JzpM4D6/0/L/DSC_2372-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-JzpM4D6/0/L/DSC_2372-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>I like cilantro so I tend to put in a bit extra; most people will probably want a bit less than what&rsquo;s shown above.
Another quick note is that the chicken thighs should preferably come with skin and bone; again, just more flavor that
way.  You could do it with boneless skinless thighs, or even breasts, but come on.</p>

<p>There really isn&rsquo;t much to this, technique-wise:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>First, combine the small spices and cilantro with the yogurt, then season the chicken pieces with salt and pepper.</p></li>
<li><p>Heat up a healthy amount of oil in your pot, then toss in the large spices and give them a quick stir.  Start
browning the chicken on medium-high heat.  The browning can be done in a separate pan, but 1) you&rsquo;d be missing out on
the flavor from the brown bits at the bottom, and 2) the theme is &ldquo;one pot&rdquo; and that&rsquo;d be cheating.  Don&rsquo;t
over-crowd&mdash;You really want the color on there, so work in multiple batches if necessary.  By the time the chicken&rsquo;s
done, the kitchen should already be smelling delicious.</p></li>
<li><p>Remove all the chicken from the pot, keeping the oil from frying, and toss in some almonds.  As soon as they start
browning, re-add all the chicken along with any juices that may have appeared.  Add the yogurt sauce and give it a good
mix, then cover and let everything simmer on low for 20 minutes or so.</p></li>
<li><p>When ready, turn the heat back up and let the sauce reduce.  Stir gently once in a while to make sure nothing is
burning and sticking.  The final thickness of the sauce is ultimately preference, but in western terms it should at
<em>least</em> pass the &ldquo;coat the back of the spoon&rdquo; test and then some.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>And since this is, after all, &ldquo;one pot&rdquo;, here is a picture of everything in one pot <em>(excuse the desaturation, I blame
the steam.)</em>:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-M9sWXcq/0/L/DSC_2379-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Chicken-Shahi-Korma/i-M9sWXcq/0/L/DSC_2379-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>When everything is ready, serve with basmati rice or a nice piece of flatbread.  And yes, like most curries, this tastes
even better after sitting around for a day or two.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
