<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Food | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-24T16:21:07-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Curry House Noodles]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/curry-house-noodles/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-02T13:49:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/curry-house-noodles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-8tzWS42/0/L/DSC_3216-L.jpg"></p>




<p>These noodles were heavily inspired by my trip to <a href="http://www.thehse.com/">The House</a> in San Francisco.  They had a dish
that was essentially a very fancy lo mein, with some Satay-ish sauce with wasabi, topped with vegetable and steak.
Noodles?  Steak?  SAUCE?!  I didn&rsquo;t know it was possible to combine so many of my favorite things.</p>




<!-- more -->




<p>This version is much more simple, with much less vegetable variety and substituting the wasabi-sauce with the good ol&#8217;
standby Madras curry.</p>




<p>First, prep all relevant vegetables&ndash;In my case, julienning carrots and cucumbers, and slicing some onions.  Then boil
the noodles according to the relevant package instructions and shock with cold water to stop the cooking.  I recommend a
wheat-based noodle; nothing with huge amounts of egg, or alkaline.  Not that it&rsquo;d be terrible or anything, I just don&rsquo;t
think it&rsquo;d work as well.</p>




<p>While doing all that, also sear off and cook a steak&ndash;The specifics of a well-cooked steak probably deserve a post of
their own.</p>




<p>While the steak is resting in a nice warm place, get a pan nice and hot and cook off the onions and vegetables.  Add in
the spices.  I was feeling slightly lazy, so I went back to the ol&#8217; Madras curry powder.  Anyone hand-mixing spices
should go for something with heavier turmeric/coriander and just a touch of spice, as opposed to a mixture that&rsquo;s
basically all cayenne.</p>




<p>Add a tiny bit of water to turn the curry into a thick paste and help the vegetables cook off.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-JBZW4kW/0/L/DSC_3210-L.jpg"></p>




<p>Add the noodles and give them a toss.  Add some cream to round out the flavors, then finish the cooking.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-bdKbzWN/0/L/DSC_3215-L.jpg"></p>




<p>And after everything is all nice, cooked, and combined, top with julienned cucumbers, steak, and maybe some scallions.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Curry-House-Noodles/i-d7hpQdj/0/L/DSC_3221-L.jpg"></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Funny Pina Coladas]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/funny-pina-coladas/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-02T13:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/funny-pina-coladas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And so ends my streak of weekly posts.  ~8 months isn&rsquo;t too bad, is it?  I swear I have a legitimate excuse, though.
You see, last week I was away at an all-hands retreat for work.  Not only was I away from my computer for the majority
of it, some <a href="http://blog.bizo.com/blog/from-the-digital-c-suite/linkedin-to-acquire-bizo">big announcements</a> and the
resultant celebrations left me physically incapacitated, to put it politely.</p>




<p>In retribution, I offer you two things.  First, is a make-up food post (that will be published immediately after this
one).  Second, is a picture of a pina colada in a pineapple that I made on a bored Sunday afternoon:</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-qwZfFsq/0/L/DSC_3201-L.jpg"></p>




<p>The pineapple idea turned out pretty nicely.  I actually came really close to buying one of those fancy kitchen gadgets
that I always make fun of&ndash;in this case, a pineapple corer.  Luckily I refrained and, as it turns out, you can do pretty
well with a <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-s2XvKSK/0/L/DSC_3153-L.jpg">paring knife</a> and a
<a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-d33xr5Q/0/L/DSC_3156-L.jpg">spoon</a>.  That said, the drink itself
could have used much improvement.  I used to think I wasn&rsquo;t a &ldquo;booze&rdquo; type person until I met folks who really knew what
they were doing and realized that, much like food, booze requires a lot of skill and care to pull off properly.  So I&rsquo;ll
be exploring that more; whether enough to start posting about it remains to be seen.  But in the meantime&hellip;</p>




<p>Pineapple!</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Pina-Colada/i-wt87t3P/0/L/DSC_3208-L.jpg"></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['MURICA - Ribs]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/11/murica-ribs/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-11T21:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/11/murica-ribs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-NJP5Mrc/0/L/DSC_3131-L.jpg"></p>




<p>It is one of my greatest regrets as a Super Manly-Man that my current living situation is prohibitive against the
construction of fire pits, or even the ownership of so much as a grill.  And it is a travesty that on the Fourth of
July&ndash;one of the meatiest holidays of the meatiest of countries (&lsquo;MURICAAAAA)&ndash;I had to settle for a measly oven for my
ribs.  But alas, one must make do.</p>




<!-- more -->




<p>As far as ribs done in a scrawny house-oven go, these were actually pretty good; I basically stole the entire thing
wholesale from an episode of Good Eats.  While I wouldn&rsquo;t say braised ribs inspire me to go out and slay bears, I&rsquo;d say
all in all it could have turned out a lot worse.</p>




<h2>Meat</h2>




<ul>
<li>2 racks of ribs</li>
</ul>




<h2>Spice Rub</h2>




<ul>
<li>8 parts (I used a &frac14; cup per &ldquo;part&rdquo;) brown sugar</li>
<li>3 parts kosher salt (halve that if you insist on using table salt, you heathen)</li>
<li>1 part Chili P</li>
<li>1 part &ldquo;everything else&rdquo;</li>
</ul>




<h2>Everything Else</h2>




<p>A great big mix of&hellip;</p>




<ul>
<li>Old Bay</li>
<li>Dried Thyme</li>
<li>Cayenne Pepper</li>
<li>Black Pepper</li>
<li>Onion Powder</li>
</ul>




<h2>Braising Liquid</h2>




<ul>
<li>1 cup white while</li>
<li>2 Tb white wine vinegar</li>
<li>A few cloves of garlic, crushed</li>
<li>drizzle of honey</li>
</ul>




<p>Combine everything in the Spice Rub and make sure to mix well.  I ended up mixing and storing it in a few Ball jars,
since this stuff will keep forever.  Cover the ribs in it.  Seriously, don&rsquo;t be shy with the spice either&ndash;what are you,
a communist?</p>




<p>After the ribs are completely coated, wrap them in aluminum foil.  First seal up the foil lengthwise, then roll up the
ends to make a neat little package.  If you&rsquo;re paranoid like me, you can double-layer the foil.  Stick this in the
fridge overnight.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-J847KwB/0/L/DSC_3069-L.jpg"></p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-4MR872V/0/L/DSC_3074-L.jpg"></p>




<p>Several beers and a good night&rsquo;s sleep later, wake up and groggily pre-heat your oven to 225F.  Put everything for the
Braising Liquid into a saucepan, and bring to a simmer.  Remove the ribs, unroll one of the foil ends, and dump the
braising liquid into the foil packages.  It&rsquo;s kind of like feeding a pet, if your pet were aluminum and you were
planning on eating its insides.</p>




<p>Place everything onto a metal tray, and the tray into the oven.  Wait for 2 &frac12; to 3 hours, then remove and unwrap the
ribs.  Drain the braising liquid into a saucepan.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-N6TLMVp/0/L/DSC_3079-L.jpg"></p>




<p>Reduce the liquid in the pan until it reaches a sauce-like consistency.  We&rsquo;re talking about well past the french
&ldquo;spoon-back-coating&rdquo; level; look for something closer to a thick glaze.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-ZVPCzzC/0/L/DSC_3086-L.jpg"></p>




<p>Slather the sauce onto the ribs, then stick them under a broiler for a few minutes.  Marvel at the excellent color and
sizzling goodness.</p>




<p>Slice, cover with more sauce, and garnish with copious amounts of Independence.  Potato salad might also work.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Murica-Ribs/i-qX9g7j3/0/L/DSC_3138-L.jpg"></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Caramelized Lemongrass Chicken]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/03/caramelized-lemongrass-chicken/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T15:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/07/03/caramelized-lemongrass-chicken</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-FBL6Qgb/0/L/DSC_3055-L.jpg"></p>




<p>I don&rsquo;t make this as often as I should, since to be honest prepping lemongrass is kind of a pain even with a food
processor.  But when I do make the effort, it&rsquo;s totally worth it.  The refreshing flavors of lemongrass play really well
with the rich, strong flavors of caramel and chicken.  Plus, who doesn&rsquo;t like fish sauce?  Make sure to use the brand
with the crabs, though; otherwise, what&rsquo;s the point?</p>




<!-- more -->




<ul>
<li>1 lb boneless chicken thighs</li>
<li>4 stalks of lemongrass</li>
<li>1 yellow onion, chopped</li>
<li>2 Tbs sugar, 2 Tbs high heat oil</li>
<li>2 tsp fish sauce</li>
<li>4 cloves minced garlic</li>
<li>cilantro</li>
<li>scallions</li>
<li>whole chilies</li>
<li>salt, pepper</li>
</ul>




<p>Start off with prepping the lemongrass.  Cut the bottoms off the stalks as well as the tops, right where they start
turning dark green.  Bash them a few times with the back of your knife (or a brick, I guess), and slice into thin rings.
Then run your knife through the thin rings a few times to end up with a fine mince.  This is probably the most painful
and labor-intensive part of this entire dish, but it&rsquo;s important.  Bruising and chopping the lemongrass in this way
is essential to releasing the flavor, but at the same time nobody wants to pick big pieces of lemongrass out of their
teeth.  For the lazy/economical among us, I&rsquo;m sure a few pulses in the food processor would also work.  I&rsquo;ve also been
told you can buy pulverized lemongrass frozen, but&hellip;  Come on.  If you&rsquo;re reading this blog, you obviously have the
time to do some proper prep.</p>




<p>Cut the chicken thighs into small &frac12; to 1-inch cubes.  If the thighs came with skin, great; keep it, it helps with
flavor.  If not, that&rsquo;s alright too I suppose.  Personally, I just buy thighs with bone and skin on, and just debone
myself.  And as with most of these types of dishes, I&rsquo;m morally obligated to note that trying to substitute chicken
breast here is a capital offense.  Thighs just have so much more flavor.</p>




<p>Season the chicken with salt, pepper, and a few tablespoons of the chopped lemongrass, and set it aside for a few
minutes.  In the meantime, heat the oil in a large skillet over medium-high heat until it&rsquo;s shimmery and just about to
smoke.  Add the sugar, which should melt with some stirring after a minute or two.  Keep stirring, and wait for the
sugar syrup to turn brown and caramel-y.  At no point should the mixture smoke: If it does, the pan&rsquo;s gotten too hot,
and should be taken off the heat for a bit.</p>




<p>Stir in the rest of the chopped lemongrass, the onion, and the garlic, and fry for a few minutes.  Crank the heat all
the way up and throw in the chicken.  After a minute, throw in the chilies, and keep cooking until the chicken&rsquo;s done.
Take the pan off the heat, then add the fish sauce.  (Hint: Make sure to save the fish sauce for when the high heat
cooking is done, or else it&rsquo;ll smell up the joint.)  Finish with chopped scallions and chopped cilantro.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-FHVvjDS/0/L/DSC_3045-L.jpg"></p>




<p>With a solid bowl of white rice, this amount of chicken is probably good for serving about 3-4 people, depending on
appetite needs and size.  For this particular run, I ended up with a bowl of vermicelli, with julienned cucumbers and
mint on the side.  Topped with more fish sauce.  Having no exposure to any sort of Vietnamese home culture, I can&rsquo;t
really speak to this dish&rsquo;s authenticity or anything like that.  I mean, I&rsquo;m sure some Vietnamese food icon is rolling
in their grave over my use of fish sauce and vermicelli, but at least it&rsquo;s delicious.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Caramelized-Lemongrass-Chicken/i-5CjWGbk/0/L/DSC_3063-L.jpg"></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Fuck It Friday" - Weeks 12 + 13, Street Food + Potatoes]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/fuck-it-its-friday-weeks-12-13/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T17:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/fuck-it-its-friday-weeks-12-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-5WQTNMH/0/L/DSC_3030-L.jpg"></p>




<p>This <em>was</em> going to be a big ol&#8217; fancy affair.  I set out to knock out two weeks&#8217; worth of challenges at once, and take
advantage of some sweet, sweet morels at the market.  Unfortunately, the potatoes decided to be uncooperative, so here
we are.</p>




<!-- more -->




<p>The original idea was to make curried fried clams as the &ldquo;street food&rdquo; portion of the challenge; luckily that turned out
pretty well.  I first laced some flour with turmeric, cumin, garam masala, cayenne, and salt, then soaked some minced
clams in milk.  A few minutes in some 350-degree oil later, voila!  One note though: rest them in parchment paper or a
mesh rack; paper towels will just end up steaming them as they cool, ruining the crunchy texture.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-7Rn3Gpg/0/L/DSC_3023-L.jpg"></p>




<p>While the curryish flavors got a bit overwhelmed by the tartar sauce, I like to think that it provided a bit more depth
to the flavor.  Placebo effect, anyone?</p>




<p>Here&rsquo;s where things get a bit dicey.  The original plan was to slice up a bunch of potatoes and stack them, then form a
mini-cake by surrounding it with a potato-morel &ldquo;icing&rdquo;.  However, I decided to be a dunce and add some morel-induced
cream, which ended up turning the potato-morel combo into more of a wet puree than a potato cake.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-kc4j69J/0/L/DSC_3025-L.jpg"></p>




<p>To salvage the situation, I ended up pan-frying the slices and combining them with the puree, making something like a
mutated gratin dauphinois.</p>




<p>At this point, I had given up all delusions of pretentious grandeur and decided, &ldquo;Fuck it, it&rsquo;s Friday&rdquo;.  Thus, I turned the
entire thing on its head, going from <em>frou-frou potato cake</em> to <em>giant plate of stuff</em> with cole slaw and extra tartar
sauce.  All things considered, it could have turned out much worse; at least it was still delicious, and that&rsquo;s what
really counts.  And I suppose the &ldquo;pile of food&rdquo; format is more appropriate for the street food theme anyway.</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Fuck-It-Friday/i-vjNkfpR/0/L/DSC_3035-L.jpg"></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
