<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: food | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-27T17:28:10-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oysters with Lemon Pearls - Week 11 Molecular]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/27/oysters-with-lemon-pearls-week-11-molecular/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-27T17:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/27/oysters-with-lemon-pearls-week-11-molecular</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-5NhtLD4/0/L/DSC_2972-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-5NhtLD4/0/L/DSC_2972-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>I was really looking forward to the Molecular theme, since I&rsquo;d been itching to play with some of this newfangled
Modernist Cuisine stuff for a while now.  So I went ahead and ordered a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Modernist-Pantry-Spherification-Kit/dp/B008657GS0/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1401210725&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=spherification+kit">spherification kit</a>
from amazon, and came up with the idea of pairing spheres with oysters.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The kit came with fairly straightforward instructions, so I just followed those.  For my liquid base I used lemonade
mixed with lemon juice for acidity.  I added 2 grams of sodium citrate, since the kit recommended that for potentially
acidic solutions.</p>

<p>The spheres came together fairly well, though it was pretty slow going at first.  I&rsquo;m also displeased that the syringe
included with the kit is one use only&hellip;</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-p99X433/0/L/DSC_2968-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oysters-With-Lemon-Pearls/i-p99X433/0/L/DSC_2968-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>The spheres look good, but I think that&rsquo;s about all that I can say about them positively.  Taste-wise, they were
slightly rubbery and the insides were way too viscous&mdash;Closer to maple syrup than juice.  Maybe it was the
disappointment from expecting something closer to the &ldquo;popping boba&rdquo; found in bubble tea/frozen yogurt, but overall I
just found the texture unpleasant.  In addition, the alginate stifled the acidity in the lemon and left a funny taste in
my mouth, making the pearls taste basically like jello filled with slightly off sugar syrup.</p>

<p>All in all, I would have been better served making plain old lemon jello with the oysters, which is what I&rsquo;ve done in
the past.  It&rsquo;s possible that I did something terribly wrong despite my self-perceived precision, or perhaps this kit
just didn&rsquo;t include the right substances for this set of circumstances.  Half the instructions seemed to exist for
upselling, e.g., &ldquo;buy our slotted spoon!&rdquo;, &ldquo;buy our PH meter!&rdquo;</p>

<p>Either way, this was a huge disappointment and I don&rsquo;t see myself trying again any time soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coi]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/15/coi/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-15T19:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/05/15/coi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://scontent-a-lga.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-prn2/t1.0-9/10366159_10152435781269470_5551473906445502316_n.jpg">https://scontent-a-lga.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-prn2/t1.0-9/10366159_10152435781269470_5551473906445502316_n.jpg</a>" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>Of course it&rsquo;s just after I dish out a healthy dose of self-deprecation about restaurant writing that I feel compelled
to write about another restaurant.  So I&rsquo;ll keep it short.</p>

<p>I went to Daniel Patterson&rsquo;s Coi recently.  The only thing I can say about the food is that it wasn&rsquo;t overtly
over-the-top.  Nor was it deliberately modernist or filled with crazy techniques using chemicals I can&rsquo;t pronounce.  But
it was very very delicious and still managed to surprise me.  I can&rsquo;t overstate how awesome this is, and would recommend
the trip to anyone given to spending unhealthy amounts of money on food.</p>

<p>Also bought a signed copy of the book while I was there.  I can&rsquo;t wait to read it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whole Chicken Biryani]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/23/whole-chicken-biryani/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T21:38:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/23/whole-chicken-biryani</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-2SMxkfv/0/L/DSC_2941-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-2SMxkfv/0/L/DSC_2941-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>And it&rsquo;s time for yet another episode of &ldquo;As [I Have] Seen On TV&rdquo;!  This time, I draw inspiration from Ramsay&rsquo;s Great
Escape, in which Gordon gets tired of his financial troubles and career as a TV chef and so decides to&hellip;  Go off to
make more TV.  Go figure.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Regardless of motivations, it&rsquo;s a pretty engaging show.  Throughout two seasons, he travels through southeast
Asia&mdash;India, China, Vietnam, and the like&mdash;slumming it with the locals to learn their skills and eventually returning to
the &ldquo;civilized areas&rdquo; of the country to demonstrate his newfound knowledge.  The only real complaint I have is the
(hopefully unintended) air of condescension that he develops at times.  &ldquo;Look, these people have <em>absolutely nothing</em>
and they still eat like kings!  It&rsquo;s <em>amazing</em>!&rdquo;</p>

<p>That aside, there are some memorable moments, one of which was a wedding catering to something in the neighborhood of
1000 guests.  Ramsay goes back to his line cook roots and helps a chef stuff a goat with some chicken stuffed with quail
stuffed with egg which is then loaded into a giant vat of rice. Despite my dreams to own a farm one day I still haven&rsquo;t
the means to pull a goat out of thin air, but I figured a whole chicken biryani might be worth a shot.  While I have
done biryani before, this was highly experimental, so this will be more of a photo log than set instructions</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-45Rk3rc/0/L/DSC_2943-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-45Rk3rc/0/L/DSC_2943-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>First, the chicken was rubbed with oil and lemon juice mixed with biryani-ish spices: cloves, cayenne, cumin seed,
coriander, and so on.  That was left to sit for a little bit while I par-boiled my rice, and then thrown into a pot to
roast with some potatoes.  I used my usual temps: 450 for &frac12; hour, 370 after.  In this case I shortened the cooking
time a bit, since it still had to cook with the rice.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-sD6CTSf/0/L/DSC_2944-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-sD6CTSf/0/L/DSC_2944-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>After the chicken was done, I deglazed the bottom of the pot and lined it with freshly sliced tomatoes.  Then I stuffed
some of the rice and potato into the chicken, loaded the chicken and potatoes back into the pot, and covered with the
par-boiled rice.  I lined the pot cover with a cloth to trap the steam, and it finished in about 45 minutes at a
medium-lowish heat.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-5JQdj93/0/L/DSC_2950-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Whole-Chicken-Biryani/i-5JQdj93/0/L/DSC_2950-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Overall this turned out pretty well.  There wasn&rsquo;t much deviation from &ldquo;standard biryani procedure&rdquo;, which basically
just involves cubed meat instead of a whole bird.  The biggest pain was getting the meat off the chicken at the end: it
came off, but took some effort.  Perhaps a longer cooking time, or more moisture to cook the chicken with, next time?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Garlic Soy Chicken Wings]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/17/garlic-soy-chicken-wings/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-17T20:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/17/garlic-soy-chicken-wings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-ZfrmLNX/0/L/DSC_2936-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-ZfrmLNX/0/L/DSC_2936-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Yes, I&rsquo;m going to be <em>that</em> Asian who posts a chicken wing recipe involving some combination of garlic, soy, and honey.
Next thing you know I&rsquo;ll be writing book reviews for the Joy Luck Club and acting in sketches about Tiger Moms.  Though
I suppose the latter would be pretty entertaining&hellip;</p>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t the first chicken wing recipe I&rsquo;ve posted <em>(note to self: still need to port those old entries over&hellip;)</em>, but
it is a pretty quick and easy one.  The only awkward part is that in situations like this, it&rsquo;s not worth the effort to
not make a ton, but then everything takes a while to eat&hellip;  But I think that&rsquo;s a pretty good problem to have.</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>3 lb chicken wings</li>
<li>1 cup vegetable oil</li>
<li>&frac14; cup honey</li>
<li>&frac14; cup soy sauce</li>
<li>&frac14; cup Shaoxing wine</li>
<li>4 cloves garlic</li>
<li>1 tbsp brown sugar</li>
<li>Pinch of salt</li>
</ul>


<p>To prepare, mix all the sauce ingredients together, and toss the chicken in.  If you&rsquo;re feeling really bored, jab them a
few times to help the sauce seep in.  Mix evenly, then let it sit in the fridge overnight.  In my experience, the wings
can be kept this way for up to 3 days&mdash;I&rsquo;d vouch for longer, but they&rsquo;re generally eaten in that time frame.</p>

<p>When ready, pre-heat the oven to 375, and bake for about 30 minutes.  Do note that I usually cook in batches, so if the
whole 3 lb needs to be done at once, 45 minutes would probably be safer.  Give them a quick toss on the stove with some
fresh herbs.  Scallions are usually a pretty good bet, but I like cilantro too.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-VS3Xmzp/0/L/DSC_2918-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Honey-Soy-Wings/i-VS3Xmzp/0/L/DSC_2918-L.jpg</a>"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shepherd's Pie - Week 10, Australian]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/shepherds-pie-week-10-australian/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-12T22:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/shepherds-pie-week-10-australian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-hnc6sSv/0/L/DSC_2915-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-hnc6sSv/0/L/DSC_2915-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Alright, so I cheated a little bit.  Despite extensive (not really) research, I couldn&rsquo;t find anything in the top google
results for Australian that really clicked.  At least, anything using conventional ingredients; I didn&rsquo;t quite get the
chance to special-order some kangaroo.  Since I&rsquo;m told meat pies are popular in Australia and the lamb was technically
from there, it still counts&hellip;  Right?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Even though it&rsquo;s technically an Aussie theme, I went with a more british twist on the ingredients, especially with the
Worcestershire sauce.  The following makes enough to modestly feed 4 off a pretty decent size tray.  <em>No, I don&rsquo;t have
exact dimensions for the tray, it&rsquo;s a meat pie, eyeball it FFS.</em></p>

<ul>
<li>1 lb ground lamb</li>
<li>1 lb yellow potato, heavy cream</li>
<li>Stock, preferably beef</li>
<li>A dash (or 3) Worcestershire sauce</li>
<li>1 tbsp tomato paste</li>
<li>Carrots &lsquo;n peas (or other vegetables)</li>
<li>Garlic</li>
<li>Thyme</li>
</ul>


<p>First off, the meez.  Chop up the garlic, pick the thyme leaves, and finely dice the vegetables, if applicable.  In my
case, it&rsquo;s more like &ldquo;take the bag out of the freezer.&rdquo;  Seriously, for carrots and peas in something like meat pie,
frozen works best.</p>

<p>Put a nice heavy pan on the stove and get it ripping hot.  Add the lamb and garlic, and let the meat get some color.
Don&rsquo;t jab at it or anything for the first few minutes; we want it to fry, not boil.</p>

<p>After it gets a nice dark brown color, start stirring and breaking it apart into tiny pieces.  When it&rsquo;s done, you
should hear sizzling from fat, not hissing from steam&mdash;this should take 10, 15 minutes or so.</p>

<p>Stir in the worcestershire sauce and tomato paste, then add the thyme and beef stock.  How much beef stock is pretty
subjective: I use just enough to mix with the tomato paste for a gravy-ish texture.  The key is not so little that
everything is dry, but not so much that it bubbles over in the oven.  If I had to guess, I&rsquo;d say it&rsquo;s just shy of 2
cups, but perhaps a picture of the end product would be helpful?</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-kZsbxX3/0/L/DSC_2895-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-kZsbxX3/0/L/DSC_2895-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Put a lid on, and let it simmer on very low heat for at least 30-40 minutes, preferably an hour, just to let everything
come together.  Alternately, popping the pan in the oven at ~300-350 also works.</p>

<p>Preheat the oven to 400.  While the meat is going and the oven is warming, prepare the mash.  I really hope I don&rsquo;t have
to provide detailed instructions for that&hellip;  If that&rsquo;s needed, there&rsquo;s always google.</p>

<p>When the meat is done, stick it in a tray and spread the mash on top.  Score with a fork for effect, if desired.  Then
stick into the oven again for about 30 minutes to finish everything off and brown the top a bit.  For presentation, I
bet some eggwash would help with the browning, but I&rsquo;ve never found it necessary.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-qMkv5Mz/0/L/DSC_2908-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Shepherds-Pie/i-qMkv5Mz/0/L/DSC_2908-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>In this particular attempt, I added a bit too much stock and it ended up bubbling out onto the potato.  Still delicious,
though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
