<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Misc | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/misc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-28T16:38:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2015, a Whole New Year!]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2015/01/24/2015-a-whole-new-year/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-24T14:25:50-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2015/01/24/2015-a-whole-new-year</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s 2015, and a whole new year!  Several updates, of no particular relation and in no particular order:</p>

<h3>Some Site Updates</h3>

<p>I finally got around to updating Octopress after I noticed the search bar was broken.  The process was
relatively painless and some of the new features look neat, but I can&rsquo;t say I&rsquo;m a huge fan of the enforced solarized
light scheme in codeblocks.</p>

<p>While I was at it, I also decided to refresh the headline and about page, since it&rsquo;s been a while.</p>

<h3>Thing of the Week</h3>

<p>While I&rsquo;ve actually been really good about staying on top of sending the internal email blasts for TotW, I ended up
neglecting the blog cross-posting.  Part of it is because after I started, I had more work-related travel and didn&rsquo;t
have the blog repo all properly set up on the other laptop; and the other part is that translating back and forth
between markdown and outlook is kind of a PITA.  In the future, I will probably set up a proper workflow with pandoc and
everything to make it easier.  But in the meantime, I&rsquo;ve back-posted them with dates tagged for context, plus some bonus
after-the-fact commentary.</p>

<p>As far as the TotW itself, it&rsquo;s been a success in my book.  Reactions have generally been positive, and a lot of the
posts end up generating very interesting conversation where I often end up learning something new.  In addition, to keep
up with the writing I have to be 1) more active in learning new things, and 2) more thorough since I actually have to
write about it.  Win, win.  Next step: to collect more feedback, then perhaps involve more people and hopefully expand
it beyond just my immediate teammates.</p>

<h3>2014 in Review and MicroConf</h3>

<p>Back in late 2013 / early 2014, I was extremely frustrated with a number of things and decided to leave my full-time
job.  After resting off some of the burnout, I set off to build a side project with a friend with two goals in mind: 1) Learn
new tech and get back into the game properly; in this case, Scala and Lift.  2) Build out a prototype scheduling app and
try to bootstrap an actual business with it.  The latter ultimately failed, but I still learned a ton and the knowledge
gained from the former arguably got me to my position today as a Scala developer.  (In hindsight, trying to learn a
completely new tech stack <em>and</em> all the business + domain-specific stuff required was crazy&hellip;  Next time, I would
definitely prototype with something easier and more familiar.)</p>

<p>Without getting too side-tracked, suffice to say that 2014 was insane for personal growth and productivity, and I&rsquo;d love
to continue that trend for 2015.  And while I&rsquo;m definitely not looking to do anything drastic employment-wise, I will
say that the side-project itch has never really left me.  So I figured after all this time listening to the likes of
<a href="http://www.startupsfortherestofus.com/">Startups For The Rest Of Us</a> and <a href="http://bootstrapped.fm/">bootstrapped.fm</a>,
2015 would be a great year to go to MicroConf and actually hang out with all the folks living the lifestyle.  Hopefully
I come back with heaps of new insight and ideas, but either way it looks to be a blast.  Anyway, I managed to snag a
ticket after some cutthroat site-camping and waitlist-waiting, so I am stoked.</p>

<p>tl;dr - VEGAS, BABY!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thing of the Week: keybase.io (12/24/14)]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2015/01/24/keybase-dot-io/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-24T11:53:30-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2015/01/24/keybase-dot-io</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since it&rsquo;s nearly the holidays, I figured something more frivolous would be good for this week.</p>

<p><a href="https://keybase.io/">keybase.io</a> is a combination public key store slash centralized identity slash hipster social
network app.  How it works is that you generate a key pair and upload the public key to their store.  From there, you
can use your key pair to sign messages and post them on twitter, github, bit coin sites, etc, to verify that those
accounts actually belong to you.  At the end of it, you get a funny page like this saying that “why yes, all of these
accounts are crypto-verified to be the same person”, like this:  <a href="https://keybase.io/alexkuang">https://keybase.io/alexkuang</a></p>

<p>It’s still very much in toy app status at the moment, but I think it’s a really cool idea.  I believe they’re open for
signup now; not sure if there’s a beta line or something, but apparently I have invites if anyone wants.</p>

<p>Happy holidays!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CH Backports]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/ch-backports/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-26T21:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/ch-backports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For anyone unfamiliar, I wrote a food blog a while back called curehappiness with my then-roommate,
<a href="http://tlextrait.com/">Thomas</a>.  It was active mostly during my college years, dying down due to a whole variety of
reasons&ndash;office life, apathy at the post-grad lifestyle, wordpress being a pain&hellip;  All that great stuff.  The project
had originally started as an off-the-cuff idea for something to do with a newly commissioned server; after a while, I
decided to shuffle up my server arrangements, and curehappiness&#8217; Wordpress installation got the axe.  Since I couldn&rsquo;t
be bothered to backup the entire WP install, I just saved a bunch of the posts in HTML form instead, with the idea of
one day porting it to whatever new platform I would be running.</p>

<p>After all this time on Octopress + Github Pages, I finally pulled the trigger.  All the backported posts will be from
before 2013, tagged as <code>ch-backports</code>, and will contain a link at the top to this post.  They&rsquo;ve largely been preserved
verbatim, minus a few corrections like &lsquo;boal&rsquo; -> &lsquo;bowl&rsquo; (seriously, past Alex???).  However, I couldn&rsquo;t resist adding
small notes from the future, which will be in blockquotes at the top:</p>

<blockquote><p>like so.</p></blockquote>

<p>I ported the posts with the most worthwhile content&ndash;namely, recipes and records of experiments.  Restaurant reviews and
other such content were few and far between, and honestly aside from a couple of wisecracks and some nice pictures, they
felt pretty banal; not a solid reason for censorship, granted, but I still felt it wasn&rsquo;t worth the effort.  I&rsquo;ll
probably upload the photos from those posts to smugmug at some point and save the rewrites for when I have actual
original insights beyond &ldquo;yes, the food was good&rdquo;.</p>

<p>As a final note, migrating was not trivial, but I did get some nice hackery out of it.  I&rsquo;ll probably post the
tech-gorey details later, but suffice to say that I&rsquo;ve learned my lesson about storing data in arbitrary mangled html
generated by a WYSIWYG editor run through who knows how many plugins and themes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Les Iterables]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/les-iterables/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-21T08:16:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/les-iterables</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/les-iterables.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Not very uplifting&hellip;</p><footer><strong>David Pollak</strong></footer></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Slick production values.</p><footer><strong>Jan Christopher Vogt</strong></footer></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Wonderful acting!</p><footer><strong>Jonas Boner</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><em>(Sorry guys, saw this in <a href="http://reddit.com/r/scala">/r/scala</a> and kind of had to.)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jab, Jab]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/jab/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T19:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/jab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past, my biggest problem with blogging has always been with finding something to write about.  Every time an idea
came, I&rsquo;d recall the original post that inspired it, or have one miraculously pop up on google upon doing more
research.  Inevitably the post would be articulate, well-researched, and laden with comments from impressed readers to
boot.  And I would hit control+w, convinced that I don&rsquo;t have anything to add; even if I did, I&rsquo;m an awful writer and
nobody reads my blog anyway.</p>

<p>But writing is an Important Skill, one that I&rsquo;d very much like to improve.  I&rsquo;m certainly not going to get any better by
<em>not</em> doing it, and <a href="http://weknowmemes.com/2012/05/sucking-at-something-is-the-first-step-to-becoming/">everyone has to start somewhere</a>: keep practicing, keep
drilling, keep jabbing away, and eventually you&rsquo;ll probably make progress.  I remember an old post of Jeff Atwood&rsquo;s
where his only advice was to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/10/how-to-achieve-ultimate-blog-success-in-one-easy-step.html">pick a schedule</a> and stick
with it.  Maybe it&rsquo;s about time I did just that.  <strong>One post a week</strong>, even if the topic sounds asinine and I&rsquo;m low on
inspiration and nobody will read it (or <em>especially</em> if nobody will read it?).</p>

<p>With all that said, I&rsquo;d like to introduce my newest housemate, <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Animals/Zelda">Zelda</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Animals/Zelda/i-rNGBWHH/0/L/DSC_2268-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Animals/Zelda/i-rNGBWHH/0/L/DSC_2268-L.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>She arrived with all of 3 days&#8217; notice, and is at just about that age where kittens tend to be terrible people.  She&rsquo;ll
bully the other (much bigger) cats, knock over bowls and trash bags, attack everything like the king of the jungle, and
just generally be an unabashed little snot.  But she&rsquo;s disarmingly adorable, so naturally none of that matters in the
slightest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
