<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: misc | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/misc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-21T08:28:09-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Les Iterables]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/les-iterables/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-21T08:16:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/les-iterables</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/les-iterables.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Not very uplifting&hellip;</p><footer><strong>David Pollak</strong></footer></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Slick production values.</p><footer><strong>Jan Christopher Vogt</strong></footer></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Wonderful acting!</p><footer><strong>Jonas Boner</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><em>(Sorry guys, saw this in <a href="http://reddit.com/r/scala">/r/scala</a> and kind of had to.)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jab, jab]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/jab/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T19:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/jab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past, my biggest problem with blogging has always been with finding something to write about.  Every time an idea
came, I&rsquo;d recall the original post that inspired it, or have one miraculously pop up on google upon doing more
research.  Inevitably the post would be articulate, well-researched, and laden with comments from impressed readers to
boot.  And I would hit control+w, convinced that I don&rsquo;t have anything to add; even if I did, I&rsquo;m an awful writer and
nobody reads my blog anyway.</p>

<p>But writing is an Important Skill, one that I&rsquo;d very much like to improve.  I&rsquo;m certainly not going to get any better by
<em>not</em> doing it, and <a href="http://weknowmemes.com/2012/05/sucking-at-something-is-the-first-step-to-becoming/">everyone has to start somewhere</a>: keep practicing, keep
drilling, keep jabbing away, and eventually you&rsquo;ll probably make progress.  I remember an old post of Jeff Atwood&rsquo;s
where his only advice was to <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/10/how-to-achieve-ultimate-blog-success-in-one-easy-step.html">pick a schedule</a> and stick
with it.  Maybe it&rsquo;s about time I did just that.  <strong>One post a week</strong>, even if the topic sounds asinine and I&rsquo;m low on
inspiration and nobody will read it (or <em>especially</em> if nobody will read it?).</p>

<p>With all that said, I&rsquo;d like to introduce my newest housemate, <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Animals/Zelda">Zelda</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Animals/Zelda/i-rNGBWHH/0/L/DSC_2268-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Animals/Zelda/i-rNGBWHH/0/L/DSC_2268-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>She arrived with all of 3 days' notice, and is at just about that age where kittens tend to be terrible people.  She&rsquo;ll
bully the other (much bigger) cats, knock over bowls and trash bags, attack everything like the king of the jungle, and
just generally be an unabashed little snot.  But she&rsquo;s disarmingly adorable, so naturally none of that matters in the
slightest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First post]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/10/10/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T22:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2013/10/10/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&hellip; Or, &ldquo;How I Chose a Blog Platform.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Multiple people have said that I should get back into writing, so I guess I&rsquo;m back into the blogging scene now.  It&rsquo;s
true I did have a food blog before a particular work project completely pole-axed it, and I would love to start it up
again.  The problem is that WordPress has always been a bit cumbersome for me so this time around I wanted something
different.  Plus I&rsquo;ve been meaning to get into the whole tech/misc blogging thing.  So I set out to find something that:</p>

<ol>
<li>Is easy to write in.  I&rsquo;d been fascinated by the idea of blogging in Markdown, so preferably that.</li>
<li>Could render code snippets / do syntax highlighting in most major languages.</li>
<li>Could display pictures with reasonable flexibility and prettiness.</li>
<li>Supported some form of organization based on categories/tags.</li>
</ol>


<p><a href="https://telegr.am/">telegr.am</a> was a strong contender for a while, since it uses Markdown and is written in <code>Scala</code> and
thus would have been familiar ground, but sadly it was missing in some key features.  All the other frameworks I found
were either lackluster, pay-only, or required self-deployment on a server, which I&rsquo;m clearly too lazy to do nowadays.
Thus I came to settle on <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>, a framework based on <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> which I
had already played with for my personal site before.  Thus far it fits the bill nearly perfectly, with the only rub
being the heavy dependency on git (or in my particular case, github).  But that isn&rsquo;t really a problem unless I ever
want a blog with non-technical contributors, so that bridge can be crossed when the time comes.</p>

<p>TL;DR &ndash; New blog.  Pardon the appearance during construction.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
