<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: totw | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/totw/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-25T18:08:22-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thing of the Week: Bash Bangs]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/11/25/thing-of-the-week-bash-bangs/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-25T17:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/11/25/thing-of-the-week-bash-bangs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week I wanted to do a quick tip on some neat functionality in bash (and other bash-like shells), the bang commands.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say you have some long important command that you want to run.  You run it, only to discover that you need sudo
privileges.  For situations like this, <code>!!</code> (entire last command) can be a great time-saver.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ echo 1 2 3 4 5
1 2 3 4 5 # let's pretend echo throws an error too and wants sudo for some reason
$ sudo !!
sudo echo 1 2 3 4 5
Password:
1 2 3 4 5
</code></p>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s say you don&rsquo;t want to blindly re-run the last command.  <code>:p</code> can be used without overwriting the &ldquo;last
command&rdquo; history.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ echo 1 2 3 4 5
1 2 3 4 5
$ !!:p
echo 1 2 3 4 5
$ sudo !!
sudo echo 1 2 3 4 5
Password:
1 2 3 4 5
</code></p>

<p>Bang commands also extend to the individual parts of the last command you ran.  The most basic form of this is <code>echo
!:[n]</code>, where [n] is the nth word in the command, indexed from 0.  There are also shortcuts: <code>!^</code> gives the first arg
(like <code>!:1</code>) and <code>!$</code> gives the last arg.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ echo a b c d e
a b c d e
$ echo !:1
echo a
a
$ echo a b c d e
a b c d e
$ !:5:p # :p works with any bangs!
e
$ echo !:5
echo e
e
$ echo a b c d e
a b c d e
$ echo !$
echo e
e
</code></p>

<p>Personally, I use <code>!$</code> the most, since very often I&rsquo;ll only want the last arg (e.g., <code>ls [some tab-completed dir]</code> &ndash;>
<code>rm -r !$</code>).  Plus, it&rsquo;s the easiest sequence to hit, finger-wise.</p>

<p>One final tip: awesome shells like, say, <code>zsh</code>, will actually tab-complete bangs and get rid of the need for <code>:p</code>.
e.g. <code>sudo !!&lt;TAB&gt;</code> gets replaced with <code>sudo echo 1 2 3 4 5</code> in place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thing of the Week: Vim Visual Block Mode]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/11/20/thing-of-the-week-vim-visual-block-mode/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-20T18:33:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/11/20/thing-of-the-week-vim-visual-block-mode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friday Dev Demos are a big part of Bizo culture.  Every Friday, developers take turn presenting a short 10-15 min
demo on something cool they&rsquo;d found that wasn&rsquo;t necessarily work related.  The topic could be anything from a neat
snippet of code to a cool iOS application they&rsquo;d just found to a fun web game.  Dev demo day is great for the social
aspect, but also for the chance to showcase (and draw inspiration from) ideas that might not come up in day-to-day
discussion.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the practice kind of fell by the wayside in the chaos of
<a href="http://blog.bizo.com/blog/from-the-digital-c-suite/linkedin-to-acquire-bizo">joining a new company</a> and all the
changes that entails.  While I&rsquo;m sure it&mdash;or something similar&mdash;will make a comeback, in the meantime I decided to
try carrying on the torch by starting a weekly &ldquo;Thing of the Week&rdquo; email blast that is in roughly the same spirit.  And
I figured while I&rsquo;m at it, why not stick it on the blog?  If nothing else, it will mean more practice writing and more
incentive for me to be proactive in learning new things to talk about.</p>

<p>So without further ado, the first &ldquo;Thing of the Week&rdquo; is a neat little feature in vim that I don&rsquo;t think deserves enough
attention&mdash;Visual Block mode.  The visual modes in vim are very similar to highlighting in other editors, but I&rsquo;ve
always felt that Visual Block is the underrated cousin to Visual and Visual Line mode.  Rather than trying to explain
what it does in words, here&rsquo;s a quick terminal cast to demonstrate via asciinema:</p>

<script type="text/javascript" src="https://asciinema.org/a/14064.js" id="asciicast-14064" async></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
