<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 52weeks | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/52weeks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-13T22:41:16-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instant Ramen Gnocchi - Week 8, TV Show Inspired]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/instant-ramen-gnocchi-week-8-tv-show-inspired/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T22:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/instant-ramen-gnocchi-week-8-tv-show-inspired</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>(In which I am served a massive slice of humble pie)</em></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-HPM7fVm/0/L/DSC_2602-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-HPM7fVm/0/L/DSC_2602-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p><em>Mind of a Chef</em> is not just great background noise for getting work done, it also pads out the list of cool and
unusual things I&rsquo;d like to try in the kitchen.  Out of all the things I&rsquo;d seen on the show, making gnocchi out of ramen
seemed among the most unusual and also among the simplest, so I decided it would be a prime target for this week&rsquo;s &ldquo;TV
Show Inspired&rdquo; theme.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Failure</h2>

<p>Because of its apparent simplicity, I decided to take this on on the night before my flight.  In an uncharacteristic
bout of hubris, my thoughts went something like&hellip; <em>It&rsquo;s just instant ramen blended with milk, right?  No need for a
methodical approach or anything, just toss everything in.</em>  Of course, as the Universe is wont to do, my sloppiness was
rewarded promptly with miserable failure.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-mzq93d8/0/L/DSC_2469-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-mzq93d8/0/L/DSC_2469-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>I started off by boiling the ramen in milk, and dumping all of it into a food processor with a bunch of egg yolks.  The
first hint that things were off probably should have come at this stage.  The dough held a consistency that was closer
to batter than anything, and there were far too many lumps to be normal.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-FsDKq22/0/L/DSC_2470-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-FsDKq22/0/L/DSC_2470-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-fNZCkgb/0/L/DSC_2474-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-fNZCkgb/0/L/DSC_2474-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>As anyone who isn&rsquo;t an idiot should have predicted <em>(ahem)</em>, as soon as the mixture was piped into boiling water, it
completely fell apart.  Even reducing the pot to a bare simmer, it could not hold together at all, and just ended up a
lumpy mess.  I tried frying the results of this, and piping the raw batter straight into the pan, but there&rsquo;s just no
fighting physics.</p>

<p>The best that could have happened here would have been something resembling a grit cake, and that would require some
stabilization in the way of flour / eggs / what-have-you, which I didn&rsquo;t have since I&rsquo;d cleaned out my food supplies in
preparation for my 2-week trip the next day.  &hellip;  Yep.</p>

<p>On hindsight, it&rsquo;s pretty easy to spot the things that went wrong:</p>

<ul>
<li>First off, the ramen should not have been boiled.  By the time it&rsquo;s finished boiling, it&rsquo;s already absorbed all the
liquid it can, which means that it will not integrate with any more that&rsquo;s added, no matter how much time it spends in
the food processor.</li>
<li>Along the lines of the above, I should have used much much less liquid, since I want barely enough to turn the ramen
into a dough.</li>
<li>The eggs yolks were added way too soon into the mixture.  The residual heat from the boiling liquid probably cooked
the yolks before they could be integrated, resulting in more of lumps and robbing the dough of any thickening effects
from the yolks overall.</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Retry</h2>

<p>With that spectacular SNAFU under my belt, I&rsquo;d resolved that I&rsquo;d make another proper attempt as soon as I touched back
down in Boston.  Luckily, this time went much better&mdash;Good enough to actually write out, in fact.  Here are the
ingredients I eventually settled on:</p>

<ul>
<li>500ml whole milk</li>
<li>4 egg yolks</li>
<li>2 packs instant ramen (I used Nong Shim, ~119g apiece)</li>
</ul>


<p>First off, boil 500ml milk.  Break the ramen bricks up and soak them in the milk.  There should be just barely enough
milk to cover.  Take the ramen out as soon as they become pliable enough to no longer be considered bricks&mdash;this should
only take a minute, two tops.  Dump the ramen with ~200ml of the milk into a food processor, and blend until it reaches
a dough-like consistency.  <em>(Note: I have a decently sturdy Cuisinart, and the dough had enough thickness to make it
move, so I&rsquo;d say aim for something along those lines)</em>  When everything is mixed together and cool enough to touch, add
the egg yolks and give it another few pulses to incorporate.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-SFK4xfS/0/L/DSC_2584-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-SFK4xfS/0/L/DSC_2584-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Now that looks like a proper dough.  Bring a large pot of salted water to boil, then scoop the dough into a pastry bag
(a ziploc with the corner cut out also works).  Pipe out an inch or so at a time into the water, slicing pieces off with
a straight edge.  I used the back of a paring knife for this part.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-mrqgdF2/0/L/DSC_2589-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Instant-Ramen-Gnocchi/i-mrqgdF2/0/L/DSC_2589-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Never have I been so glad to see my food looking like poo in a toilet.</p>

<p>As soon as the pieces start floating, get them onto a greased plate.  Fry in butter, then serve as preferred.</p>

<h2>Impressions</h2>

<p>DISCLAIMER: I realized soon after tasting these that I have not actually had potato gnocchi before, so I have nothing to
draw a comparison to.  I&rsquo;ll make it a point to get some from Whole Foods or something ASAP.</p>

<p>Overall the gnocchi had a very interesting texture.  For reasons unknown, I&rsquo;d always expected these to have more bite or
chew to them, but they tasted more creamy than anything.  Simultaneously, they were much heavier than I thought they
would be.  No big surprise here, since they&rsquo;re just pulverized starch and milk.  In the headline picture I served them
with pork belly and spinach, and for my second portion I used pork and miso corn.  Both times I was going for a sort of
&ldquo;deconstructed ramen&rdquo; theme, which worked out fairly well.  The only thing I&rsquo;d change is the portion size&mdash;Something
this heavy is much better suited as an appetizer or a first course.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Corn with Miso Butter - Week 7, Poaching]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/corn-with-miso-butter-week-7-poaching/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-28T20:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/corn-with-miso-butter-week-7-poaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Miso-Corn/i-RCTZjJw/0/L/DSC_2447-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Miso-Corn/i-RCTZjJw/0/L/DSC_2447-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s my last day on my trip to the West Coast, and I&rsquo;ve just finished packing, so what better time to make sure I meet
my self-imposed weekly blog quota?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be perfectly honest here: I find poaching to be kind of boring in and of itself.  Most of the time I see it used
as an excuse for health nuts to abandon any semblance of flavor, and I&rsquo;d be lying if I said I wouldn&rsquo;t likely prefer
whatever is being served to be deep fried instead.  That said, there are cases where poaching a protein can be
delicious.  Salmon is usually a good bet, and poaching a whole chicken can make for some awesome soup as long as
care is taken not to overcook it.  I chose to go with something simpler this week&mdash;a poached egg&mdash;since it&rsquo;s dead easy
and there&rsquo;s very little that matches the luxury of a runny yolk.  The corn with miso butter for this particular setup is
shamelessly stolen from David Chang&rsquo;s <em>Mind of a Chef</em>.  (Which, by the way, for anyone who hasn&rsquo;t watched&mdash;I highly
recommend it.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Egg</h2>

<p>Since the theme is technically poaching, I&rsquo;ll lead with the egg.  Plus, it makes the timing a bit easier.  The process
is super simple&mdash;A few inchaes of simmering water with a few drops of vinegar, 2.5 &ndash; 3 minutes depending on the size of the
egg.  I&rsquo;d err towards 3 for large eggs straight from the fridge.  Just a few notes for those of us who are
poaching-challenged:</p>

<ul>
<li>Use only a few inches of water; if the water is too deep, that just gives the egg more room to scatter as it falls.</li>
<li>Yes, the vineger helps.  The acid helps bind the proteins in the water, and makes life a tiny bit easier.</li>
<li>No, the taste won&rsquo;t carry over to the egg unless half the bottle&rsquo;s gone into the pot; a light drizzle is plenty
enough.</li>
<li>Making a whirlpool and dropping the egg into the middle may help it stick together as well.  I find that a bit hit or
miss, personally.</li>
<li>After poaching, the egg should be kept in cold/icy water.  This will stop the cooking and conveniently wash off
whatever traces of vinegar happen to linger.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Corn</h2>

<p>Take 1 tsp room-temp butter with 1 tsp white (<em>shiro</em>) miso and beat the crap out of them until everything is mixed
together.  No, seriously&mdash;beat it like it&rsquo;s been saying uncouth things about your mother.  There should be no streaks
left.  (If, like me, any readers happen to fall into the intersection between <em>lazy</em> and <em>keeps butter in the fridge</em>,
microwaving a few seconds helps soften things up&hellip;)</p>

<p>Next, crisp up some bacon in the pan, and set aside on paper towels to dry.  I guess technically you could skip the
bacon here&hellip;  If you <strong>hate happiness</strong>.  Either way, make sure to drain the pan of the bacon fat.  The miso will be
plenty salty even without the help of bacon fat.  Bring the pan back up to searing heat, and add a drizzle of canola
oil.  Fry up about 2 cups of corn kernels until they start browning.  If the kernels start popping and leaping around,
dial the heat back a little&mdash;think roast corn, not popcorn.</p>

<p>After it starts browning, add the miso butter.  Wait a few seconds and really enjoy the smell of that, then deglaze with
a bit of water or any stock that happens to be lying around.  Toss another few times, then plate with the bacon, the
poached egg, and some chopped scallions.</p>

<p>Seriously dead simple, and probably one of the best &ldquo;bang for buck&rdquo; dishes I can think of.  Here&rsquo;s the dish
pre-yolk-pop:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Miso-Corn/i-wNF2Mq7/0/L/DSC_2444-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Miso-Corn/i-wNF2Mq7/0/L/DSC_2444-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>&hellip; and a few more pictures <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Miso-Corn">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jamaican Beef Patty - Week 6, Jamaican]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/22/jamaican-beef-patty-week-6-jamaican/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-22T13:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/22/jamaican-beef-patty-week-6-jamaican</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Jamaican-Beef-Patty/i-gFrttbp/0/L/DSC_2467-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Jamaican-Beef-Patty/i-gFrttbp/0/L/DSC_2467-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Living out of a hotel room in San Francisco makes it pretty hard to complete any sort of themed cooking challenge.
Luckily, I had the wherewithal to go one or two challenges ahead and snap up some appropriate pictures.  Unluckily, I
was a dunce and left the notes on the ingredient amounts at home&hellip;  Times like this I wish that Octopress had a proper
draft feature so I could just write the entire post out ahead of time.  As it is, everyone will have to settle for a
<a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Jamaican-Beef-Patty/i-LsmL2g8">photo</a> of the meez for &frac12; lb of beef, and some
quick notes from memory:</p>

<ul>
<li>The seasonings in the photo are salt, allspice, paprika, garlic, scotch bonnets, and thyme.  Basically, the beginnings
of a slightly ghetto jerk seasoning.</li>
<li>The crust was built kind of like your standard shortcrust pie dough.  The only thing is that I found a lot of places
recommending vegetable shortening.  We don&rsquo;t abide by shortening in my house, so I just replaced it with a slightly
smaller quantity of butter.  It also contained a bit of turmeric, hence the brilliant yellow color.</li>
<li>Prep was simple: saute everything, wrap in dough, bake at 375 for about 25 minutes.</li>
</ul>


<p>The result tasted just about how you&rsquo;d expect the above combination to taste: like a curry beef pie.  I&rsquo;d shaped these
into a rough slightly-bigger-than-pierogi sort of shape, but that left an unsatisfying amount of filling per bite.  Next
time I&rsquo;d probably go with something like McDonald&rsquo;s Apple Pie size.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, even with that hypothetical improvement I found the patties a bit flat and boring.  I guess it&rsquo;s because
curry meat pie-like constructs were a mainstay of my childhood, and most of the time the Chinese version was made with
puff pastry which I vastly prefer to shortcrust.  Plus, I&rsquo;ve read that the most common way to eat the Jamaican patties
is stuffed inside coco-bread (a soft roll made with coconut milk), and the thought of the bread starch on top of the
crust starch just grosses me out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Panna Cotta with Apple Compote - Week 5, Vanilla]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/panna-cotta-with-apple-compote-week-5-vanilla/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-08T10:52:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/panna-cotta-with-apple-compote-week-5-vanilla</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-gpKW6cR/0/L/DSC_2421-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-gpKW6cR/0/L/DSC_2421-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>The few times I&rsquo;ve used vanilla have always been for dessert, so for this week&rsquo;s challenge I really wanted to try
something savory.  Unfortunately I couldn&rsquo;t think of anything that didn&rsquo;t sound horrifying even in my head, so I ended
up going with a dessert anyway; tough nuts.  To be fair though, I stuck with the spirit of leaving my comfort zone and
made multiple things I&rsquo;ve never done before&mdash;panna cotta and apple compote.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Since this was my first attempt, I feel like everything could still use some fine-tuning, but overall the results were
acceptable (more on that below), so I&rsquo;ll jot down the quantities and everything just for reference.</p>

<h2>Apples</h2>

<ul>
<li>2 braeburn apples</li>
<li>200g sugar</li>
<li>8g pectin</li>
<li>1 vanilla bean</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>A quick note on pectin:</strong>  Pectin comes in many forms.  The top differentiator is high or low methoxy
pectin, which dictates what kind of environment the pectin needs to set.  Generally speaking, unless you&rsquo;re shopping at
the modernist pantry, high-methoxy pectin is what you&rsquo;ll be getting.  HM pectin sets in an acidic environment, which is
why most of the time it&rsquo;s already cut with a little bit of citric acid when sold.  This is perfectly fine.  Of course, HM
pectin is itself differentiated by how fast it sets: Rapid set, medium set, and so on.  In this case, it shouldn&rsquo;t
matter too much, as any common consumer pectin that&rsquo;s labeled as suitable for jam should be around the right range, but
it&rsquo;s still worth noting since the variation in citric acid + pectin type is what accounts for some brands of pectin not
working with some types of fruit.</p>

<p>The first part is fairly easy.  Dice up the apples into small &frac12; inch chunks (for the more particular among us, I ended
up with roughly 240g apple).  Combine it with the sugar, pectin, and vanilla bean, and put everything on low heat.  The
sugar should start melting fairly quickly, and the apples will start bubbling as they cook, like so:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-nrDwR7n/0/L/DSC_2395-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-nrDwR7n/0/L/DSC_2395-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Keep the apples on low heat until they are completely cooked through and translucent; this should take about 45 minutes.
In the above photo, a few of the chunks in the center and to the left are starting to get there.  Be careful not to burn
anything, and give the pot a stir every once in a while.</p>

<p>After the cooking, they should basically look like jelly.  At this point, the seeds from the spent vanilla pod can be
scraped out and combined with the apples, but that&rsquo;s optional.  Stick everything in a ball jar (or other container of
choice) and chill in the fridge.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-DtBs7C2/0/L/DSC_2405-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Panna-Cotta-with-Apple/i-DtBs7C2/0/L/DSC_2405-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<h2>Panna Cotta</h2>

<ul>
<li>600ml cream</li>
<li>3 sheets of gelatin (~5g)</li>
<li>50g sugar</li>
<li>1 vanilla bean</li>
<li>4 cardamom pods</li>
</ul>


<p>First thing is to bloom the gelatin in cold water, using whatever timing the manufacturer recommends.  Pierce the
cardamom pods to help let the flavor out&mdash;either use your hands to crack them a bit, or score the pods with a knife.
For the sugar, just split the bean down the middle and scrape out the seeds.  Because of the moisture, the seeds often
come out feeling more like a paste; just knead it into the sugar with your fingers to prevent clumps in the final
product.</p>

<p>Add about 50ml of the cream to the sugar, and whisk&mdash;Again, this is just to prevent any clumping that may occur.  Add
the rest of the cream, and the cardamom pods, and bring everything to a light simmer&mdash;be careful that it doesn&rsquo;t come to
a full rolling boil.  Hopefully the gelatin has bloomed by now, so add that and let it simmer for another minute or two.
Pour the cream into whatever containers are appropriate, and let everything set in the fridge.  I recommend at least 3-4
hours, preferably overnight.</p>

<h2>Impressions</h2>

<ul>
<li>The apples came out way denser than I expected.  I&rsquo;ve never worked with pectin before, but I think the big mistake was
not accounting for the naturally occurring pectin in the fruit itself.  On hindsight, given how the most commonly sold
pectin is <em>apple pectin</em>, this was kind of a dunce cap moment.</li>
<li>The fruit was also way stronger and sweeter than I expected.  Next time I might dial down the sugar/vanilla in the
fruit, serve less of it, or just not combine it with something as delicate as panna cotta.  Haven&rsquo;t quite decided on
that one yet.</li>
<li>The panna cotta did not have gelatin problems (thankfully), but it was still a bit dense.  For the next try I might
cut the cream down with some milk, probably about 500ml cream to 100ml milk.</li>
<li>The cardamom also didn&rsquo;t come out as much as I would have liked.  It was just barely noticeable if tasting the cream
alone, so I think in the future a full 6 pods for 600ml liquid would be better.  Or even more if being served with
something as strong as a fruit compote.</li>
<li>Now that I think about it, maybe I&rsquo;d be better of cutting out the fruit and serving the panna cotta alone with some
sugar syrup that I&rsquo;ve steeped with cardamom pods.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raclette - Week 4, Things You Hated as a Kid]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/28/raclette-week-4-things-you-hated-as-a-kid/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T06:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/28/raclette-week-4-things-you-hated-as-a-kid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-gvTHKVq/0/L/DSC_2393-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Oneshots/i-gvTHKVq/0/L/DSC_2393-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Being your token asian immigrant, my experience with cheese was limited to Kraft slices and string cheese.  Now, there&rsquo;s
nothing wrong with good american cheese on a burger, but I hated string cheese with a burning passion&mdash;Especially when
my mom wanted me to eat some as a snack, citing something or other about calcium and strong bones.  <em>Pfft</em>.  Subsequent
exposure to the likes of cheez-whiz and store-brand grated parmesan really didn&rsquo;t help, and eventually I just dismissed
cheese as categorically unpleasant.</p>

<p>Since then I&rsquo;ve discovered the miracles of parmesan and mozzarella and even some more exotic ones like morbier and p'tit
basque.  But the first moment I realized that cheese could be excellent in its own right, and even be a major player in
a proper dish, was with raclette.</p>

<p>Raclette is commonly eaten in the swiss alps.  At its core, it&rsquo;s raclette cheese melted over boiled potatoes, commonly
served with cured meat and some pickles or vegetables in the root family; in the above photo, I went with the common
french pickle <em>cornichon</em> and some prosciutto.  The preparation is as easy as food gets: literally just boiling some
potatoes and melting some cheese (I recommend using a toaster oven or a broiler), and then arranging everything on a
plate.</p>

<p>But despite its simplicity, raclette had a large effect on expanding my worldview in food, so&hellip;  There it is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
