<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 52weeks | alex kuang]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/categories/52weeks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-06T13:52:24-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kuang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ramen Cake - Week 1, Eggs]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/06/ramen-cake-week-1-eggs/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-06T13:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkuang.github.io/blog/2014/01/06/ramen-cake-week-1-eggs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&mdash;Or, really ghetto okonomiyaki&hellip;</em></p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-zJ4NmjL/0/L/DSC_2315-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-zJ4NmjL/0/L/DSC_2315-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>It should come as no surprise to anyone that I&rsquo;m subscribed to
<a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/52weeksofcooking">/r/52weeksofcooking</a>.  The tl;dr is that each week, the subreddit chooses a
food &ldquo;theme&rdquo;&mdash;an ingredient, ethnicity, or some other idea&mdash;and users post dishes that they make according to the theme.
I&rsquo;ve always thought that the idea seemed like a lot of fun, so what better time to start than the new year?  If nothing
else, it makes good blog fodder.</p>

<p>Week 1&rsquo;s theme is eggs, which is a nice and easy start to this little series of experiments.  For this theme I chose
what I like to call &ldquo;ramen cake&rdquo;.  The idea is roughly the same as that of okonomiyaki&mdash;In fact, I got the idea after
watching the corresponding <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=od2YWgQmeo4">video</a> on Cooking With Dog (an excellent channel
in general, by the way).  It&rsquo;s a nice way to have ramen that doesn&rsquo;t come in a bowl of soup, and with the right
combination of fillings it could even be something approaching nutritious.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First, boil your ramen and set aside.  I recommend removing the ramen 30 seconds or so before it&rsquo;s fully cooked.  It&rsquo;ll
continue cooking in the pan later, and overcooking just results in mush&mdash;especially when freeze-dried noodles are
involved.  In the meantime, prepare any other toppings you need as well.  For the pictures in this post I used nong shim
ramen with some sardines and quickly stir-fried bok choy, but basically anything works.  Finally, beat about 3-4 large
eggs (depending on your preferences) until the yolks and whites are evenly incorporated.</p>

<p>Heat up a well-oiled, preferably non-stick, pan over medium-high heat.  Drop the eggs, and as soon as the bottom starts
cooking add the other ingredients and the ramen. Jostle it a bit as necessary to distribute everything, the leave it
alone to set.  Now is a great time to garnish with scallions and add some sauce&mdash;to keep it real, I like using oyster
sauce mixed with part of the ramen packet and a bit of peanut oil to adjust for viscosity.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-xtFsvCZ/0/L/DSC_2304-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-xtFsvCZ/0/L/DSC_2304-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>When the bottom has solidified enough to handle without disintegrating, it&rsquo;s ready to flip.  Just make sure that the egg
hasn&rsquo;t entirely cooked through yet&mdash;after the flip, we want it to drip downwards a bit and bind all of the ingredients
into one cohesive mass.  Also note that flipping can be a bit hit or miss sometimes, depending on a combination of
spatula size, pan skills, and luck.  One easy option is to cut it into pieces in the pan, and just flip the pieces
individually.</p>

<p>In this case, the culinary gods were with me, and I made the flip successfully:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-BNVnCJp/0/L/DSC_2307-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-BNVnCJp/0/L/DSC_2307-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>After the flip, let everything keep frying.  The goal here is to let the rest of the egg cook through and caramelize the
ramen a little bit along the way&mdash;Extra points if the bottom is slightly crispy, like so:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-M4rt2bc/0/L/DSC_2310-L.jpg">http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake/i-M4rt2bc/0/L/DSC_2310-L.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>While waiting for everything to cook, feel free to slather on more sauce.  Either way, it should be ready to be shoveled
into faces after a few minutes.</p>

<p>(Full gallery <a href="http://waffleparadox.smugmug.com/Food/Ramen-Cake">here</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
